<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-10-27T12:55:41-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bruin Sports Analytics</title><author><name>Bruin Sports Analytics</name></author><entry><title type="html">How ‘Mexican Style’ Came Back to Haunt GGG</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mexicanStyle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How 'Mexican Style' Came Back to Haunt GGG" /><published>2018-10-26T20:25:27-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-26T20:25:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mexicanStyle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mexicanStyle">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image11.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of a boxer comes down to not only how he can fight, but also how he can spread his brand. The man from Kazakhstan known around the world today as 'GGG' did not have traction in the popularity department for a massive portion of his fighting career. After an incredible amatuer career of 350 fights, Gennady Golovkin's professional career stalled for years due to promotional issues. In 2012, already 30 years of age, Golovkin finally decided to take his career to the United States under a new promoter. At the time, his record was 23-0 with 20 knockouts and he was already the WBA Middleweight Champion. Because of his dangerous record and lack of popularity, the top fighters in the division heavily avoided him for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many lower-tier middleweights were put in front of Golovkin and he dismantled one after the other, gaining favor with American fight fans as the &quot;people's champion&quot;. Of great importance is the fact that he began to have a massive following among Mexican fans as well, as his &quot;seek and destroy&quot; style and increasing knockout streak was reminiscent of the Mexican legend Julio Caesar Chavez. In other words, Golovkin finally had a promotional cornerstone. His promoter Tom Loeffler and trainer Abel Sanchez promoted the 'GGG' brand as 'Mexican Style' and promised action in every fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2015, Golovkin went from being a foreign delight to becoming the IBF, IBO, WBA, WBC, and Ring Magazine Unified Middleweight Champion of the World with one of the largest fan bases in North America. Phrases like 'Triple G', 'Mexican Style', and 'Big Drama Show' have become forever tied to his legacy. He lived as boxing's longest reigning champion of his time until September of this year, when he lost via decision to Mexican superstar Saul 'Canelo' Alvarez. It was the rematch of a fight that took place a year prior and ended in a draw. Both results are deemed controversial because 77% of ringside media scored the first fight for Golovkin and 98% of ringside media scored the second fight as either a draw or win for Golovkin. So how did he end up walking away with a draw and a loss on his record (now 38-1-1, 34 KO) instead? Perhaps it was simply corruption since Alvarez is the biggest money maker in prize fighting and has a history of judges being biased towards him in big fights. But more plausible is the idea that the very 'Mexican Style' brand that brought Golovkin to stardom was not accurate. His style is simply not that of a belligerent Mexican fighter and the numbers are here to prove it. This truth was made clear when he came out and fought a very cautious, non-'Mexican Style' fight against the highly talented Alvarez. Although Golovkin may have won both fights in the eyes of the fans, this uncharacteristic change of gameplan was likely and unfortunately seen as discomfort and failure in the eyes of the judges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Mexicans are not from Kazakhstan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to first have an idea of what Mexican style boxing really is. Technically, Mexican style fighting involves close proximity between fighters and emphasizes power punches, especially body work, over jabbing and distance. As much as Golovkin has been branded as a Mexican style fighter, his fighting simply does not line up with this definition. In fact, he controls distance and utilizes his jab more than any fighter in the entire sport:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golovkin lands more jabs than any man in boxing with 10.3 per round and does so at a higher percentage than any man boxing with a 31.6% connect rate. He has mastered the art of distance, using his ramrod jab to set up his offense. This is not something that is encompassed by the Mexican style as distance is relatively ignored and fighters prefer to exchange in the pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's also the less technical but more electric quality about Mexican style fighting: fighters are willing to take punishment to give it back. It involves a certain lack of respect for opponents' power that makes every event a fight rather than a boxing match. But the hardest puncher that Golovkin has faced, Canada's David Lemieux, ended up being the man against whom he took the least risks and fought the most carefully behind his jab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golovkin obliterated rational jabbing statistics across the board in his fight against Lemieux. He landed an unreal 21.3 jabs per round, four times the middleweight average at the time, with 47% connection. A staggering 65% of the punches he threw were jabs. So what does all of this jabbing mean? It means that while Golovkin is known for having a tremendous chin, he had absolutely no interest in a &quot;take two give one&quot; war against a big puncher when his ring generalship and length could dominate the fight. Nothing is being taken away from Golovkin's win; he brilliantly out-boxed Lemieux and his performance was a masterpiece. But brilliantly out-boxing someone is not nearly the Mexican solution to that problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that Golovkin still landed 58.8% of his power punches in the Lemieux fight when the middleweight average was 37.7%. Throughout this time he was also thought of as perhaps the biggest puncher in the division. His high power output and connection in virtually all of his fights is what continued to string him along as a Mexican Style destroyer, a false image that would create unnecessary expectations for him in his two historic fights against Canelo Alvarez.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image13.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 13&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Wars in the Desert&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canelo-Golovkin fights both took place in Las Vegas and generated tremendous interest as boxing's Super Bowl. Both delivered on their promises, but Golovkin was coming into each with an additional onus. Alvarez is a natural counter puncher so it was widely expected that Golovkin, the &quot;true Mexican style fighter&quot; of the two, would be the one to take the fight to Alvarez and press forward. But when push came to shove in the ring, he realized how dangerous Alvarez was and did what his instincts told him. Much to the surprise of experts and fans, 'Mexican Style' officially went out the window. Golovkin has a 2 inch reach and height advantage over Alvarez and, as it has been throughout this article, Golovkin's jab was a key ingredient to both fights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvarez is known for being a counter puncher with tremendous power. A Mexican Style fighter may normally walk such a man down and be willing to eat leather along the way as long as he can get inside and dish punishment back. But the most prolific jabber in boxing once again stuck to his true roots to win rounds in both fights. He did not need to get hit unnecessarily when he could wear Alvarez down with his jabbing and footwork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Golovkin jabbed, jabbed, and jabbed to set up his power punches, seemingly racking up points as the mere volume of his attack was tremendous. He didn't just out-jab Alvarez, he more than doubled Alvarez's landed jabs across both fights. And such a mismatch in the jab department was not Golovkin's only notable success. In both fights, he out-landed Canelo in total punches for the majority of rounds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a casual boxing fan were told that in two fights, one man would double the other's landed jabs and out-land the other outright in 18 of the 24 combined rounds, the casual fan would probably guess that this man handily won both fights. Yet only one of the six combined official judges had Gennady Golovkin winning. This is where the 'Mexican Style' image that Golovkin has built around himself over the years comes into play. Everyone, including the judges, was expecting Golovkin to make each fight a close distance firefight because that's the way he has been marketed. As great as Golovkin's jab and overall output were, he failed in the 'Mexican Style' department. As mentioned earlier, Mexican style fighting comes down to two technical aspects: power punches and body work. Golovkin was not able to beat Alvarez at either of those two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golovkin totally neglected attacking the body in both fights; only 6.2% of his landed power punches were downstairs. Alvarez, meanwhile, threw to the body much more vigorously, with 35% of his landed power shots going there. More notably, Golovkin, the man who was supposed to bring the power-punching fire, was actually out-landed by Alvarez in terms of power punches and was less efficient with his power punches as well, landing 33.5% of his shots while Alvarez landed 40.2%. Essentially, Alvarez, the Mexican man in the fight, also ended up having the more Mexican statistics across both fights and undermining Golovkin's signature 'Mexican Style'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to have had a direct effect on the official score cards, as there is a glaring trend about the way that each of the 24 combined rounds was scored (by the majority of the 3 judges in each round):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image12.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, judges were scoring rounds for the man who had the higher power punch percentage regardless of the volume of punches, jab, or ring generalship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appeared to most ringside observers and fans that Golovkin had done enough to win both fights because despite getting outlanded in power shots and never hitting the body, he often controlled the tempo and did so with incredible punch output. But the thing that seems to have mattered to the official judges more than anything else is: &quot;Who is fighting more like a Mexican?&quot;, a question that only entered their heads in the first place because of how much 'Mexican Style' had become entangled with the story of the fight over the years. In their eyes, here is what happened: A man who has built his career around being a Mexican style fighter that comes forward and attacks relentlessly was unable to do so because Canelo Alvarez was dictating the fights and making him afraid and uncomfortable in the ring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's sound logic if Golovkin was ever actually a Mexican style fighter, but he's not and the numbers have made it quite clear. The fact is that Golovkin is a high quality attacker who had an extensive amateur career for years with an Eastern European style based on distance and calculation. He came to the United States hoping to make the most of his incredible boxing ability and after a string of knockouts against lower-tier opponents, fans across the continent fell in love with the idea of 'GGG': the true Mexican style monster who traps opponents on the ropes and finishes them. But he was just a fighter who had never yet had truly elite-level opposition. When the elite opponent was finally put in front of him, the undefeated champ dug deep into his bag of tricks and amateur pedigree to outbox the man, but it unfortunately didn't come across that way to the judges; they had expectations for him that stemmed from false advertising and were never realistic. He is the greatest middleweight of this era, but like many people who go to Vegas, Gennady Golovkin walked in with high expectations and ended up leaving empty handed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: CompuBox numbers via HBO Boxing and Sports Illustrated, mmafighting.com, sportsviewlondon.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kathir Ilango</name></author><summary type="html">The success of a boxer comes down to not only how he can fight, but also how he can spread his brand. The man from Kazakhstan known around the world today as 'GGG' did not have traction in the popularity department for a massive portion of his fighting career. After an incredible amatuer career of 350 fights, Gennady Golovkin's professional career stalled for years due to promotional issues. In 2012, already 30 years of age, Golovkin finally decided to take his career to the United States under a new promoter. At the time, his record was 23-0 with 20 knockouts and he was already the WBA Middleweight Champion. Because of his dangerous record and lack of popularity, the top fighters in the division heavily avoided him for years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vegas Golden Knights: The Most Successful Expansion Team in NHL History</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vegasGK" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vegas Golden Knights: The Most Successful Expansion Team in NHL History" /><published>2018-06-08T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-08T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vegasGK</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vegasGK">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Associated Press&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t supposed to happen. The first major professional sports team to ever grace the city of Las Vegas wasn’t supposed to be this good. Hockey wasn’t meant to be played in the desert. A team full of disposable parts and cast-offs wasn’t supposed to mesh this well together. It must be a fluke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vegas Golden Knights have been bombarded with these narratives all season, brushing them aside with every milestone attained, every record broken. They are for real. If finishing with 109 points atop the Pacific division and fifth in the league didn’t convince you, their playoff run sure did. Stanley Cup Finalists. Western Conference Champions. Not a bad inaugural season for the NHL’s newest franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one saw this coming in the offseason of last year. Preseason odds given to Vegas to win the Stanley Cup ranged from 300-1 to 500-1. Almost every expert, media personality, and journalist had the team as a cellar dweller who would be vying for a favorable position in the draft lottery come April; not cruising to home-ice advantage in the playoffs. Ironically, the city of Las Vegas was facing one of its biggest potential losses in betting history as the Knights were on the brink of a Cup win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To all the fans who stuck with them from the beginning, through all the adversity… yeah, no. The unprecedented success of the Golden Knights has brought to the forefront a recurring theme: Sports aren’t always fair. Kevin Durant joining the Golden State Warriors. The college football playoff selection process when it comes to non-power-5 teams (read: UCF). The list goes on. Do you think fans of the St. Louis Blues, who have never won a Cup and haven’t made it to the Finals in 48 years, have a soft spot for Vegas? Or fans of the Florida Panthers, who have gone 21 years without winning a single playoff series?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how one of the greatest sports stories of this millennium unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to look at is roster composition. Although teams were not able to protect as many players as in previous expansion drafts, general manager George McPhee didn’t exactly have a cupboard full of exciting star talent to choose from. Each team was allowed to protect seven forwards, three defensemen, and one goaltender, or eight skaters regardless of position and one goaltender. There were some minor rules such as the requirement to expose at least two forwards and one defenseman who played 40 or more games in the previous season, but nothing that would make an organization have to give up a perennial superstar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mock drafts had the team chalk full of fringe top-6 forwards, borderline top-4 defensemen and a slew of young but unproven wildcards. And that is how the actual draft appeared to go down last summer. Pundits lamented the mediocre, uninspiring collection of players. Sure, the future looked bright with some exciting prospects and draft picks to develop in coming years. But there was no indication that this team would be competing for a Stanley Cup in their first season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enter an offense that would see the emergence of new, elite talent, a goaltender with a history of success playing the best hockey of his career, and a coach whose system is very much compatible with the ‘speed and skill’ style of the modern NHL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Karlsson turned into an elite goal scorer seemingly overnight. He failed to top 10 goals in each of his first three seasons in the NHL with Anaheim and Columbus. Moves to Vegas and pots 43, third in the league behind only Alex Ovechkin, one of the best scorers of all time, and young phenom Patrik Laine. Even worse for Columbus, they traded Vegas two high draft picks to select Karlsson (and take on a bad contract to provide salary cap relief).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many on the Vegas roster who had breakout seasons took advantage of increased responsibility, leading to more ice time, powerplay time, etc. Karlsson played nearly 19 minutes per game, on the first powerplay unit, compared to 13-14 minutes and almost no PP time with Columbus. This is a recipe for increased production, regardless of the player. A 23.4 shooting percentage is unsustainable, so some type of regression is expected next year. But scoring 40+ goals in a season doesn’t happen by accident. Karlsson is one of the top young players in the game today and a building block for Vegas going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Marchessault was similarly involved in a trade that would help Florida clear out a bad contract. In hindsight, that did not turn out so well for the Panthers. Every dollar counts in the salary cap era, and it’s clear that teams have made it a top priority to manage their money. Vegas took advantage of this because they have plenty of cap space; no superstars means no reason to sign anyone to albatross contracts. Karlsson is a restricted free agent and is due to get paid this offseason, but they locked up Marchessault to a six year, $5 million per deal that is looking like it could be an absolute steal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Vegas was competitive right off the bat. By midseason mark, they created a sizable gap from first to second in the Pacific and never relinquished it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Golden Knights boasted a record of 29-10-2 at T-Mobile Arena on the Las Vegas strip. Only Winnipeg and Pittsburgh had more wins at home. The theory of ‘Vegas Flu’ has been tossed around, where visiting teams would succumb to the atmosphere/distractions of the city on nights before playing the Knights. But nearly every game has been sold out and their 103.9% average capacity is fourth in the league. Ticket prices are not cheap either. Extravagant pregame shows, boisterous locals, and the support of a city riding a wave of anomalous success has created significant home ice advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advanced hockey analytics paint a favorable picture of the Knights as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scope of quality hockey statistics is not nearly at the level of basketball, and nowhere close to baseball. The sport is more fluid than either of those two, and parallels soccer in its low scoring nature. How do you judge a team’s overall strength? Goals scored and against is the obvious answer, but there are only a few hundred of those per team, per season. Largely influenced by random fluctuations and ‘puck luck’, the sample size over a single year is not enough to draw definitive conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of looking at goals, shots (on goal, blocked, missed net) have been used as a proxy for puck possession. Generally, if a team has more shot attempts for than against, they probably have the puck more. The graph above uses scoring chances, which are shot attempts from dangerous scoring locations. 5v5 indicates these are even strength scoring chances. Further adjustments such as taking into account the score of the game (a team with the lead tends to sit back and defend it, hence the trailing team will get a skewed percentage of chances) can also be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlighted regions of the graphic above are top-5 and bottom-5 indicators. While Vegas does not lie in any of the blue, they are in the fourth quadrant (‘Good’), generating more scoring chances per 60 minutes and allowing less than league average. It’s important to not put too much stock into any one statistic. Calgary and Carolina look like superb teams here, but neither made the postseason (due to a combination of mediocre goaltending and scoring ineptitude).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A record of 20-6-3 against Pacific division rivals foreshadowed good things to come in the playoffs. The overwhelming factor in Vegas’ run to the Stanley Cup Final was the play of their goaltender, Marc-Andre Fleury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleury has been the face of the franchise from the beginning. After losing his starting job to the younger Matt Murray in Pittsburgh, he was clearly the best available netminder up for selection. The first overall pick in the 2003 Entry Draft, ‘The Flower’ has enjoyed a decorated career. Three Stanley Cups, 404 wins (11th all time). He posted career highs in save percentage and goals against average in Vegas’ inaugural season. A concussion caused him to miss two months early in the year or he might’ve topped his previous high of 42 wins. Remarkably, the Golden Knights hardly missed a beat despite being down to their fourth string goalie at one point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first playoff series in franchise history would come against Los Angeles: A veteran team that has won two Cups in recent years, and usually turns it up a notch in the postseason. It was a goaltending duel from start to finish. Kings goalie Jonathan Quick, 2012 Conn Smythe winner, did everything he could to give his team a chance to win. Unfortunately for him, the Kings offense scored 3 goals in 4 games and were shutout twice by Fleury in a sweep for Vegas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up was San Jose. Okay, this was a real playoff team. Coming of a sweep of their own against Anaheim, the Sharks will put Vegas in their place. Nope. The Knights jumped out to a 4-0 lead just 12 minutes into the series, completely outclassing the Sharks 7-0 in Game 1. It would go six games, but on the back of Marc-Andre Fleury, Vegas proved too much for San Jose to overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Western Conference Final would pit them against the Jets. The Pacific Division was weak this year; this was the true Cup contender that would end the Knights Cinderella run. Negative. Vegas won four straight after dropping Game 1 in Winnipeg. Fleury did not allow more than two goals in games 2 through 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miraculously, an expansion team was heading to the Stanley Cup Finals. Only the Washington Capitals, a franchise with a long history of playoff disappointment, stood in their way. They were not favorites to come out of the East, and Vegas had defeated them in both matchups during the regular season. Surely the Knights were destined to achieve the unthinkable and make quick work of them…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny how sports work sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleury fell back down to Earth. Heading into the SCF, he was on track to have the best playoff run by a goaltender in terms of save percentage since the 2005 lockout (at least 10GP). His numbers fell off a cliff against Washington, although he was hardly to blame for the series loss. Vegas’ defense was carved up by the Capitals attack, leaving Fleury out to dry. Caps goalie Braden Holtby stole the spotlight. Evgeny Kuznetsov had the most productive spring since Evgeni Malkin and Sidney Crosby of the ’08-09 Penguins. Alex Ovechkin, starved of postseason success throughout his career, played inspired hockey to lead Washington to its first Stanley Cup in franchise history. There are very few people in the entirety of the sports world who deserved a championship more than him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this incredible run by Vegas did not get its storybook ending, their inaugural season was an overwhelming success. They’ve accomplished more in one year than many teams have in decades. With a core of young studs, a franchise goaltender, and plenty of cap space, it will be an exciting summer and future for the Golden Knights.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joey Maurer</name></author><summary type="html">The Associated PressThis wasn’t supposed to happen. The first major professional sports team to ever grace the city of Las Vegas wasn’t supposed to be this good. Hockey wasn’t meant to be played in the desert. A team full of disposable parts and cast-offs wasn’t supposed to mesh this well together. It must be a fluke.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BSA Exclusive: Our Journey Through Research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/pred_NBA_salaries_journey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BSA Exclusive: Our Journey Through Research" /><published>2018-06-03T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-03T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/pred_NBA_salaries_journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pred_NBA_salaries_journey">&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Goal of this Article&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this article, we hope to detail our process as members of Bruin Sports Analytics to work towards getting a well-done research paper completed, with guidance given by our club advisor, Professor Almohalwas of the UCLA Statistics department. We wish to detail our journey, and all the lessons we have taken from each one to move us closer to completing our desired task. In hopes of creating a paper worthy of being published in an official sports analytics journal, we have decided to take more time in working towards our final result. However, we have decided to write this extended article to provide a checkpoint of where currently stand in hopes for others to get inspired to do research as an undergrad, and learn more about the interesting attempts we have tried to solve our problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;Predicting NBA Free Agent Salaries&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Introduction&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Relevance&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Front offices and player agents alike would benefit from a model that can assess a free agent’s true value given the player’s performance in an array of statistical categories. In 2016, teams were clearly unsure how much free agents were actually worth due to the increased salary cap (it increased by over $24 million). As the salary cap continues to increase with the influx of more league revenue from television contracts, this problem will continue. Our research attempts to lay the groundwork for a tool to accurately gauge the true worth of a player’s on-court contributions in relation to the salary cap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Background&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More so than any of the other big four American sports, the NBA is a superstar-driven league. Every championship team this millennium aside from the 2004 Detroit Pistons and the 2011 Dallas Mavericks have featured at least two bona-fide superstars. This trend has been accentuated by the 2010-2014 Miami Heat featuring three superstars and the current Golden State Warriors featuring four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far the easiest way to acquire superstars is through signing a superstar through free agency, which requires no sacrifice of time or assets except money of course. The player and his new team need only agree to a maximum contract, without the team compensating his previous team. Thus, signing free agent superstars is, on paper, the easiest way to get a superstar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NBA CBA designates a salary cap and a maximum contract, which complicate the signing of multiple high-salary superstars while keeping a strong roster of complementary players. This leaves little to no room for overpaying players - every dollar counts. Thus, there is a need for a model that can analyze statistics to accurately predict any player’s appropriate salary for the next season, a tool which can help teams avoid overspending and help free agents know their clients’ worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Understanding Contracts and Free Agency&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First round draft picks enter the league on two-year guaranteed contracts dictated by the CBA and its “rookie scale”. The rookie scale outlines how first rounders’ pay is based on a range tied to the salary cap in their draft year. This means players on rookie contracts are paid based on draft position, NOT on-court performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rookie scale&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rookie scale makes players on rookie contracts irrelevant to our research, and thus we removed these players from our data. Players like Donovan Mitchell (13th pick) and Kyle Kuzma (27th pick) have greatly outperformed their draft positions’ salaries while other players (busts) would underperform. Either way, both types of players would damage our model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Methodology&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Organizing the Data&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We obtained player metrics (both basic box-score and advanced numbers) from basketball-reference.com for players from the 2013-2014 through 2016-17 season. These metrics included the player’s Per Game and Advanced statistics, as these statistics do an adequate job of detailing the skill of a particular player. Each player was matched with average salary data for the corresponding player for the next season via spotrac.com. Our reason for using the next season’s salary was so that the model would be trained to predict player salary in the following season based on their performance in the previous season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we had a dataframe of four seasons, we decided to optimize our data to focus our attention on players who were relevant over the course of an NBA season. Thus, we cleaned the data by removing duplicates and players who played less than 25 games in a season. These are generally players who are either injured or do not have much impact in games. In the case that a player was injured during the season, it would not make sense to predict their salary based on the performance from a season in which they were injured. Also, players that are generally unproductive when they are on the floor often bounce around teams on shorter contracts and thus have a greater variability in salaries over seasons. Cases like these could affect the model unfavorably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another step taken to clean the data for the model was to take out players on rookie contracts. As stated earlier, when a player is on a rookie contract, their salaries are set in stone for a certain amount of years. This means that predicting a player’s salary while on a rookie contract would be futile, since their salaries are set in stone for a fixed amount of years after they are drafted, and are not based on performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we had to re-examine the goal of this project, which was to create a statistically valid model that could predict NBA player salaries for next season, the 2018-19 season. To do this, we decided to train the model on predicting player salaries for the 2017-18 season based on player performance in the 2016-17 season. We found that using the larger dataset of data from the previous seasons (2013-16) posed some issues in our methodology, namely in that the “local model” with just one season’s worth of data was more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Interesting Notes&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the data had been prepared, one of the first statistics we looked at was whether there was a significant difference in terms of average salary by player position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;By Position&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To our surprise, after running a One-way ANOVA test comparing whether the average salary between groups was different, we concluded no significant difference between position thus did not add this factor into our multiple linear regression model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor we explored was if playing for a specific team impacted the type of salary a player is expected to get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;By Team&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After performing another another ANOVA test, there was a significant difference in terms of average salary by Team. However, after performing Post-hoc Tukey’s test to discover which pair was significant and adding that to our model, it also proved insignificant compared to our other variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;An Attempt to Create our Own Statistic&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the other aspects that we worked on was creating a new statistic that we could eventually use in our regression model. The goal was to create a metric that would quantify how much a player was overachieving or underachieving with respect to their contract. Our belief was that a player who was underpaid would eventually see a pay raise in their next contract and a player that was underperforming would more than likely have to take a pay cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in creating this new metric was to place the players into salary brackets according to how much they were being paid. We worked with the 2016-2017 player data and used their next year’s salary  (2017-2018 season) to place them into salary brackets. We chose to have eight different salary brackets, where bracket eight represented players who received a max level contract, which was over 21% of the salary cap. The lowest bracket belonged to players on a minimum contract and from there the brackets went up in increments of roughly 3-4% of the overall cap. The following chart displays the distribution of players in each of the eight salary brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Salary Bracket&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After assigning each of the players in the 2016-2017 season into a salary bracket, the next step was to group the players into clusters based on their performance. We used the K-Means clustering algorithm to create the groups. We chose to use a k-value of 8, because we wanted to be consistent with the number of salary brackets that we had previously created. After running the K-Means algorithm, each player was assigned into a performance cluster from one to eight. The eighth performance cluster represented the top performing players in the league and not surprisingly contained players like Lebron James, Stephen Curry, and Russell Westbrook. The chart below highlights the number of players in each of the respective performance clusters based on the 2016-2017 player data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Performance Cluster&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After assigning each player a performance cluster and a salary bracket, we had the information needed in order to create our new metric, which we called over/under. The formula for over/under was the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;over/under = performance cluster - salary bracket&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A positive over/under score meant that the player was outperforming their contract and was in line for a pay raise. Conversely, a negative over/under score represented a player that was underachieving and was most likely due for a decrease in pay in their next contract. The chart below shows a few players from our 2016-2017 dataset and their over/under score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/table1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Prediction Table&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown, Lebron James, who belongs to both the highest performance cluster and highest salary bracket, has an over/under score of 0 which means that he should see similar pay in his future contract. In the cases of the Isaiah Thomas, who was an MVP candidate, and Will Barton, a sixth man of the year candidate, both had some of the highest over/under scores, which makes sense because they both significantly outperformed with respect to their contract. Joakim Noah achieved a negative score because of his limited production even though he belonged to such a high salary bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, after adding the over/under statistic into our regression model, we received an R^2 value of 82%, which was one of the best models that we had produced. However, the issue was that the over/under statistic relied on know the next year’s player salary, which was not possible if you were working with the most current NBA season. One way that we will use to solve this issue is by scaling the years back when calculating a player’s salary bracket. This would mean that for example with the 2016-2017 player data we would use the 2016-2017 player salary and not the 2017-2018 player salary. We also tried to use just the performance cluster metric for each player in a model and see if that had any statistical significance, but unfortunately it did not. Going forward there are numerous aspects that we can tune such as changing the number of performance clusters/salary brackets and scaling the salary years back in order to create a new metric that may improve our eventual regression model. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Final Variable Selection &amp; Model Creation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we decided a multiple linear regression model would do the job in predicting average salary given a combination of various statistics, we had to require our model follow a large number of assumptions in order draw adequate conclusions. To begin with, we had to ensure that the player salaries were as close to normally distributed as possible. Average salary’s Gaussian Kernel Density estimation shape was greatly skewed but after applying the square root transformation, the assumption of normality was satisfied. Had this transformation not been applied, the standard errors would have been biased leading to faulty conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we took a look at how the variables correlated with each other to better understand relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Correlation Table&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When analyzing data as large as this, it is vital to view how the other statistics interact with average salary (the far right column). Next, for the variables which correlate greatly, you need to check how they correlate with each other. By checking for possible multicollinearity, we can avoid adding variables into our model which give the same information and just choose the one who provides us with the most information. For instance, the number of free throws made per game and free throw percentage tell nearly the same story in how a player performs at the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we decided to use a powerful function within R, regsubsets, for regression subset selection which basically finds the best combination of variables at various subset sizes in terms of a given criterion. We decided Adjusted R^2 was an adequate criteria to base our ability to explain average salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic7.png&quot; alt=&quot;regsubsets&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our task then became selecting the subset which provides the highest adjust R^2 and cutting the model down while taking VIF into account. The variance inflation factor of a variable gives us a sign of multicollinearity which we obviously want to avoid from our model. Finally, we worked our model down while keeping VIF of each variable under 5 to obtain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic8.png&quot; alt=&quot;regsubsets&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We noticed that Minutes played per game, Win Shares, Steals per game, True Shooting %, Games played in the season, and offensive rebound % proved the most significant variables in predicting average salary according to this model. When checking for validity of a model, diagnostics must be examined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic9.png&quot; alt=&quot;regsubsets&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four plots prove to us that our assumptions of normality and constant variance are all satisfied meaning that the conclusions we draw from the model can be taken seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model is nowhere near perfect yet, it has a low adjusted R^2, and some of the coefficients are negative when intuitively should be positive. We are still in progress to rework the regression model to raise our adjusted R^2 and explore different interactions between variables. However, we were able to satisfy all model assumption which at least gives a checkpoint to build off of as we begin to tune or rework this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Results&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based off this model for predicting 17-18 salaries, we decided to approximate what free agents for the 18-19 season should earn. Since the salary cap for the 18-19 season is so close to the 17-18 season, we decided to reuse this model to create approximate predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some top performers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/table2.png&quot; alt=&quot;top performers&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editor's Picks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/table3.png&quot; alt=&quot;editor picks&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not too shabby, but there’s so much more to go with the project if we want to improve our accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Next Steps&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently working with the professor on obtaining a model using Principal Component Analysis, and also exploring unsupervised methods to help create predictions on data with no attached labels. We also will try to incorporate more statistics such as offensive and defensive rating to hopefully give us more insight into detailing what a player is worth. Additionally, we will working to create extra statistics, such as our performance cluster and another which takes into account previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope to one day predict full contracts with contract length attached, and possibly a web application for people to easily check a player’s worth in terms of what they deserve in salary against what they are currently earning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This piece was just an update of where we are at so far, and to hopefully lay out a foundation on which we or others can build upon. All of our data from 2011-2017 of player’s perGame, advStats, salaries, free agent lists, etc is all our our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/konnermacias/Free-Agents&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; for you to use. Working towards getting this project completed has been an extremely rewarding experience, allowing us to get closer with our club members and working with our club advisory. It is highly recommended if you ever want to work towards solving a difficult problem and doing something you’re passionate about.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Konner Macias</name></author><summary type="html">With this article, we hope to detail our process as members of Bruin Sports Analytics to work towards getting a well-done research paper completed, with guidance given by our club advisor, Professor Almohalwas of the UCLA Statistics department. We wish to detail our journey, and all the lessons we have taken from each one to move us closer to completing our desired task. In hopes of creating a paper worthy of being published in an official sports analytics journal, we have decided to take more time in working towards our final result. However, we have decided to write this extended article to provide a checkpoint of where currently stand in hopes for others to get inspired to do research as an undergrad, and learn more about the interesting attempts we have tried to solve our problem.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Early Overachievers: The 2018 Oakland Athletics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/oakAs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Early Overachievers: The 2018 Oakland Athletics" /><published>2018-05-30T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-30T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/oakAs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/oakAs">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/cover.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A's Teammates&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Mercury News&lt;/i&gt;; from L to R, Matt Chapman, Matt Olson, and Marcus Semien&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the 2018 MLB season, many experts thought the Oakland Athletics would once again sport one of the worst records in baseball. According to Baseball Prospectus, the Athletics were projected to have a 76-86 record this year, which would be a miniscule improvement from their 75-87 record last year. The oddsmakers at Bovada had even lower expectations for the squad, as the over/under for their win total was set at 74.5. Given that the team has been in the American League West cellar for three years straight, even the most optimistic A’s fans had to acknowledge that a playoff appearance might not be in order for at least a couple of years. So, you can’t really blame all the people who slept on the A’s going into the season, especially since Oakland didn’t do much over the offseason to improve themselves. But, the A’s have given their fans some hope with their impressive start to the season; after the first 54 games of the campaign, Oakland stands at 28-26, good for a .519 win percentage. People around the game might be surprised at this kind of run, but when looking at the roster makeup and the major statistics on both sides of the ball, one can better understand why the A’s are experiencing this kind of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/pic1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stephen Piscotty&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;MLB.com; Stephen Piscotty&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/pic2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jonathon Lucroy&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;MLB: Jonathon Lucroy&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a team not in contention going into the 2018 year, the Oakland Athletics didn’t make any splashes with trades or free agency. As a result, much of the team from last year has been kept intact, as only a few moves were made here and there. First of all, the A’s traded away first baseman Ryon Healy to the Seattle Mariners in order to give emerging youngster Matt Olson more playing time. As a result, Olson has performed admirably as a starter, as the 6’5” power hitter has carried the momentum of his 24-home run effort last year into 2018. Then, the A’s traded for St. Louis Cardinals’ outfielder Stephen Piscotty to bolster their outfield depth, which was important given they were bringing up guys from Triple-A to fill those spots last year. Later on, they traded away struggling pitcher Jesse Hahn to the Kansas City Royals and received a dependable reliever in Ryan Buchter as a result. And in March, Oakland signed a quality catcher in Jonathan Lucroy, who was a hot item on the trade market not too long ago due to his 2014 and 2016 All-Star credentials. And just before the season, the A’s brought on Trevor Cahill and Brett Anderson, both former A’s, to solidify the starting rotation. Nothing flashy, but Oakland filled a couple of key needs heading into 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick look at the depth chart gives us an idea of the main contributors this year. First, the newly-acquired Lucroy has been the predominant starter at catcher for Oakland, and his presence behind the plate has arguably calmed the nerves of the young pitching staff. For the infield, Olson has been the guy at 1st base, Jed Lowrie has been excellent as the starting 2nd baseman, Marcus Semien has been stationed at shortstop, and Matt Chapman has played stellar defense at third base. In the outfield, it’s mainly been some combination of Matt Joyce, Dustin Fowler, Stephen Piscotty, and Chad Pinder. Joyce has played in left field for the most part, Fowler has been in center field, and Piscotty has been in right field. Pinder is a utility guy, so he has filled in for any of the three aforementioned players when they had an off day. In the designated hitter slot, Khris Davis has gotten his fair share of hacks as the team’s best power hitter, but a recent leg injury has sidelined him for the past few games. Thankfully, he should be back this week. Finally, the pitching rotation has been arguably the weakest link for Oakland recently, as an array of injuries has forced quite a bit of shuffling to occur. As it stands now, the five main starters are ace Sean Manaea, Daniel Mengden, Trevor Cahill, Daniel Gossett, and Frankie Montas. This is a relatively young rotation, as Cahill is the elder statesman at 30 years of age, while the others are all either 25 or 26 years old. They have held it together up to this point, but we’ll have to see if the A’s staff can maintain this level of consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Athletics struggled to win last year, they have bounced back in 2018 with a winning record so far. This success is largely due to the offensive efforts of the squad, as young guns and veterans alike have enjoyed their fair share of triumphs at the plate. As a team, the Athletics rank 6th in the American League (AL) with 66 home runs and have a slugging percentage of .412, good for 7th in the AL. Clearly, these metrics demonstrate the offensive power of the A’s. After all, five A’s players rank in the top 50 in the AL with at least 7 home runs on the year: outfielder Khris Davis (ranked 8th with 13), 2nd baseman Jed Lowrie (ranked 24th with 9), 3rd baseman Matt Chapman / 1st baseman Matt Olson (both tied for 32nd with 8), and utility player Mark Canha (ranked 43rd with 7). In particular, Lowrie has had quite the year so far; he possesses a .303 batting average, good for 14th in the AL, and he has 38 runs batted in (RBIs), tied with Davis for 5th in the AL. And in terms of hits, shortstop Marcus Semien and Lowrie are tied for 9th with 63 apiece. Clearly, Oakland has the firepower to hit with the best offensive teams in the league, and their ability to do so has been why they have a winning record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;RBI Leaders&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is a chart detailing some of the RBI leaders in the American League thus far in the 2018 season. Manny Machado and J.D. Martinez are tied for the league lead with 44 apiece, but A’s teammates Khris Davis and Jed Lowrie aren’t too far behind them. With 38 RBIs each, Lowrie and Davis are tied for 5th in this category, which makes for a formidable pairing in the heart of the Oakland lineup. In fact, they have the 3rd-highest combined RBI total for two teammates in the league, trailing a couple of Red Sox pairs for that honor. Now, Lowrie and Davis aren’t exactly your household names when you think of Major League Baseball. No, you’d probably think of reigning AL MVP Jose Altuve, defending NL MVP Giancarlo Stanton, and Future Hall-of-Famer Albert Pujols. Well, Davis and Lowrie have clearly outproduced these big names in the RBI department so far, as the closest player to them, Altuve, comes up a full 9 RBIs short of the Athletics’ duo. Comparing small market players like Lowrie and Davis to the big guns emphasizes the fact that Oakland’s offense has been underrated this year, but if the A’s can continue to produce at this level, maybe they’ll get some attention from national networks like ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Assist Leaders&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, the Athletics’ defense has improved markedly from past seasons. The A’s have been one of the worst defensive teams in the AL for the past couple of years, as they have been notorious for committing tons of errors and not converting simple putouts. Part of that was the youth of the team, but many of these guys now have some major league experience, which has presumably given them confidence to field better. The numbers from this year suggest that they are an above-average defensive team. First of all, it’s quite impressive that Oakland ranks 1st in the AL in total assists with 580, a full 38 more than the Texas Rangers, the next-highest total. Even the league average, 493, is almost 100 assists less than what the A’s have tallied so far. Moreover, they rank 5th in the AL in putouts with 1499 and are 3rd in the league in defensive efficiency ratio at .705. This statistic is basically a measure of how likely a team’s defense is to convert a ball in play into an out. So, the A’s have been able to do this roughly 70% of the time. Plus, some individual performers have stood out on defense. For one, 3rd baseman Matt Chapman has been a consistent playmaker, as his 144 assists are good for 3rd place in the league among all fielders. Also, 1st baseman Matt Olson has a tremendous 530 putouts to lead the league in that category; not only is he making plays, but he has started every game for the A’s thus far. Additionally, he sports a relatively high fielding percentage of .995, as he has made only 3 errors on the year. Overall, these defensive strides have allowed the pitching staff to relax and get to the dugout even faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the Oakland pitchers, the A’s slingers have held their own in the home-run era of Major League Baseball. After all, they rank 5th in the AL with an impressive 3.94 Earned Run Average (ERA), a vast improvement from their 4.67 ERA from 2017. Their pitchers also do a good job of not giving away too many walks; Oakland has only issued 153 free passes, the 4th-lowest total in the AL. As for individual performances, the two headliners in the starting rotation have been youngsters Sean Manaea and Daniel Mengden. Manaea, the decided ace of the staff, has a no-hitter to his name against the dangerous Boston Red Sox from this past April. And amongst qualified AL starters, he ranks 15th with a 3.34 ERA and 12th in innings pitched with 70.0. Perhaps his most impressive stat is the low amount of walks and hits he gives up per inning (WHIP), as his 0.96 WHIP is 6th among AL starters. Similarly, Daniel Mengden’s early success has also yielded some stellar statistics. In fact, he bettered Manaea in ERA, as his 2.85 figure is 9th in the AL, while he matched Manaea with a 0.96 WHIP. It’s nice that Oakland can depend on these two workhorses for quality starts, especially since the rotation as a whole has been prone to injury. As for the bullpen, Blake Treinen has assumed the role of closer ever since he was traded from the Washington Nationals last year. Although he struggled quite a bit in D.C., he has thrived as a hard-throwing reliever in Oakland thus far. Through 27 innings pitched in 2018, Treinen has accumulated an ERA of 1.00, and opponents are batting a mere .196 against him. Plus, he is tied for 4th in AL in saves, as he has converted on 12 out of 14 save opportunities. If Oakland can minimize any kind of regression from their current efforts, then they will give their offense a better chance to win games for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Oakland Athletics have overachieved in the first third of the 2018 season, we still have to remember there is a ton of baseball left to play. Major questions still loom over the Oakland pitching staff with respect to both health and consistency, and they need to get themselves together for Oakland to have a realistic shot at a wild card berth. We know the offense is pretty solid, but as they say, defense wins championships, so the A’s offensive firepower will be a moot point if the pitching unravels. But at this point, a fanbase that last experienced the playoffs in 2014 is glad that their team is giving them hope to believe that 2018 will be a successful season. Only time will tell if Oakland will clinch a playoff berth or wallow in the cellar of the competitive AL West.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;*Stats updated as of 5/29&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: athletics.mlb.com, Baseballprospectus.com, Baseball-reference.com, mlb.com/stats&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Veroulis</name></author><summary type="html">The Mercury News; from L to R, Matt Chapman, Matt Olson, and Marcus SemienAt the beginning of the 2018 MLB season, many experts thought the Oakland Athletics would once again sport one of the worst records in baseball. According to Baseball Prospectus, the Athletics were projected to have a 76-86 record this year, which would be a miniscule improvement from their 75-87 record last year. The oddsmakers at Bovada had even lower expectations for the squad, as the over/under for their win total was set at 74.5. Given that the team has been in the American League West cellar for three years straight, even the most optimistic A’s fans had to acknowledge that a playoff appearance might not be in order for at least a couple of years. So, you can’t really blame all the people who slept on the A’s going into the season, especially since Oakland didn’t do much over the offseason to improve themselves. But, the A’s have given their fans some hope with their impressive start to the season; after the first 54 games of the campaign, Oakland stands at 28-26, good for a .519 win percentage. People around the game might be surprised at this kind of run, but when looking at the roster makeup and the major statistics on both sides of the ball, one can better understand why the A’s are experiencing this kind of success.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does Defense Really Win Championships? An In-Depth Analysis of the NBA Playoffs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/defChamp" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does Defense Really Win Championships? An In-Depth Analysis of the NBA Playoffs" /><published>2018-05-22T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-22T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/defChamp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/defChamp">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2004 Pistons&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Jed Jacobsohn/Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Introduction&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 2 minutes left on the clock, Richard Hamilton stepped up to the free throw line.  He dribbled the ball a few times and calmly knocked down both shots to seal one of the most stunning upsets in playoff history.  The Detroit Pistons had defeated the heavily favored Los Angeles Lakers to become the 2004 NBA Champions.  Hardly anyone could have predicted that this team would overcome the combined talents of Kobe Bryant and Shaquille O’Neal along with the brilliance of Phil Jackson.  Most analysts give credit to the outstanding defense the Pistons displayed.  Though their offense just placed 7th, this Pistons team had the best ranked defense throughout the playoffs and actually had the highest average defensive rating in postseason history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic1.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Top off/def teams&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;*Adjusted for Pace (Defensive rating is reversed scored)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was largely due in part because of their defensive stalwart Ben Wallace, who averaged 19.8 rebounds, 2.7 steals, and 3.4 blocks per 100 possessions.  Clearly, defense was a significant aspect of the playoffs that year, but since then, the game has started to trend in another direction.  Nowadays, there has been a resurgence in robust offenses as shown by both the 2017 Warriors and Cavaliers who contributed substantially to the recent spike in average offensive rating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;avg off/def per year&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even with this new style of fast-paced basketball taking over, can one say with certainty that a relentless offense is more valuable than a resilient defense?  Or even, is there a way to quantify the impact of defensive prowess versus offensive tenacity on a team’s postseason success?  Using comprehensive data from previous playoffs, we can explore all the possible answers to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Dataset&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this analysis, I scraped 32 seasons of playoff statistics (1986-2017) from basketball-reference.com giving me 512 instances of teams to work with.  The data used were the playoff averages of each statistic.  The reason I excluded the regular season is because playoff basketball creates a highly competitive atmosphere.  Each possession is much more valuable and players exert an exceptional level of effort when the season is on the line.  Also, the goal is to measure the components of a win within the scope of the playoffs so it would be erroneous to use regular season data which includes tanking teams and high variances in player performances due to injuries and suspensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After extracting the information, I created a database with all the necessary offensive and defensive variables that would be viable predictors of a team’s success.  I determined these based on the correlation coefficients between each variable and a team’s number of wins during their playoff run.  All statistically insignificant predictors were removed using t-tests for individual factors and likelihood-ratio tests for joint significance tests. This step is done to avoid removing relevant variables because of multicollinearity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The database is located in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Donaldvu18/Playoffproject&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;. The predictors are described in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/table1.png&quot; alt=&quot;variable descriptions&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;i&gt;Note that defensive rating, defensive FG %, and defensive FT/FGA are correlated inversely with predicted number of wins since they measure the opponent’s performance.  This means the lower the value, the better a team’s defensive ability.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Method&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective is to create a model that can predict the total amount of playoff wins a team will achieve based on their averages for the parameters mentioned above.  Note that the purpose of this model is not to predict whether a certain team will win the championship, but rather to see the trends associated with teams given their amount of wins and other variables.  From these estimates, we are able to see how deep a playoff team will go, but the intention is to see how much each offensive or defensive measure contributes to an overall win count.  This is better than just simply making an algorithm purely focused on win outcome because that would depend on matchups and countless other elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before creating the models, I standardized and centered each predictor due to the varying magnitudes from percentages and ratings.  Using forward and backwards stepwise regression, I generated the best model for each subset size based on the criteria of highest R-squared.  The R-squared value for each model represents how accurately the predictors can estimate the outcome, which in this case is total playoff wins.  Since we have eleven predictors, this produced eleven unique models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/table2.png&quot; alt=&quot;models&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was to choose the optimal model out of all these options which means  finding the one with the lowest mean squared error.  The MSE will provide us with an idea of a model’s precision since it measures how much its predictions deviate from the true observations. To acquire these MSE values, I chose to employ cross-validation methods instead of traditional criterions such as AIC, BIC, or adjusted R-squared.  Cross validation is a more suitable approach since our sample size is relatively small (n=512) compared to the amount of predictors (k=11) which makes the error variance much harder to estimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I utilized a 10-folds cross validation which consists of dividing the dataset into ten groups, or folds, of equal sizes.  The first fold is chosen as the validation set while the rest of the data is used to fit the proposed model.  The fitted model is then tested on the first fold and we are able to find our first MSE value by comparing our estimates of each team’s total wins with the actual numbers.  We continue to do 10 iterations of this step with a different fold being designated as the validation set each time while all the other groups are used to train the model.  Then we average the ten MSE values acquired which gives us the overall MSE of that specific model.  This entire process is repeated for each subset size listed above which consequently allows us to narrow down our pool to a single quintessential model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Final Model&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/model1.png&quot; alt=&quot;model 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Results&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we have standardized and centered our predictor values, there are certain ways to interpret these numbers.  The intercept value represents the base number of wins that all teams start off with and then it will increase or decrease depending on the values of the parameters.  For example, keeping all else constant (fancy way of saying keep all other variables at their average value), for every increase in one standard deviation of a team’s offensive rating, the amount of predicted wins increases by 2.4010377.  Conversely, for every increase in one standard deviation of a team’s defensive rating, the amount of predicted wins decreases by -2.1930858 (remember that defensive rating is inversely correlated).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am just looking to compare the magnitude of offensive measures versus defensive ones, I will interpret the results in terms of standard deviation.  However, if you want to work with concrete numbers, you can find the mean and standard deviation of each predictor by referencing back to the excel database in my github.  The number of total wins remains unscaled so it can be construed normally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, our model gives the edge to the defensive side of the ball by incorporating five defensive components in its algorithm versus two offensive ones.  However, the strongest indicators are offensive and defensive rating with the former having the edge.  The correlation is illustrated in the graphic below where one can visualize the apparent trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Playoff Wins&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the results of the model dictate that all the various mechanics of a team’s defensive scheme play a pivotal role in achieving wins, while on the offensive side, the main factor is if your shots are falling through the net or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were four variables left out of the model as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Offensive rebound percentage&lt;/b&gt; - excluded from the model probably because there are not enough instances of it in a game to impact a team’s total wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Offensive FG/FTA&lt;/b&gt; - usually most teams do not have to rely on getting to the line often to achieve a win which could explain why offensive FG/FTA was left out of the equation.  However, if a team’s opponents are getting an abundance of calls from the referees, it can shift the game outcome which explains why defensive FG/FTA is used in the model still.  An example of this would be teams facing against James Harden who notoriously goes to the free throw line with high-frequency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Offensive Turnover Percentage&lt;/b&gt; - a possible explanation for this predictor being omitted from the model is that most playoff teams are usually skilled at taking care of the ball so the offensive turnover percentages may be similar across the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;3-Point Attempt Rate&lt;/b&gt; - when considering all the playoff teams, the amount of 3-pointers attempted do not differ greatly among them.  You might have a few exceptions like the recent Golden State Warriors and Houston Rockets but those are not enough to warrant the inclusion of the predictor in the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's take a glance at the predictive aspect of our model.  At first, it may seem like a prediction error of 2.887163 wins is fairly high.  But one has to consider that the model consist of handpicked predictors that would best showcase the influence of offensive and defensive traits.  Since the primary objective was to analyze these effects, other predictors that could have refined the algorithm’s prediction ability like a team’s seed or number of all-stars were excluded to reduce noise.  Having said that, our estimates are still in close vicinity to the actual number of wins. With the standard error being 2.887163 wins, it gives our estimates some breathing room while not forfeiting too much precision.  It also helps that the playoffs are set up in a best-of-seven format because this way, the better team will usually move on and have the opportunity to add to their win total thus lowering the variance.  This is in contrast to the NFL where each playoff round consists of a single game and can lead to highly unexpected results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the model heavily relies on the accuracy of its predictors, it may also use a bit of luck.  For example, it predicted that the 2015 Clippers would reach a total win count of seven in the playoffs.  Though the model was correct with that estimate, it is far-fetched to believe the algorithm could have anticipated that the Clippers would infamously collapse and blow a 3-1 lead against the Rockets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Residual Error&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The histogram above displays the distribution of our model’s residual error rounded to the nearest .5.  If the estimate was a negative number, I converted it to a zero which explains the spike around the 0 to 1 interval.  As depicted by the graph, a majority of the residual errors fall within the range of -3 to 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our model does have its weaknesses.  For example, consider the 2016 San Antonio Spurs who finished their season with a 67–15 record, their best winning percentage in franchise history.  With a roster comprised of decorated all-stars such as Tim Duncan, Tony Parker, Kawhi Leonard, and LaMarcus Aldridge, this Spurs team was expected to compete head-to-head with the defending champion Warriors.  When we plug their average statistics into the model, the Spurs are predicted to have 11.78863 wins which is equivalent to reaching the championship finals.  However, they were defeated in the conference semifinals by the OKC Thunder led by spectacular performances from future MVP Russell Westbrook and scoring champion Kevin Durant.  The Spurs ended up with a total of 6 wins which deviates substantially from our estimate when you consider the model’s error range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, our algorithm runs into problems when players perform well above their expectations or below them, but it is difficult to foresee these anomalies since each game is treated as an independent event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though these results do provide some insight into our research question, we can make things a bit more interesting.  Instead of generalizing our models to the entire postseason, lets customize our model on a round-to-round basis.  Since each playoff round is based on seedings, this will produce higher skilled matchups in the later stages which may lead to unique insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Further Methods&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the same methods from before, but instead of sampling the entire pool of playoff teams, I only used the teams that advanced into the next round to compute the respective model.  I decided to skip the initial round just because of the high variation of statistics due to one-sided matchups (1st vs 8th seed, 2nd vs 7th, etc…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Further Findings&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conference Semifinals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Celtics Sixers&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;YONG KIM / File Photograph&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/model2.png&quot; alt=&quot;model 2&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this model, I sampled all the playoff teams that made it into their conference semifinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yikes.  Only three predictors remain out of the eleven that were available.  Offensive and defensive ratings continue to have a profound impact on wins as expected, but offensive FG was the only other variable to be included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;FG conf semis&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As illustrated above, there is a strong correlation between field goal percentage and a team’s playoff run. Overall, this model confirms the importance of a team’s shot selection but does not give us too much to interpret other than that which may be due to the numerous one-sided matchups that are still skewing the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conference Finals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Harden&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Image via Air Alamo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/model3.png&quot; alt=&quot;model 3&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model will help identify what factors assist teams in the conference finals advance to the championship finals.  The sample size only includes teams that made it into their conference finals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all the defensive measures had a significant role in a team’s wins while only one offensive factor was deemed notable. Conference final matchups involve the top two teams within each conference battling it out and usually these lineups consist of superstars who can score at will. As a result, the different offensive factors are not as remarkable since teams will usually find a way to attain points.  However, defensive effort can vary for each team depending on the roster assembled and coach’s personal style. Defensive plays such as forcing a turnover or a clutch block can swing the outcome of a tightly contested game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, remember that in our overall model, offensive rating was the strongest predictors of wins.  However, defensive rating has now surpassed it by about .20 which is a sizable difference.  This further supports the notion that defensive grit is critical in these middle playoff rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;NBA Finals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lebron vs. Steph&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Associated Press&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/model4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Model 4&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will help us choose what factors help teams move on from the finals to become the NBA champions.  Only teams that have gone to the finals were sampled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this model, we have the usual suspects but also a few surprises.  It makes sense that when the best two teams go head to head, whoever can defensively lock down their opponents will most likely get the win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is interesting to see that the 3-point attempt rate made the cut as a predictor in this model while other variables did not.  I believe this is because when a team is hustling and outplaying their opponents, they are producing more open looks which correlates with the amount of 3 pointers being taken.  In this case, the 3-point attempt rate would be a compelling indicator of which team is controlling the flow of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic9.png&quot; alt=&quot;FG Finals&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there are other plausible explanations such as a team adopting an offensive strategy based on 3 pointers or individual sharpshooters having hot hands.  Also, note that offensive rating has reclaimed the top coefficient over defensive rating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on which playoff round it is, there are certain team attributes that are emphasized more than others.  However, for the most part, defensive abilities have the potential to make more of an overall impact on an outcome even though the amount of points scored is still usually the highest weighted determinant.  In the conference semifinals and conference finals, defensive potency is valued more than offensive power which demonstrates the strong leverage of defensive plays in the middle rounds.  For the finals , it does shift back to an offensive based model that takes the amount of 3 pointers attempted into consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though all these statistics and equations can tell you about the various aspects that go into winning a playoff game, it is not an absolute indicator of what a team should focus on.  The data used in this research goes back 32 seasons when a distinct style of basketball was being played and since then, the game has evolved immensely.  Also, there are factors that one cannot quantify or account for such as the greatness of Lebron James or Draymond Green’s ability to earn himself technicals.  Nevertheless, these models can still provide us insight on the offensive and defensive patterns associated with successful playoff teams.  In the end, these are just analytics and nothing will beat the good old-fashioned way of playing your heart out and leaving it all on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;i&gt;All analytics computed in R&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/br&gt;
    &lt;i&gt;Graphics produced in Tableau&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Don Vu</name></author><summary type="html">Jed Jacobsohn/Getty ImagesWith 2 minutes left on the clock, Richard Hamilton stepped up to the free throw line. He dribbled the ball a few times and calmly knocked down both shots to seal one of the most stunning upsets in playoff history. The Detroit Pistons had defeated the heavily favored Los Angeles Lakers to become the 2004 NBA Champions. Hardly anyone could have predicted that this team would overcome the combined talents of Kobe Bryant and Shaquille O’Neal along with the brilliance of Phil Jackson. Most analysts give credit to the outstanding defense the Pistons displayed. Though their offense just placed 7th, this Pistons team had the best ranked defense throughout the playoffs and actually had the highest average defensive rating in postseason history.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Has Alexander Zverev Failed to Deliver at Grand Slams?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zverevGS" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Has Alexander Zverev Failed to Deliver at Grand Slams?" /><published>2018-05-09T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-09T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zverevGS</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zverevGS">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;zverev backhand&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2004, the ATP “World Number 1” ranking in tennis has been controlled by four men. In fact, no one else has been able to even enter the top 2 over the last decade and a half. But all good things must come to an end. The Big Four are not getting any younger, and they cannot sustain this era of unparalleled dominance forever. So what’s next for men’s tennis? Who will take up the mantle of world number 1 after Federer, Nadal, Djokovic, and Murray can no longer play as they have? Look no further than Alexander “Sascha” Zverev Jr, the 21 year old German youngster who took the tennis world by storm this past year. Of all of the “Next Gen” players on tour, Zverev has made the most progress as he is currently ranked number 3 in the world. In 2017, at just 20 years old, he legitimized his potential for greatness when he finished the year at world number 4. Along the way, he captured 5 singles titles overall, including 2 Masters 1000 titles over Djokovic and Federer in each final, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a six-foot-six frame, excellent footwork and speed, fantastic mechanics, and an engaging personality, Zverev has everything it takes to be the face of the sport for many years to come. However, there is one glaring issue. Despite all of his success last year, he has been unable to make any kind of mark on the most prestigious part of the ATP world tour: Grand Slams. Having never made it past the 4th round of a major, he has given many people reason to doubt his capability of someday becoming the best player in the world. This article takes a closer look at his game and what to take away from this young man’s career thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Best of 3 Dominance&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;confetti&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In best of 3 matches (all matches not including Slams and Davis Cup) since the beginning of 2017, Zverev has been on cruise control. He has played in more tournaments than any other player on tour and had incredible success. The chart below shows the performance of 32 of the top ranked players in best of 3 matches, where the size of the bubbles represents how much above 1800 their average opponent’s elo rating is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;bubbles&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite playing more matches than anyone else, Zverev boasts a fantastic win percentage of 73.2%. He has also accomplished this against more difficult opposition, with his average opponent’s elo rating sitting at 2010.4 (his own elo being 2129.4 and the highest being 2380.1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zverev’s speed in best of 3 matches is also noteworthy. Since the beginning of 2017, no player in the current ATP top 10 has won more games per minute than he:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;games per minute&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is he winning a lot against difficult opposition, but he is also winning games at the highest rate. The combination of his stellar consistency throughout the tour and the speed with which he wins games underscores how dominant he has been in all matches outside of Grand Slams on the tour. It is the reason why he has reached more rounds of 32, rounds of 16, quarter-finals, and semifinals than any other man since the beginning of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Grand Slam Disappointment&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;break that racket&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not as if Zverev’s game falls off of a cliff the second he enters a Grand Slam; it’s just that he has never reached the quarterfinal of a Grand Slam, let alone won one. He has posted very similar in-game numbers in his Grand Slam matches as he has during the rest of the tour. There must be a reason, then, for his disproportionate lack of success in Slams. There are a few important differences in the spider chart below that can explain this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;spider chart&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Grand Slams, Zverev sees roughly 4 more break point opportunities than in his best of 3 set matches. Moreover, he saves 7% more break points faced in Slams at a clutch 69.7% clip. If he holds his serve this well and has more break point chances, then why is he consistently coming up short in these Grand Slam matches? One possible factor is a nearly 9% decrease in break points won, or in other words, a 9% increase in break point opportunities squandered. Fewer break point conversions entails much tighter sets and possibly longer matches. Coupled with a 5% decrease in tiebreaks won, Zverev’s wasted break point opportunities have proven to be costly. Consequently, he finds himself in more high-pressure situations with even smaller margins of error because losing a tiebreaker, which can literally come down to just one bad service point, can easily change the momentum of an entire match and be extremely demoralizing for the player who loses it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting indicator of his dip in form in Grand Slams is seen through 2 key ratios:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Points Dominance (% of return points won divided by % of service points lost)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Break Points Ratio (% of break points converted divided by % of faced break points lost)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;key ratios&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 2 ratios progressively decline and dip below tour average (1.00) as he advances to deeper stages of slams. However, in best-of-3 contests, his ratios stabilize and still remain well above the tour average as he goes further into the tournaments. Though one may argue that the quality of opposition likely increases in the later phases of a tournament, Zverev’s freefall in Grand Slams detracts from his consistency in all rounds of best-of-3 tournaments and accentuates his shortcomings on tennis’ brightest stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Time is the Enemy...&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s clear that Zverev’s numbers drop in Grand Slams enough to derail his prospects of groundbreaking success so far in any of the four majors. But why? Our guess is fatigue and a lack of mental and physical endurance. The most obvious difference between a 3 set match and a 5 set match is the most important one for Zverev: match time. In 3 set matches, he spends 96 minutes on the court in wins and 99 in losses. Win or lose, he is on the court for a little more than an hour and a half. In Grand Slams, however, he spends 160 minutes on the court in wins and 202 minutes in losses. He tends to lose matches when they drag on past 3 hours. A lack of ability to perform well in very long matches strongly suggests a lack of the physical conditioning that is required to succeed at this level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More intriguingly, when a Grand Slam match is tied 1-1 in the set score, it essentially becomes a best of 3 match. Considering the fact that Zverev is a phenomenal 3 set player, he should be able to win most of his Slam matches when they go 1-1. But he doesn’t. Of his six Slam matches that have gone 1-1 through the first two sets, he has won a grand total of one. The only difference between this type of 3 set match and a normal 3 set match is the extra hour or so that Zverev has spent on the court. A match in a grand slam is a marathon and players need to manage their bodies to go the distance if necessary. Zverev does not yet have the ability to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic7.png&quot; alt=&quot;mad zverev&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking all of this into consideration, it’s not just a physical issue with Zverev. Here are the scores of the final set in Grand Slam matches that Zverev has lost:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic8.png&quot; alt=&quot;table&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except for his 4 set loss to Coric last year, he’s gotten annihilated in the final set of matches that he loses. This is demonstrative not only of exhaustion physically but also of a lack of mental toughness. It appears as though Zverev loses interest towards the later sets of matches that are not quite going his way and therefore ends up getting demolished in the final sets of losing efforts. It’s a combination of relatively poor endurance and a lack of mental discipline and concentration that cause his Grand Slam numbers to drop, denying him the opportunity to reach the second week of a Major.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;But Time is Also a Friend&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic9.png&quot; alt=&quot;fist pump&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note through all of this that Alexander Zverev is still 21 years old. Although Grand Slam success continues to elude him, he is still the future of men’s tennis and is spearheading the Next Gen youth movement. The tour has not seen a player as young as Zverev dominate the way he has since the Big Four made their mark. At the moment, he may lack the necessary stamina for five set matches, but with more experience and gameplay, he can only become better. To put things into perspective, at 21 years of age, Rafael Nadal and Novak Djokovic certainly weren’t the unbreakable five-set marathoners that they are now. Roger Federer didn’t even crack the top 3 until a month before his 22nd birthday. Andy Murray didn’t win his first Grand Slam until he was 25. Time is on Zverev’s side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, there are virtually no weaknesses in Zverev’s game technique-wise. The dual-threat of the speed with which he wins games and covers the court for someone of his size is just one of many weapons in his burgeoning arsenal. His blistering groundstrokes are enough to blast his opponent off the court. His agile, towering 6’6” frame allows for impeccable precision of serve placement. One can only expect so much early on from a generational talent like Zverev, who has certainly not disappointed through his age-21 season so far, relative to other highly touted youngsters like Nick Kyrgios and Hyeon Chung. Zverev himself has admitted to suffering from mental issues during decisive moments at Slams, which gives us additional context for his fifth set meltdowns. He has all the right tools but simply doesn’t know how to put them altogether just yet. With a great ATP ranking comes great expectations, and it is up to Zverev to make the necessary adjustments to prove his doubters wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kevin Hahn</name></author><summary type="html">Since 2004, the ATP “World Number 1” ranking in tennis has been controlled by four men. In fact, no one else has been able to even enter the top 2 over the last decade and a half. But all good things must come to an end. The Big Four are not getting any younger, and they cannot sustain this era of unparalleled dominance forever. So what’s next for men’s tennis? Who will take up the mantle of world number 1 after Federer, Nadal, Djokovic, and Murray can no longer play as they have? Look no further than Alexander “Sascha” Zverev Jr, the 21 year old German youngster who took the tennis world by storm this past year. Of all of the “Next Gen” players on tour, Zverev has made the most progress as he is currently ranked number 3 in the world. In 2017, at just 20 years old, he legitimized his potential for greatness when he finished the year at world number 4. Along the way, he captured 5 singles titles overall, including 2 Masters 1000 titles over Djokovic and Federer in each final, respectively.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kentucky Derby 2018: History, Trends, and Predictions</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/kenDerby" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kentucky Derby 2018: History, Trends, and Predictions" /><published>2018-05-01T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-01T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/kenDerby</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/kenDerby">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kent/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Horses Charging&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;horseracingnation.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Described as “The Most Exciting Two Minutes in Sports”, the Kentucky Derby never fails to capture the attention of sports and gambling enthusiasts alike each May. First held in 1875, the world famous race at Churchill Downs has become ingrained in American sports culture. Thoroughbreds that have gone on to become immortalized in history used the Derby as a stepping stone to greatness. The 144th Kentucky Derby will take place on Saturday, May 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2018 field is shaping up to be a strong one. Two horses will come in undefeated. A few others come from notable pedigrees. Qualification for the Derby nowadays is based on a points system implemented in 2012. &lt;i&gt;The Road to the Kentucky Derby&lt;/i&gt; is a series of 30-40 prep races that begin in late September and conclude in April. Each is worth a certain amount of points (i.e. 10-4-2-1 for 1st-2nd-3rd-4th place). The races become more valuable deeper into the season (50-20-10-5). Winning one of these will typically cement a horse’s spot in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horses come from stables across the country; there is usually one or two from overseas as well. Trainers will sometimes qualify multiple runners as the prize money for first place is well over a million dollars. Handicapping the sport in general is serious business. Some companies offer top-of-the-line data (for top-of-the-line dollar) to hobbyists and professionals hoping to gain an edge over the general public. This article will focus less about the strategies of picking a winner and more about recent trends that could shed some light into how the 2018 Kentucky Derby will unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following data was obtained through this &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1TxAZq-RMvFMcgmgUtIC6rl9aaxs1czvjCFm6Iw4medc/pub#&quot;&gt;Google Sheet&lt;/a&gt;. It lists more than 20 different factors for every horse that has raced in the Derby since 2003. 288 of them, to be exact. After importing the data into R, I trimmed it down, keeping the most applicable variables such as performance in 2 and 3-year-old seasons, odds heading into the race, career starts/wins, etc. Here is an overview of how much experience the horses have going into the first Saturday of May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kent/im1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Total Starts going into Ken Derby&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Derby is a race for 3-year olds. Most, but not all, run for the first time as a 2-year old. The above histogram shows the distribution of experience in terms of career starts and races as a 3-year old. 2-4 prep races before the ‘Run for the Roses’ and 5-8 total races seem to be the most common usage tactic by trainers. Of course, horses need time to rest and recover after a physically taxing sprint. This usually entails going multiple weeks, or even months, between races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been 135 years since a horse who did not make a start as a 2-year old won the Kentucky Derby. The infamous “Curse of Apollo” refers to this fact; not since 1882 when the horse Apollo accomplished the feat. A storyline this year is the very real possibility of that streak coming to an end. Justify, the 2/1 favorite, has burst onto the scene as a 3-year old. Undefeated and flashing ‘super-horse’ potential, the colt has generated a lot of excitement in the racing world over the past couple months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magnum Moon will also come in without a loss in four races to date. Coincidentally, he did not race as a 2-year old either. While not as hyped as Justify, he is still given the third best odds. Entering the Derby as the favorite is by far the top predictor of success given the variables we have to work with. Look no further than the chart below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kent/im2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Result of Favorite Horse&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The favorite has won the past five years, and has finished no worse than second in 10 out of 15 Derby’s since 2003. Justify looks primed to continue this trend, although there have been many instances of promising horses that end up falling flat. The talent in this Derby has diversified the betting scene, as it will be considered safer to take the field over any particular horse. Magnum Moon, Mendelssohn, Bolt d’Oro, Good Magic, and Audible all have legitimate shots to beat Justify. And of course, every competition has its underdogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest longshot to ever win the Kentucky Derby was Donerail, who won the 1913 edition with odds of 91-1. Twice in the last 15 years a horse with odds of 50-1 has come through with the upset; Giacomo in 2005 and Mine that Bird in 2009. But of the 28 others with odds of 50-1 or higher, only one finished in the top-4. They are called longshots for a reason. This year, potential sleepers who could make some noise include Promises Fulfilled (win over Good Magic in key prep race), Free Drop Billy (plenty of experience and success as a 2-year old), and Hofburg (excellent pedigree). We’ll see if any of them can join the group of three horses with odds of 30/1 or greater that have finished second or better in the past five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does starting position create advantages and disadvantages among the field?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kent/im3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wins and top 4 finishes&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post position may not be the make-or-break factor for most horses, but there is still considerable angst among owners and trainers going into the randomly drawn selection a few days before the Derby. Generally, the four outside spots (#1, #2, #19, and #20) are least desired. Those are occupied by Firenze Fire, Free Drop Billy, Noble Indy, and Combatant respectively this year. All with odds of 30-1 or greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No horse has ever won from gate #17. Solomini will occupy that unlucky spot. Gate #5 was the spot of last year’s winner, Always Dreaming, and narrowly edges out gate #10 for highest total winning percentage. Audible will start from 5 and My Boy Jack from 10. Justify drew post #7 and the other serious contenders are sprinkled in from 6-14, so this should be an even race right off the bat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A horse has no control over its post position, but performance leading up to the Derby could be looked at to determine predictive factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kent/im4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Conditional Probabilities&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a lot to digest at first glance. These are conditional probabilities in the form P(X|Y) = probability that X happened given Y happened. Example: P(Win|Favorite) is the probability a horse won given it was a favorite. Find the Favorite row via the y-axis, then go across and line it up with the Win column from the x-axis. This value is .533. So if a horse is a favorite, they have won the Derby 53.3% of the time. Note that these are based on outcomes from the last 15 years and do not represent the true probability of an event occurring. The purpose is to find trends that could hint at a certain result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the Win column and F1-F8 rows, we see that winning as a 3-year old (F3) and winning your final prep race (F8) both translate to a higher winning % in the Derby than the other F variables. Many of the top contenders have indeed won their final prep race. Having experience (F5, 5+ career starts) does not appear to matter much. Overall, winning as a 3-year old seems like the best indicator of success when looking at wins, place (top-2), show (top-3), and top-4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winning the Kentucky Derby is a remarkable feat, but it’s just the first leg of a trio of conquests en route to becoming an all-time great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kent/im5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Triple Crown Winners&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Derby is the Preakness Stakes in Baltimore and the Belmont Stakes in New York. The three races make up the Triple Crown. Only 12 horses have ever won the Triple Crown (winning all three of the aforementioned races), which include some legendary names. Secretariat is considered the greatest thoroughbred racehorse of all time. Citation racked up 31 wins in four years. Seattle Slew is still the only horse to remain undefeated while winning the Triple Crown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent point on that chart is American Pharoah in 2015. Many thought they would never see another Triple Crown winner in their lifetime in the midst of a 37-year drought. American Pharoah dispensed that notion and breathed life into a sport that was gradually becoming an afterthought. Last year’s Kentucky Derby pulled in a record $139.2 million. A star-studded field this year could deliver plenty of excitement. No doubt many will be rooting for the Derby winner to take the Preakness. If that happens, the Triple Crown watch will be on for the third time in five years (California Chrome won the Derby and Preakness in 2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tune in to NBC on Saturday, May 5, to watch the race. Post time is 3:34pm Pacific. My prediction for the 2018 Kentucky Derby:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;1st – Justify | 2nd – Mendelssohn | 3rd - Hofburg | 4th – Good Magic&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Picking the top-4 horses correctly in last year’s Derby would have returned a massive $151,949 on a $2 bet.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joey Maurer</name></author><summary type="html">Described as “The Most Exciting Two Minutes in Sports”, the Kentucky Derby never fails to capture the attention of sports and gambling enthusiasts alike each May. First held in 1875, the world famous race at Churchill Downs has become ingrained in American sports culture. Thoroughbreds that have gone on to become immortalized in history used the Derby as a stepping stone to greatness. The 144th Kentucky Derby will take place on Saturday, May 5.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NFL Draft 2018: Bruin Prospects</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/nflDraft" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NFL Draft 2018: Bruin Prospects" /><published>2018-04-20T12:55:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-20T12:55:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nflDraft</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/nflDraft">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;NFL Draft Logo&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;NFL.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s that time of year, again. The 2018 NFL Draft is right around the corner, as the event will take place this year on April 26th in Arlington, Texas at the Dallas Cowboys’ stadium. The draft is a chance for all teams to improve in their own ways; teams at the top of the draft like the Cleveland Browns have to fill a litany of position needs, while teams at the bottom of the draft like the Super Bowl LII Champion Philadelphia Eagles just need to polish their already strong squads. The draft is also a crucial time for general managers around the league, who all bear the responsibility of determining the fates of their respective teams for many years to come. Millions of dollars are at stake for each franchise, so it’s important for these executives to make the right calls when it comes to drafting players. In addition, it’s an exciting time for hundreds of draft prospects who have worked for years to hone their football skills. These kids are eager to join the best football league in the world, where big bucks are made and lifelong dreams come true. Seeing that UCLA was recently named the best value college of 2018 by Forbes, I decided to look exclusively at the NFL prospects coming out of Westwood this year. Specifically, there are five top UCLA prospects I would like to highlight: Josh Rosen, Kolton Miller, Jordan Lasley, Scott Quessenberry, and Kenny Young. I will look at how each player compares with prospects at their same positions and how their skill sets may translate to the next level. Through an examination of these five individuals, I hope to provide both brief scouting reports and projections for when each prospect will be drafted based on the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Josh Rosen&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;LA Times&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first prospect I will analyze is Josh Rosen, the quarterback everybody knows will be going in the 1st round. The question many are wondering, however, is how early the UCLA product will go. Many coaches like his polished passing style and football intellect, as they believe these traits will translate well to the NFL. Mock draft experts, such as Mel Kiper Jr. and Todd McShay, like Rosen for the same reasons, and as a result, they have consistently placed him at the top of their draft boards. Obviously, Rosen’s accuracy and competent arm strength bode well for him, but there are concerns as well. First of all, he has interests outside of football, like the environment, that may interfere with his desire to play football. This isn’t unprecedented, however, as last year’s 1st overall pick, Myles Garrett, had a passion for paleontology, but he performed well in his rookie year. Another criticism of Rosen is his perceived immaturity, as there have been rumors that teammates may not like him due to his arrogance and perceived family wealth. Furthermore, Rosen may be under question due to his slim frame; he has taken some big hits during his college career that have left him with several injuries. Hopefully for Rosen these concerns don’t become reasons for teams to pass on him, especially since this is projected to be one of the most quarterback-heavy drafts in recent memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;TD/int&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Completion Percentage&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Passing Rating&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, I have put together some histograms to compare Rosen to other top quarterback prospects around the country. Namely, Rosen is being measured against Sam Darnold (USC), Baker Mayfield (Oklahoma), Josh Allen (Wyoming), and Lamar Jackson (Louisville). Specifically, I have looked over three statistical categories in particular: touchdown to interception (TD/Int) ratio, completion percentage, and passer rating on the college scale for each player over their college careers at their current schools (for Mayfield, I didn’t include his time at Texas Tech). The justification for these metrics is that none of them take into account the volume of games played, so regardless of how many games each quarterback played, these categories should still be good comparisons. Plus, the TD/Int ratio measures how well each player takes care of the ball, which is vital at the next level, the completion percentage shows how accurate and poised a quarterback is, and passer rating on the college scale takes into account a number of statistics to show how efficient a quarterback is with the ball. After looking at each of these categories for the aforementioned players, I found that Rosen is in the middle of the pack statistically speaking. Out of the five prospects, he ranks 4th in Td/Int ratio, 3rd in completion percentage, and 4th in passer rating on the college scale. For TD/Int ratio, although Rosen threw for a healthy 59 touchdowns at UCLA, his 26 interceptions hint to his proclivity to do too much with the football. As for completion percentage, Rosen did hit the coveted 60 percent threshold that executives like to see from incoming prospects, but a lack of help at the receiver position might factor into why he is behind Baker Mayfield and Sam Darnold in this category. Finally, in terms of passer rating on the college scale, Rosen has a respectable 140.1 mark, but again, the lack of offensive weapons might have hurt him in comparison to the other quarterbacks. Overall, these stats suggest that although Rosen might be a bit overrated, he still has the potential to succeed at the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of where Josh Rosen could be selected in the draft, there are a few teams within the top 15 selections that are in need of a quarterback. First, there are the Cleveland Browns, who have the 1st overall selection; they will more than likely go with Sam Darnold, the safest quarterback pick. Then, at the 3rd slot, there are the New York Jets, who probably will choose between Josh Allen and Baker Mayfield at quarterback. Rosen has an outside shot to be a Jet, but Jets no-nonsense head coach Todd Bowles may take issue with Rosen’s character. The Miami Dolphins at the 11th position will be the most likely landing spot for Rosen, as he would fit nicely behind current quarterback Ryan Tannehill, who has had injury issues recently. Plus, Dolphins’ head man Adam Gase is known as an offensive specialist, so I could see him developing Rosen quite well. Another possibility would be the Buffalo Bills at the 12th spot, but they could also make a trade to get Rosen earlier if they are confident he will outperform the recently-acquired A.J. McCarron. If I had to guess, I would say Rosen ends up going to Miami, but there’s a chance he lands in Buffalo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Number 77&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Sacramento Bee&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other potential first-rounder coming out of UCLA is offensive tackle Kolton Miller, a big left tackle with great athleticism for a guy his size. Despite being 6 foot 9 and 310 pounds, the man put on a clinic at the NFL Combine in March. Although offensive linemen don’t have conventional in-game statistics like quarterbacks and wide receivers do, they showcase their talent through measurables at the combine. For instance, Miller was a top-4 performer among all offensive linemen in the 40-yard dash (4.95 s), the vertical jump (31.5”), the broad jump (121”), and the 20-yard shuttle (4.49 s). In fact, he broke a combine record for the broad jump for offensive linemen by a full 2 inches. So, not only is he big, but he’s seemingly more agile than guys at his position who are both shorter and lighter than him. This kind of athleticism is very rare for an offensive lineman, so Miller could be a versatile blocker who could play different positions and in different offensive schemes. Also, it doesn’t hurt that he has good football instincts, which just strengthens the argument that he could be a versatile lineman. The only concern with him is that he is extremely tall, so it might be difficult for him to get low and block against smaller, faster pass rushers like Aaron Donald. Kolton Miller reminds me a lot of Nate Solder, who also came into the league from the Pac-12 and was similar with respect to size and athleticism. If teams see Miller as the next coming of Solder, this would be a great sign for the Bruin product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Best Broad Jumps&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the above graph, we have the top five offensive linemen from this year’s combine in terms of the broad jump compared to the historical average of broad jumps of all offensive line positions. This was the event that Miller broke the combine record with his amazing 121-inch leap, which is considered above-average even for wide receivers and running backs. In the past 12 years, the next-longest jump was by current Philadelphia Eagles lineman Lane Johnson, whose leap was 2 inches shorter than Miller’s. But to give everyone an idea of how impressive this feat was in the context of this year’s combine, Miller dominated his fellow offensive linemen, as the next-closest competitor was Wyatt Teller from Virginia Tech, who had a jump seven inches shorter. Even more impressive, Teller is roughly 5 inches shorter and 10 pounds lighter than Miller. In fact, Miller is the tallest of the five offensive linemen listed, and he is third-heaviest among them. In addition to his record-breaking broad jump, Miller impressed in the 40-yard dash, where his 4.95-second gallop ranked third among offensive linemen. To put this into context, a sub-5 second time is above-average for an offensive lineman of any size, but Miller did this despite being one of the largest humans currently playing football in the world. The same goes for the other two events he excelled in; his 31.5-inch vertical jump exceeded the impressive 30-inch mark for guys at his position, and his 4.49-second shuttle easily beat the respectable 4.7-second time that most O-linemen would expect. Clearly, Miller is a physical specimen who has vastly improved his draft stock due to his athleticism and hard work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were to have projected Miller before the combine, there’s no way he would have sniffed the first two rounds. Now, there’s talk that some teams in need of big bodies might consider drafting him in the 1st round. Some squads that might take a look at Miller are the Green Bay Packers, the Los Angeles Chargers, and the New England Patriots, who have the 14th, 17th, and 23rd picks, respectively. Each team has dealt with injuries on their offensive fronts as of late, so by drafting Kolton Miller, these teams could at least bolster their O-line depth. Yet, these are unlikely scenarios so early in the draft, as the Packers, Chargers, and Patriots might have more pressing needs than an offensive lineman. However, one team that would really make sense is the Minnesota Vikings at the 30th spot. The Vikings simply don’t have the quality of linemen to protect their new quarterback, Kirk Cousins, so one of their priorities is to get a big guy up front. With an already stellar defense, the Vikings could really contend this upcoming year with some help on offense. Also, since Miller seems to be a relatively versatile player, the Vikings could plug him in where they need him most on the line. I’m going to say the Vikings take him, but don’t be surprised if a team like the Patriots snatches him up earlier than anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Number 2&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;gojoebruin.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, one of the nation’s most explosive receivers was Jordan Lasley, perhaps the number one target for Josh Rosen. His ability to create offense after the catch is easily his best trait as a football player. Lasley is able to not only secure the ball quickly, but he also has playmaking ability that is similar to many kick returners. He ran a 4.5-second 40-yard dash, which is decent for his position, but his speed and elusiveness on the football field with pads really shows on film. After all, he averaged 8.8 yards after catch (YAC) this past season, which makes him very dangerous in the open field. Plus, he is a great route runner, as he takes efficient angles to holes in coverage. His explosiveness was demonstrated at the combine with an impressive 34.5-inch vertical leap, which shows that he has the ability to finish plays high in the air. However, Lasley has his fair share of detractors due to his character off the field. After all, he was suspended for 3 games this year, and he has had some run-ins with the law in years past. We have seen too many times how great talents like Justin Blackmon and Aldon Smith have ruined their careers with off-the-field issues, so I’m not sure if teams will be willing to take the risk with a prospect like Jordan Lasley. Another criticism is that he drops the ball with a higher frequency than most, which could be a red flag for teams who are looking for a dependable option at wide receiver. Only time will tell if his football skills will outweigh the criticisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Distribution of UCLA Offense&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lasley was a consistent target as a deep threat for the Bruins in 2017, as he averaged 18.3 yards per reception, good for 28th in the nation. He also had quite a bit of volume as the primary option for Rosen, as Lasley caught 69 passes with 9 receiving touchdowns in the 9 games that he played. When you put together volume and explosiveness, you get a high total for yards amassed; in Lasley’s case, he accrued a total of 1,264 receiving yards, which was 9th among college football receivers with at least 1.875 receptions per game. Above I’ve prepared a pie chart that shows the distribution of yards for the Bruin offense in the 2017 season to show the impact of Jordan Lasley’s skills. In total, UCLA gained 5,961 total yards in the 13 games they played, with 4,479 (75%) of them being through the air and the remaining 1,482 (25%) yards being of the ground. This makes sense since Josh Rosen was the focal point of the offense, and the ground game never really gained momentum. As for Lasley, his receiving yards (1,264) in only 9 games made up a staggering 21% of the total offense. The fact that Lasley missed significant time and still put a dent in the Bruins’ offensive totals shows just how impressive he has been when on the field. He put up at least 100 yards receiving in a total of 7 games this year, and out of these games, 2 of them happened to be for 200+ yards receiving. That’s what I’d call explosiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Jordan Lasley is a really difficult evaluation when it comes to projecting when he will be drafted. While he does have great potential to be a Pro Bowl-caliber wideout, he also possesses some glaring issues that will definitely steer some teams away from him. My best guess is that he goes in the 4th round, because by that time, some desperate teams in need of a playmaker might take the risk on Lasley. And quite frankly, some of the better receivers of the class like Courtland Sutton will be off the board by then. I’m not sure Lasley could fall to the 5th, 6th or 7th rounds because at least one team in need of a wide receiver is probably high on him. His upside is undeniable, and he deserves to be drafted sooner rather than later due to his potential. As for a team he could land on, Lasley would be a good fit for the Dallas Cowboys for a couple of reasons. First, the Cowboys just released Dez Bryant, so they need somebody to step in his place and be productive. Also, the team has a rising star at quarterback in Dak Prescott, and I feel as if they could potentially be a solid tandem for years to come. Overall, the possibilities for Jordan Lasley are endless, but if he can keep his act together both on and off the field, he is destined to have a bright future at the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Number 52&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;247sports.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up is Scott Quessenberry, the heart of the Bruins’ offensive line for the past four years or so. He has been a solid presence at center with decent size and above-average agility; his bulky frame and decent height provide a near-ideal stature for an NFL center. In addition, he uses his hands very well in pass protection, and he is mobile enough to be a good run blocker as well. Plus, he has made the Director’s Honor Roll several times, and he was a finalist for the Senior CLASS Award, which is presented to a senior athlete who excels in athletics, academics, and leadership. Yet, there are some concerns that come along with Quessenberry. First of all, he has relatively short arms (31.25 inches), which could be a problem against lanky, athletic defensive linemen. Lengthy arms give linemen their leverage, so this could be a disadvantage for Scott at the next level. Another possible concern could be his injury history; he had to take off the 2015 season to get surgery on both of his shoulders, which is worrisome for an offensive lineman’s durability. The guys up front have to use their shoulders to extend and block just about every play, so if Scott’s shoulders can’t hold up for whatever reason, he’ll be rendered ineffective against anybody he plays. Nevertheless, Scott’s character and passion for football should give him a shot to compete for a starting job a few months from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Best Vertical Jumps&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is a histogram representing the top 8 vertical jumps among offensive linemen compared with the historical average of all offensive line positions. Quessenberry was tied for second in the vertical jump among guys at his position with a very impressive 33.5-inch leap. Despite being well north of 300 pounds, Scott was able to display his athleticism and explosiveness at the combine, as he outperformed the historical average by a sizable 5.1-inch margin. He matched Auburn lineman Braden Smith and was only behind Texas big man Connor Williams by a half-inch, who is projected as a potential first-round pick. As for names he beat out, there is the aforementioned Kolton Miller, NC State product Will Richardson, Iowa center James Daniels, Ole Miss tackle Rod Taylor, and Oregon alum Tyrell Crosby. In fact, the only center besides Quessenberry on this chart is James Daniels, who is a relatively light 295 pounds in comparison to Quessenberry’s 315-pound frame. Even then, Quessenberry beat Daniels by a full three inches in this event. So, he could be considered one of the most athletic centers in the draft, especially when you consider his strength as well. With 25 repetitions in the 225-pound bench press, he answered questions about his ability to block bigger defenders, which he will definitely encounter in the NFL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course Scott isn’t as highly touted as his fellow UCLA lineman Kolton Miller, but he does have potential to be a consistent center in the league. Although many of his skills are seen as average to scouts currently, his character and coachability could make him a decent developmental prospect for teams looking to bolster offensive line depth. I wouldn’t slot him in as a starter immediately; this way he can learn from veterans who have been at the highest level for years. Teams have to be patient with Scott in order to help him grow as a player; this is the most likely way for him to be successful in the NFL. With this in mind, I would slot him in the later rounds of the draft; I’d say the 6th round is a good spot for him to be taken. As I mentioned in Miller’s section, there are some teams out there who need big bodies, like the Green Bay Packers, the Los Angeles Chargers, and the New England Patriots. In particular, I could envision the Patriots taking a stab at Scott; this past season, their starting center, David Andrews, was out for an extended time, and the team scrambled to find a backup for him. Plus, Andrews could be a good mentor for Quessenberry to learn the in’s and out’s of NFL football, so coach Bill Belichick could be looking not only for immediate depth, but also for a potential successor to Andrews. Overall, Scott’s talent level may not be up to par with many of this year’s prospects, but his grit and great intangibles may enable him to become a consistent force in the NFL for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Number 42&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;LA Sentinel&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps one of the most consistent four-year defensive starters in recent memory for the UCLA Bruins has been Kenny Young, a star inside linebacker prospect. A first-team All-Pac-12 selection, Young kept a struggling UCLA defense afloat with his versatility at the linebacking spot. He did well in coverage with his above-average speed (4.6-second 40-yard dash), and he made plenty of tackles near the line of scrimmage during run plays. Another positive is that he has prototypical size for a guy at his position; he’s a shade above six feet, and he comes in at a solid 235 pounds, so it would be hard to argue that he’s undersized. In addition to his skills on the field, Young has a tremendous amount of character. He’s been named to the Director’s Honor Roll a number of times, and he received the 2017 Academic Student Services Success Award. Plus, he’s active in the community, he was a member of the school’s debate team at one point, and he is the last athlete to wear Jackie Robinson’s #42 at UCLA due to his character. However, critics point to his perceived lack of physicality on some plays, which could hurt him in the future. He has to get better with confronting blocks as opposed to shying away from them, or he will be eaten alive by bigger, faster athletes in the NFL. Also, he needs to be able to recognize plays more quickly so he can react appropriately and take appropriate angles to the ball. Hopefully this skill will improve with good coaching and a willingness on Young’s part to study the game. If anything, Young has a shot at being a special teams contributor with his athleticism if things don’t work out at linebacker; this added value gives him a great shot at being an NFL player in the upcoming years&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDraft/image12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Top Career Tacklers&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we have a graph representing the UCLA players with the most career tackles over the past 13 years. Only two individuals have over 300 career tackles: Eric Kendricks, a standout linebacker with the Minnesota Vikings, and Kenny Young. While Kendricks had an amazing 476 tackles, Young still had a very respectable 304 total tackles during his time as a Bruin. He beat out former teammate Jaleel Wadood, NFL veteran and 2013 All-Pro Alterraun Verner, former Bruin standouts Reggie Carter and Dennis Keyes, and newly-minted Super Bowl LII Champion Randall Goforth. This is an impressive list, and being near the top speaks volumes about Young’s usage, versatility, and dedication to UCLA football. In addition, the 2017 season was the most prolific for Young in terms of tackles; it was the first time he eclipsed 100 tackles in a single season, with 77 solo tackles and 33 assists for a total of 110 tackles, which was good for 9.2 tackles per game (2nd best in the Pac-12). This all-league campaign included 8.5 tackles for loss (TFL), one of which was a sack, three passes defensed, and a fumble recovery. Although this was his best season, Young had a respectable 90-tackle year in 2016, a 69-tackle year in 2015, and a 35-tackle year in 2014. And finally, when you look at the top tacklers since 2005 in the Pac-12 Conference as a whole, Young’s 304 tackles still rank an impressive 10th place, behind the likes of NFL standouts Patrick Chung (New England Patriots), Hayes Pullard (Los Angeles Chargers), and Deone Bucannon (Arizona Cardinals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Kenny Young is a decent inside linebacker, it’s hard to say if his skills will translate to the NFL. He definitely has a future in special teams, where he could contribute on kickoffs, punts, and field goals, but there are too many linebackers in this draft class that have more talent than Young. When potential Pro-Bowlers like Roquan Smith and Tremaine Edmunds are the best linebackers in this draft, more obscure players like Young sometimes go undrafted. Also, teams might overlook him due to his main flaw, which is his lack of physicality. But, I have a feeling that at least one team in need of a linebacker will enjoy what they see both on tape and in character evaluations, so I predict Young will be drafted at some point in the 7th and final round. As for a team looking for extra linebackers, the Chicago Bears could use some depth at the position, as they only have three guys listed at inside linebacker: 2016 draft pick Nick Kwiatkoski, NFL veteran Danny Trevathan, and 2015 undrafted pickup John Timu. While Kwiatkoski and Timu are relatively new to the league, Trevathan has been in the league for a while and starred in the Denver Broncos’ Super Bowl 50 win as part of that ferocious defense. So, perhaps Young can be mentored by Trevathan if the Bears draft him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the UCLA class of 2018 looks to make a splash in this year’s draft with five prospects in particular. First, Josh Rosen is a lock to be selected in the 1st round, as there are several teams that are desperate for a franchise quarterback. Then, Kolton Miller looks to be selected in the 1st round by a team that needs a big, athletic lineman, and his combine performance was absolutely legendary. Next, there’s Jordan Lasley, a talented yet undisciplined wide receiver who could end up in a multitude of rounds due to his troubles off the field, but due to his upside, it’s likely a team takes a chance on him in the 4th round. Moreover, Scott Quessenberry is a solid prospect at center, and teams looking for extra bodies at that position could select him in the 6th round due to both his skill and high character. Likewise, Kenny Young has great intangibles, but his skill set makes it difficult to see him as a starting linebacker; for this reason, he could find himself selected in the 7th round by a team that is in need of depth at linebacker and/or special teams. Overall, the draft is a time for all sides to be excited about, as it has enormous implications for teams and prospects alike. Here’s to a successful draft for the UCLA Bruins this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        All statistics courtesy of sports-reference.com, NFL.com, nflsavant.com, and uclabruins.com.
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Veroulis</name></author><summary type="html">It’s that time of year, again. The 2018 NFL Draft is right around the corner, as the event will take place this year on April 26th in Arlington, Texas at the Dallas Cowboys’ stadium. The draft is a chance for all teams to improve in their own ways; teams at the top of the draft like the Cleveland Browns have to fill a litany of position needs, while teams at the bottom of the draft like the Super Bowl LII Champion Philadelphia Eagles just need to polish their already strong squads. The draft is also a crucial time for general managers around the league, who all bear the responsibility of determining the fates of their respective teams for many years to come.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UCLA Gymnastics: Analysis and Optimal Lineups Heading into Championship Meets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/uclaGym" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UCLA Gymnastics: Analysis and Optimal Lineups Heading into Championship Meets" /><published>2018-03-22T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-22T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/uclaGym</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/uclaGym">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gymnastics Girl&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most exciting time of the year for women’s collegiate gymnastics is just around the corner. UCLA, currently ranked #3 in the country, will compete for a conference, regional, and hopefully national championship in the coming weeks. Boasting a roster littered with former Olympians and elite gymnasts, the Bruins are in a great position to challenge Oklahoma, LSU, and the rest of the best programs in America for a NCAA title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gymnastics is somewhat of a niche sport, holding especially true for the college scene. Most people hear about it every four years during the Olympics, then don’t think twice after. What a shame. Collegiate gymnastics showcases some of the top athletes in the world performing difficult routines to near (and sometimes complete) perfection. The technical side of the sport is daunting, but after attending just a few meets, one will find themselves playing the part of ‘judge’ to surprisingly good accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the analytics, here is a rundown of the important details. There are 62 Division-I schools. At the end of the regular season and conference championships, the top 36 are distributed among six regional championships, the top two finishers of each advancing to the national championship. The major conferences such as Pac-12, SEC, Big-12, etc. are at least partially represented, though not every school has a gymnastics program. Rankings are all that matter; win/loss record is not important. Schools will compete against each other, but average total score is the key component during regular season. Specifically, the RQS system is used. Take the top 3 away meet scores, then the next highest three, subtract the maximum score, and average the remaining five. This system is used to ensure that ‘overscoring’ at home meets is taken into account and consistently scoring high is rewarded. Most schools will compete on a weekly basis from early January to late March for a total of around a dozen meets before postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meets are structured as follows. There are four events: Vault, uneven bars, balance beam, and floor exercise. The home team starts on vault and visitors on bars, eventually cycling through each. With alternating performances, there is little time between routines. Typically, six gymnasts from each team will compete on an event, the highest five scores being counted and the lowest dropped. Every routine is scored out of 10.0. The best gymnasts will usually hit around 9.900 or above. Weaker gymnasts will post 9.600-9.700s. For the top teams, the standard is very high with little margin for error. Anything below a 9.850 is a score that would prefer to be dropped, and programs are counting on a few individuals to hit the 9.950+ range. Each apparatus is scored out of 50, with the total score out of 200. Heading into postseason, Oklahoma is currently ranked #1 with an RQS of 198.120.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between gymnastics and most other sports is apparent. Theoretically, each routine is independent. There is no direct interaction between teams, no offensive or defensive strategies, nothing one opponent can do to affect the performance of the other. Gymnastics is a team sport in the sense that scores are aggregated, but the actual ‘gameplay’ is purely individualistic. 
That makes the statistics simple. All we care about is the score given to a gymnast by the judges. It is subjective, and sometimes actual performance and the score received don’t seem to align. But that’s a whole other topic. For simplicity’s sake, we are going to assume every score is fairly accurate. Here is a look at UCLA’s scores by meet this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Total Scores&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Noticeable improvement by week as the season progresses. This is to be expected. Early in the year, it takes a few weeks to shake off the rust and get back into competition mode after a long offseason. Additionally, freshmen are making their first starts with no prior exposure to NCAA gymnastics. Coaches are experimenting with different lineups, and overall everyone is trying to get into a groove. The continued improvement even in the final weeks of the regular season bodes well for UCLA moving forward. How does this break down by event?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scores by Event&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty consistent across the board. The Bruins are ranked 2nd in the country on vault, 4th on bars, 2nd on beam, and 1st on floor (RQS). They have no glaring weaknesses and have shown the capability of putting up 49.500+ on each event at least once this season. Note that the sum of the dots for each meet number is the total score. The higher and closer together they are, the better. Meet 11, the last home one of the season, was their best in terms of total score and balance of all four scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Analysis by Event&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will go through each event to determine the top gymnasts (score-based) and possible lineup strategies heading into the championship meets. A few statistics you will see below: Adjusted mean. Often, ‘event RQS’ is used to rank gymnasts individually. But this throws away a lot of the data. The sample size is already small, so I created this adjusted mean number that will keep most of the data. It is simply the mean of all scores for an event, dropping the lowest if the gymnast has at least five starts, and two lowest if the gymnast has at least 10 starts. This is done to account for the occasional failed routine that will severely affect the total average. Upper 50% mean is the mean of scores in the 50th percentile or above (i.e. 6 starts = mean of top 3). This is akin to ‘potential’. A high U50% mean indicates the gymnast is capable of putting up big scores. Paired with standard deviation, a risk/reward outlook can be visualized as seen below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Vault&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/pic3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vault Scores&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UCLA has a balanced vault lineup. The top 5 are established and include two freshmen in Nia Dennis and Pauline Tratz. For Nia in particular, this is her best event thus far out of the four. Senior Napualani Hall is serving as a vault specialist this year (i.e. the only event she regularly competes on). Along with Felicia Hano, she has the most difficult vault; but with a 10.0 start value, the highest potential score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mPvcgyahFCM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyla Ross is rock solid as always, we will see later on why she has been UCLA’s best all-around gymnast. Katelyn Ohashi started a few times earlier in the season, but it appears Anna Glenn has a hold of that sixth spot in the lineup. Sonya Meraz and Gracie Kramer have each had a pair of starts as well. It will be interesting to see if Madison Kocian steps in at some point. She is nursing a shoulder injury and has only competed on beam and floor this season, but was a staple in last year’s vault lineup. Otherwise, the top 6 looks to be set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal Lineup: Felicia Hano – Kyla Ross – Napualani Hall – Nia Dennis – Pauline Tratz – Anna Glenn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Bars&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt; 


&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/pic4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bars Scores&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bars are UCLA’s most top heavy event. Five gymnasts have started all 11 meets and there is little in the way of depth. The chief cause is again, injuries. Stella Savvidou was a regular last year but redshirted this season. Madison Kocian’s success on bars is well documented (Olympic silver medalist), but that shoulder injury has restricted her. Perhaps we see her this postseason, as it’s been hinted at before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyla Ross stands out as a big score performer, and rightfully so. She has a 10.0 this season and three in her career on this event. She is the epitome of consistency and delivers nothing less than near-perfect routines week in and week out. Tied for second in the country, she is also the defending NCAA champion on bars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZoeukuLZQNQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peng-Peng Lee does not fall far behind. The sixth year senior is a fan favorite and performs some of the most difficult routines in college gymnastics. Along with Kyla, she is one of five gymnasts to notch a perfect 10 this season and has three to her name at UCLA. And this isn’t even her best event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nia Dennis, JaNay Honest, and Katelyn Ohashi have started all 11 meets as well. This is JaNay’s third straight year of starting at least 11 meets on bars. She does not have the highest upside, but provides consistently solid scores in the mid-to-high 9.800s range. Katelyn returned to this event and struggled early on, but has been very good of late. She is one of the classic risk/reward plays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from those five regulars, the sixth spot appears up for grabs. If Madison Kocian is healthy enough she will surely fill it. Otherwise, Sonya Meraz, Savannah Kooyman, Anna Glenn, and Felicia Hano have all performed at least once this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal Lineup: Kyla Ross – Peng-Peng Lee – Nia Dennis – JaNay Honest – Katelyn Ohashi – Sonya Meraz/Madison Kocian&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Beam&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all the stigma surrounding balance beam, UCLA is remarkably consistent and has the highest pure average score in the country. This is the one event where all of the Bruins most technically skilled gymnasts are starters. Leading the way is Peng-Peng Lee, who has one of the most iconic beam mounts you will see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ni_vfla_rUw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peng is #2 in the country on beam and has three perfect scores this year. She has only gotten below 9.925 twice in ten starts. Katelyn Ohashi was an excellent beam worker her first two years and has picked up right where she left off. She’s right behind Peng at #3 in the country. Grace Glenn has competed on only this event, but has made it count performing in every meet and standing at #5 in the country. Her twin sister Anna Glenn did well in her beam debut a couple weeks ago. Madison Kocian has a role in this lineup, although her scores are slightly down from last year (remember the shoulder). Brielle Nguyen served as lead off for most of the season but her numbers have slipped of late, failing to record above 9.850 in her last five starts. She is on the bubble and could be competing with Anna Glenn for that sixth spot down the stretch. Whatever the case, there are plenty of options for this lineup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal Lineup: Peng-Peng Lee – Katelyn Ohashi – Grace Glenn – Kyla Ross – Madison Kocian – Brielle Nguyen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Floor&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally we get to floor. UCLA’s signature event and the apparatus where the toughest decisions will need to be made. Ten different gymnasts have started at least one time on floor, and only two are virtual locks to be in the lineup this April. Katelyn Ohashi and Felicia Hano have separated themselves from the rest, posting ridiculous scores on a very consistent basis. Katelyn is #2 on floor and has three 10.0s. In her last seven starts, she has not scored below a 9.925.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z150ZbLF-9I&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freshman Pauline Tratz has excelled in this event as well. Kyla Ross is steady as always, and Madison Kocian will likely be a fixture after returning to floor midseason. The looming decision to be made for that sixth spot appears to be between Gracie Kramer, Nia Dennis, and Sonya Meraz. It could depend on the meet to see which one draws into the lineup. For regionals, the Bruins don’t necessarily need to score their highest possible, which is why it could pay off to go with the most consistent in Sonya Meraz. For nationals, it will take gymnasts performing to their highest potential to beat the powerhouses. Massive scores are needed, possibly opening the door for the upside start in Gracie Kramer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal Lineup: Katelyn Ohashi – Felicia Hano – Kyla Ross – Pauline Tratz – Madison Kocian – Gracie Kramer/Sonya Meraz&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Recap&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the full lineups listed again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Vault&lt;/u&gt;:Felicia Hano – Kyla Ross – Napualani Hall – Nia Dennis – Pauline Tratz – Anna Glenn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Bars&lt;/u&gt;:Kyla Ross – Peng-Peng Lee – Nia Dennis – JaNay Honest – Katelyn Ohashi – Sonya Meraz/Madison Kocian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Beam&lt;/u&gt;:Peng-Peng Lee – Katelyn Ohashi – Grace Glenn – Kyla Ross – Madison Kocian – Brielle Nguyen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Floor&lt;/u&gt;:Katelyn Ohashi – Felicia Hano – Kyla Ross – Pauline Tratz – Madison Kocian – Gracie Kramer/Sonya Meraz&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyla Ross will be likely be doing all-around, which she has done eight times this year. Interesting storylines to follow include Madison Kocian’s potential return to the bars, and the decision to be made regarding floor lineup. We will see who delivers clutch performances late in the season and how the freshmen handle increased pressure. UCLA will need to be firing on all cylinders to come out of St. Louis with a national championship on April 21st.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joey Maurer</name></author><summary type="html">The most exciting time of the year for women’s collegiate gymnastics is just around the corner. UCLA, currently ranked 3rd in the country, will compete for a conference, regional, and hopefully national championship in the coming weeks. Boasting a roster littered with former Olympians and elite gymnasts, the Bruins are in a great position to challenge Oklahoma, LSU, and the rest of the best programs in America for a NCAA title.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blake Griffin: Sharpshooter or Bricklayer?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blakegriffin" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blake Griffin: Sharpshooter or Bricklayer?" /><published>2018-03-11T15:55:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-11T15:55:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blakegriffin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blakegriffin">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Blake Griffin&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a decorated high-school recruit, to Naismith College Player of the Year, to apparent resuscitator of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=41EFwuBqEUA&quot;&gt;Dunk Contest&lt;/a&gt;, to &lt;a href=&quot;https://deadspin.com/blake-griffin-decked-equipment-manager-over-teasing-gon-1755656136&quot;&gt;slugger&lt;/a&gt; of an equipment manager, to highly &lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-pistons-trade-for-blake-griffin-was-a-desperate-move-and-it-may-backfire/&quot;&gt;controversial&lt;/a&gt; trade chip, Blake Griffin’s basketball career has had quite the peaks and valleys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blake Griffin came into the league in 2009 (but was sidelined by injury until the 2010-11 season) as a supremely athletic, bullish brute who could overpower players in the paint. This style of play lended to some amazing highlight plays that will entertain fans for years to come, like this reel of his whopping 214 dunks during his rookie season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YWzLFqptmhw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As his career progressed, he started expanding his offensive repertoire, frequently performing some &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fDXe_wvo-Ug?t=27s&quot;&gt;clumsy albeit effective post moves&lt;/a&gt; to score on defenders. After becoming teammates with pick-and-roll maestro Chris Paul during the 2011-12 season, Griffin assumed a hefty role in the pick-and-roll with Chris Paul. Not only did this partnership allow him to make some &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/b7qvdDyg8pw?t=21s&quot;&gt;dazzling plays in the paint from perfect CP3 dimes&lt;/a&gt;, but it also opened up his game to learn how to &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/bAenu52u5Ow?t=4m46s&quot;&gt;knock down mid-range jumpers out of pick-and-pop situations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the league has become drastically different since the early 2010s. After the sudden success of Steph Curry and the Steve Kerr-coached Golden State Warrior teams, the NBA as a whole has realized that long mid-range shots are nearly obsolete, since there is so much more value in stepping back a few feet to take a 3-pointer and scoring an extra point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this change happened, Griffin faced a significant conundrum. As he played more and more with Chris Paul, he was shooting more and more of those mid-range shots as he got more and more comfortable popping out from the pick-and-roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/table_griff.png&quot; alt=&quot;table&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in the table, Griffin clearly took less of those mid-range attempts after the 2015-16 season. In the offseason before the 2016-17 season, he spoke on wanting to shoot “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ocregister.com/2016/09/29/clippers-blake-griffin-ready-to-extend-range-shoot-more-3-pointers/&quot;&gt;confidently&lt;/a&gt;” from 3-point land as he saw some of his contemporaries, such as Anthony Davis and Lamarcus Aldridge, doing the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers certainly reflect his desire to shoot more 3-pointers. The season after he made these comments (2016-17), Griffin increased his 3-point attempts per game to 1.9 per game from just 0.5 per game. This season, he has shot them even more, taking 5.5 per game. This graphic illustrates his offensive game stretching away from the basket as his career has continued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Spider Plot&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this chart, we can see that in the last two seasons, he has drastically increased the amount of 3-pointers he takes. As seen in the chart, Griffin has also reduced those shots from 10 to 16 feet and 16 feet to the 3-point arc, instead opting to shoot more 3-pointers. He has clearly seen the direction in which the league is headed, and has made adjustments to try and keep up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while it is good that he is shooting more 3s, there is a more important question here: how well is he shooting these 3s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, sadly, is a resounding “meh.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this season, Griffin is shooting 33.5% from 3-point land, putting him below the league average mark of 36.2% from 3. On top of this, he is shooting about 5.6 3-point attempts per game. Let’s look at how players of comparable size at the same forward position that Griffin plays shoot the 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Three pt FG%&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not look pretty for Griffin. Out of these 21 players, Griffin is second-to-last in 3-point FG%, with only Danilo Gallinari trailing him. Some may say this comparison is unfair, as the classification of “Forwards Taller Than 6'7&quot; (at least 5 3-Point Attempts/Game)” includes players like Paul George and Trevor Ariza: guys who could easily double as guards and predicate their games more on shooting. It can be easily argued that in today’s NBA, the forward and the shooting guard positions are almost fluid, with many so-called “death lineups” featuring traditional shooting guards/small forwards occupying the power forward spot. Thus, it can be fair to compare Griffin to these players, especially when he is taking 5.5 3-pointers per game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for argument's sake, let’s just look at how Griffin compares to players that traditionally fill a role similar to his on offense in terms of 3-point accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Three pt FG% 6foot10&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results are still ugly, as he is still second-to-last among these players, with only our returning friend Danilo Gallinari behind him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the beginning of the season, when he was still with the Clippers, there was a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sbnation.com/2017/10/27/16557294/blake-griffin-3-point-shooting-clippers-trend-mid-range-shot-history&quot;&gt;hoopla&lt;/a&gt; surrounding his seemingly sudden pinpoint accuracy from beyond the arc. However, this was a classic case of looking at too small a sample size; while he might have been shooting 43.5% from 3 through 4 games, he is now shooting below league average after 60+ games into the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams are aware of his lackluster shooting, too. Take a look at this clip; even though Griffin makes the shot, note how his defender, Serge Ibaka, does not even try to fight through the screen to close out on Griffin. Players on opposing teams will let him take those all day, since he’s shooting them at a low accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QpPiyOepYbg?start=76&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps in the offseason, he can work on developing a more fluid motion on his jumpers. As seen in these warm-up shots (and also in his in-game shots), his release is not quite fluid - he very sharply flicks his wrist, causing the ball to fling out of his hands rather than smoothly glide to the basket. Working on ironing out minute shooting mechanics such as these has helped players in the past, and can maybe elevate Griffin’s 3-point game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QpPiyOepYbg?start=22&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Griffin is going to have to improve on his 3-point shooting to sustain the latter years of his career. In addition to adapting to the new NBA, improving his perimeter shooting might help his durability as a player. At age 28, with a significant injury history behind him, his athleticism is waning, and he is not going to be able to make zany shots like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SG4pKhPMZ6I&quot;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; on a regular basis. While he is on the right track, Griffin will have to practice hard this offseason to become a superior outside shooter. Otherwise, the Detroit Pistons might regret taking on his $173 million contract for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All statistics courtesy of stats.nba.com and basketball-reference.com. Image courtesy of Carlos Osorio, Associated Press.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nikhil Sharma</name></author><summary type="html">From a decorated high-school recruit, to Naismith College Player of the Year, to apparent resuscitator of the Dunk Contest, to slugger of an equipment manager, to highly controversial trade chip, Blake Griffin’s basketball career has had quite the peaks and valleys.</summary></entry></feed>