<<<<<<< HEAD
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-03-30T13:01:36-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Bruin Sports Analytics</title><author><name>Bruin Sports Analytics</name></author><entry><title type="html">UCLA Gymnastics: Analysis and Optimal Lineups Heading into Championship Meets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/uclaGym" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UCLA Gymnastics: Analysis and Optimal Lineups Heading into Championship Meets" /><published>2018-03-22T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-22T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/uclaGym</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/uclaGym">&lt;figure&gt;
=======
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-04-03T19:13:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Bruin Sports Analytics</title><author><name>Bruin Sports Analytics</name></author><entry><title type="html">UCLA Gymnastics: Analysis and Optimal Lineups Heading into Championship Meets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/uclaGym" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UCLA Gymnastics: Analysis and Optimal Lineups Heading into Championship Meets" /><published>2018-03-22T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-22T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/uclaGym</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/uclaGym">&lt;figure&gt;
>>>>>>> c75505e528ab0ba5d0ce59d32d70020efe39840b
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gymnastics Girl&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most exciting time of the year for women’s collegiate gymnastics is just around the corner. UCLA, currently ranked #3 in the country, will compete for a conference, regional, and hopefully national championship in the coming weeks. Boasting a roster littered with former Olympians and elite gymnasts, the Bruins are in a great position to challenge Oklahoma, LSU, and the rest of the best programs in America for a NCAA title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gymnastics is somewhat of a niche sport, holding especially true for the college scene. Most people hear about it every four years during the Olympics, then don’t think twice after. What a shame. Collegiate gymnastics showcases some of the top athletes in the world performing difficult routines to near (and sometimes complete) perfection. The technical side of the sport is daunting, but after attending just a few meets, one will find themselves playing the part of ‘judge’ to surprisingly good accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the analytics, here is a rundown of the important details. There are 62 Division-I schools. At the end of the regular season and conference championships, the top 36 are distributed among six regional championships, the top two finishers of each advancing to the national championship. The major conferences such as Pac-12, SEC, Big-12, etc. are at least partially represented, though not every school has a gymnastics program. Rankings are all that matter; win/loss record is not important. Schools will compete against each other, but average total score is the key component during regular season. Specifically, the RQS system is used. Take the top 3 away meet scores, then the next highest three, subtract the maximum score, and average the remaining five. This system is used to ensure that ‘overscoring’ at home meets is taken into account and consistently scoring high is rewarded. Most schools will compete on a weekly basis from early January to late March for a total of around a dozen meets before postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meets are structured as follows. There are four events: Vault, uneven bars, balance beam, and floor exercise. The home team starts on vault and visitors on bars, eventually cycling through each. With alternating performances, there is little time between routines. Typically, six gymnasts from each team will compete on an event, the highest five scores being counted and the lowest dropped. Every routine is scored out of 10.0. The best gymnasts will usually hit around 9.900 or above. Weaker gymnasts will post 9.600-9.700s. For the top teams, the standard is very high with little margin for error. Anything below a 9.850 is a score that would prefer to be dropped, and programs are counting on a few individuals to hit the 9.950+ range. Each apparatus is scored out of 50, with the total score out of 200. Heading into postseason, Oklahoma is currently ranked #1 with an RQS of 198.120.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between gymnastics and most other sports is apparent. Theoretically, each routine is independent. There is no direct interaction between teams, no offensive or defensive strategies, nothing one opponent can do to affect the performance of the other. Gymnastics is a team sport in the sense that scores are aggregated, but the actual ‘gameplay’ is purely individualistic. 
That makes the statistics simple. All we care about is the score given to a gymnast by the judges. It is subjective, and sometimes actual performance and the score received don’t seem to align. But that’s a whole other topic. For simplicity’s sake, we are going to assume every score is fairly accurate. Here is a look at UCLA’s scores by meet this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Total Scores&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Noticeable improvement by week as the season progresses. This is to be expected. Early in the year, it takes a few weeks to shake off the rust and get back into competition mode after a long offseason. Additionally, freshmen are making their first starts with no prior exposure to NCAA gymnastics. Coaches are experimenting with different lineups, and overall everyone is trying to get into a groove. The continued improvement even in the final weeks of the regular season bodes well for UCLA moving forward. How does this break down by event?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scores by Event&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty consistent across the board. The Bruins are ranked 2nd in the country on vault, 4th on bars, 2nd on beam, and 1st on floor (RQS). They have no glaring weaknesses and have shown the capability of putting up 49.500+ on each event at least once this season. Note that the sum of the dots for each meet number is the total score. The higher and closer together they are, the better. Meet 11, the last home one of the season, was their best in terms of total score and balance of all four scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Analysis by Event&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will go through each event to determine the top gymnasts (score-based) and possible lineup strategies heading into the championship meets. A few statistics you will see below: Adjusted mean. Often, ‘event RQS’ is used to rank gymnasts individually. But this throws away a lot of the data. The sample size is already small, so I created this adjusted mean number that will keep most of the data. It is simply the mean of all scores for an event, dropping the lowest if the gymnast has at least five starts, and two lowest if the gymnast has at least 10 starts. This is done to account for the occasional failed routine that will severely affect the total average. Upper 50% mean is the mean of scores in the 50th percentile or above (i.e. 6 starts = mean of top 3). This is akin to ‘potential’. A high U50% mean indicates the gymnast is capable of putting up big scores. Paired with standard deviation, a risk/reward outlook can be visualized as seen below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Vault&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/pic3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vault Scores&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UCLA has a balanced vault lineup. The top 5 are established and include two freshmen in Nia Dennis and Pauline Tratz. For Nia in particular, this is her best event thus far out of the four. Senior Napualani Hall is serving as a vault specialist this year (i.e. the only event she regularly competes on). Along with Felicia Hano, she has the most difficult vault; but with a 10.0 start value, the highest potential score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mPvcgyahFCM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyla Ross is rock solid as always, we will see later on why she has been UCLA’s best all-around gymnast. Katelyn Ohashi started a few times earlier in the season, but it appears Anna Glenn has a hold of that sixth spot in the lineup. Sonya Meraz and Gracie Kramer have each had a pair of starts as well. It will be interesting to see if Madison Kocian steps in at some point. She is nursing a shoulder injury and has only competed on beam and floor this season, but was a staple in last year’s vault lineup. Otherwise, the top 6 looks to be set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal Lineup: Felicia Hano – Kyla Ross – Napualani Hall – Nia Dennis – Pauline Tratz – Anna Glenn&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Bars&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt; 


&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/gymnastics/pic4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bars Scores&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bars are UCLA’s most top heavy event. Five gymnasts have started all 11 meets and there is little in the way of depth. The chief cause is again, injuries. Stella Savvidou was a regular last year but redshirted this season. Madison Kocian’s success on bars is well documented (Olympic silver medalist), but that shoulder injury has restricted her. Perhaps we see her this postseason, as it’s been hinted at before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyla Ross stands out as a big score performer, and rightfully so. She has a 10.0 this season and three in her career on this event. She is the epitome of consistency and delivers nothing less than near-perfect routines week in and week out. Tied for second in the country, she is also the defending NCAA champion on bars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZoeukuLZQNQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peng-Peng Lee does not fall far behind. The sixth year senior is a fan favorite and performs some of the most difficult routines in college gymnastics. Along with Kyla, she is one of five gymnasts to notch a perfect 10 this season and has three to her name at UCLA. And this isn’t even her best event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nia Dennis, JaNay Honest, and Katelyn Ohashi have started all 11 meets as well. This is JaNay’s third straight year of starting at least 11 meets on bars. She does not have the highest upside, but provides consistently solid scores in the mid-to-high 9.800s range. Katelyn returned to this event and struggled early on, but has been very good of late. She is one of the classic risk/reward plays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from those five regulars, the sixth spot appears up for grabs. If Madison Kocian is healthy enough she will surely fill it. Otherwise, Sonya Meraz, Savannah Kooyman, Anna Glenn, and Felicia Hano have all performed at least once this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal Lineup: Kyla Ross – Peng-Peng Lee – Nia Dennis – JaNay Honest – Katelyn Ohashi – Sonya Meraz/Madison Kocian&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Beam&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all the stigma surrounding balance beam, UCLA is remarkably consistent and has the highest pure average score in the country. This is the one event where all of the Bruins most technically skilled gymnasts are starters. Leading the way is Peng-Peng Lee, who has one of the most iconic beam mounts you will see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ni_vfla_rUw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peng is #2 in the country on beam and has three perfect scores this year. She has only gotten below 9.925 twice in ten starts. Katelyn Ohashi was an excellent beam worker her first two years and has picked up right where she left off. She’s right behind Peng at #3 in the country. Grace Glenn has competed on only this event, but has made it count performing in every meet and standing at #5 in the country. Her twin sister Anna Glenn did well in her beam debut a couple weeks ago. Madison Kocian has a role in this lineup, although her scores are slightly down from last year (remember the shoulder). Brielle Nguyen served as lead off for most of the season but her numbers have slipped of late, failing to record above 9.850 in her last five starts. She is on the bubble and could be competing with Anna Glenn for that sixth spot down the stretch. Whatever the case, there are plenty of options for this lineup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal Lineup: Peng-Peng Lee – Katelyn Ohashi – Grace Glenn – Kyla Ross – Madison Kocian – Brielle Nguyen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Floor&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally we get to floor. UCLA’s signature event and the apparatus where the toughest decisions will need to be made. Ten different gymnasts have started at least one time on floor, and only two are virtual locks to be in the lineup this April. Katelyn Ohashi and Felicia Hano have separated themselves from the rest, posting ridiculous scores on a very consistent basis. Katelyn is #2 on floor and has three 10.0s. In her last seven starts, she has not scored below a 9.925.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z150ZbLF-9I&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freshman Pauline Tratz has excelled in this event as well. Kyla Ross is steady as always, and Madison Kocian will likely be a fixture after returning to floor midseason. The looming decision to be made for that sixth spot appears to be between Gracie Kramer, Nia Dennis, and Sonya Meraz. It could depend on the meet to see which one draws into the lineup. For regionals, the Bruins don’t necessarily need to score their highest possible, which is why it could pay off to go with the most consistent in Sonya Meraz. For nationals, it will take gymnasts performing to their highest potential to beat the powerhouses. Massive scores are needed, possibly opening the door for the upside start in Gracie Kramer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimal Lineup: Katelyn Ohashi – Felicia Hano – Kyla Ross – Pauline Tratz – Madison Kocian – Gracie Kramer/Sonya Meraz&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Recap&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the full lineups listed again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Vault&lt;/u&gt;:Felicia Hano – Kyla Ross – Napualani Hall – Nia Dennis – Pauline Tratz – Anna Glenn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Bars&lt;/u&gt;:Kyla Ross – Peng-Peng Lee – Nia Dennis – JaNay Honest – Katelyn Ohashi – Sonya Meraz/Madison Kocian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Beam&lt;/u&gt;:Peng-Peng Lee – Katelyn Ohashi – Grace Glenn – Kyla Ross – Madison Kocian – Brielle Nguyen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Floor&lt;/u&gt;:Katelyn Ohashi – Felicia Hano – Kyla Ross – Pauline Tratz – Madison Kocian – Gracie Kramer/Sonya Meraz&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kyla Ross will be likely be doing all-around, which she has done eight times this year. Interesting storylines to follow include Madison Kocian’s potential return to the bars, and the decision to be made regarding floor lineup. We will see who delivers clutch performances late in the season and how the freshmen handle increased pressure. UCLA will need to be firing on all cylinders to come out of St. Louis with a national championship on April 21st.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joey Maurer</name></author><summary type="html">The most exciting time of the year for women’s collegiate gymnastics is just around the corner. UCLA, currently ranked 3rd in the country, will compete for a conference, regional, and hopefully national championship in the coming weeks. Boasting a roster littered with former Olympians and elite gymnasts, the Bruins are in a great position to challenge Oklahoma, LSU, and the rest of the best programs in America for a NCAA title.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blake Griffin: Sharpshooter or Bricklayer?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blakegriffin" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blake Griffin: Sharpshooter or Bricklayer?" /><published>2018-03-11T15:55:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-11T15:55:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blakegriffin</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blakegriffin">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Blake Griffin&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a decorated high-school recruit, to Naismith College Player of the Year, to apparent resuscitator of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=41EFwuBqEUA&quot;&gt;Dunk Contest&lt;/a&gt;, to &lt;a href=&quot;https://deadspin.com/blake-griffin-decked-equipment-manager-over-teasing-gon-1755656136&quot;&gt;slugger&lt;/a&gt; of an equipment manager, to highly &lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-pistons-trade-for-blake-griffin-was-a-desperate-move-and-it-may-backfire/&quot;&gt;controversial&lt;/a&gt; trade chip, Blake Griffin’s basketball career has had quite the peaks and valleys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blake Griffin came into the league in 2009 (but was sidelined by injury until the 2010-11 season) as a supremely athletic, bullish brute who could overpower players in the paint. This style of play lended to some amazing highlight plays that will entertain fans for years to come, like this reel of his whopping 214 dunks during his rookie season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YWzLFqptmhw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As his career progressed, he started expanding his offensive repertoire, frequently performing some &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fDXe_wvo-Ug?t=27s&quot;&gt;clumsy albeit effective post moves&lt;/a&gt; to score on defenders. After becoming teammates with pick-and-roll maestro Chris Paul during the 2011-12 season, Griffin assumed a hefty role in the pick-and-roll with Chris Paul. Not only did this partnership allow him to make some &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/b7qvdDyg8pw?t=21s&quot;&gt;dazzling plays in the paint from perfect CP3 dimes&lt;/a&gt;, but it also opened up his game to learn how to &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/bAenu52u5Ow?t=4m46s&quot;&gt;knock down mid-range jumpers out of pick-and-pop situations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the league has become drastically different since the early 2010s. After the sudden success of Steph Curry and the Steve Kerr-coached Golden State Warrior teams, the NBA as a whole has realized that long mid-range shots are nearly obsolete, since there is so much more value in stepping back a few feet to take a 3-pointer and scoring an extra point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this change happened, Griffin faced a significant conundrum. As he played more and more with Chris Paul, he was shooting more and more of those mid-range shots as he got more and more comfortable popping out from the pick-and-roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/table_griff.png&quot; alt=&quot;table&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in the table, Griffin clearly took less of those mid-range attempts after the 2015-16 season. In the offseason before the 2016-17 season, he spoke on wanting to shoot “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ocregister.com/2016/09/29/clippers-blake-griffin-ready-to-extend-range-shoot-more-3-pointers/&quot;&gt;confidently&lt;/a&gt;” from 3-point land as he saw some of his contemporaries, such as Anthony Davis and Lamarcus Aldridge, doing the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers certainly reflect his desire to shoot more 3-pointers. The season after he made these comments (2016-17), Griffin increased his 3-point attempts per game to 1.9 per game from just 0.5 per game. This season, he has shot them even more, taking 5.5 per game. This graphic illustrates his offensive game stretching away from the basket as his career has continued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Spider Plot&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this chart, we can see that in the last two seasons, he has drastically increased the amount of 3-pointers he takes. As seen in the chart, Griffin has also reduced those shots from 10 to 16 feet and 16 feet to the 3-point arc, instead opting to shoot more 3-pointers. He has clearly seen the direction in which the league is headed, and has made adjustments to try and keep up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while it is good that he is shooting more 3s, there is a more important question here: how well is he shooting these 3s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, sadly, is a resounding “meh.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this season, Griffin is shooting 33.5% from 3-point land, putting him below the league average mark of 36.2% from 3. On top of this, he is shooting about 5.6 3-point attempts per game. Let’s look at how players of comparable size at the same forward position that Griffin plays shoot the 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Three pt FG%&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not look pretty for Griffin. Out of these 21 players, Griffin is second-to-last in 3-point FG%, with only Danilo Gallinari trailing him. Some may say this comparison is unfair, as the classification of “Forwards Taller Than 6'7&quot; (at least 5 3-Point Attempts/Game)” includes players like Paul George and Trevor Ariza: guys who could easily double as guards and predicate their games more on shooting. It can be easily argued that in today’s NBA, the forward and the shooting guard positions are almost fluid, with many so-called “death lineups” featuring traditional shooting guards/small forwards occupying the power forward spot. Thus, it can be fair to compare Griffin to these players, especially when he is taking 5.5 3-pointers per game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for argument's sake, let’s just look at how Griffin compares to players that traditionally fill a role similar to his on offense in terms of 3-point accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/griffin/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Three pt FG% 6foot10&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results are still ugly, as he is still second-to-last among these players, with only our returning friend Danilo Gallinari behind him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the beginning of the season, when he was still with the Clippers, there was a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sbnation.com/2017/10/27/16557294/blake-griffin-3-point-shooting-clippers-trend-mid-range-shot-history&quot;&gt;hoopla&lt;/a&gt; surrounding his seemingly sudden pinpoint accuracy from beyond the arc. However, this was a classic case of looking at too small a sample size; while he might have been shooting 43.5% from 3 through 4 games, he is now shooting below league average after 60+ games into the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams are aware of his lackluster shooting, too. Take a look at this clip; even though Griffin makes the shot, note how his defender, Serge Ibaka, does not even try to fight through the screen to close out on Griffin. Players on opposing teams will let him take those all day, since he’s shooting them at a low accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QpPiyOepYbg?start=76&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps in the offseason, he can work on developing a more fluid motion on his jumpers. As seen in these warm-up shots (and also in his in-game shots), his release is not quite fluid - he very sharply flicks his wrist, causing the ball to fling out of his hands rather than smoothly glide to the basket. Working on ironing out minute shooting mechanics such as these has helped players in the past, and can maybe elevate Griffin’s 3-point game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QpPiyOepYbg?start=22&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Griffin is going to have to improve on his 3-point shooting to sustain the latter years of his career. In addition to adapting to the new NBA, improving his perimeter shooting might help his durability as a player. At age 28, with a significant injury history behind him, his athleticism is waning, and he is not going to be able to make zany shots like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SG4pKhPMZ6I&quot;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; on a regular basis. While he is on the right track, Griffin will have to practice hard this offseason to become a superior outside shooter. Otherwise, the Detroit Pistons might regret taking on his $173 million contract for many years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All statistics courtesy of stats.nba.com and basketball-reference.com. Image courtesy of Carlos Osorio, Associated Press.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nikhil Sharma</name></author><summary type="html">From a decorated high-school recruit, to Naismith College Player of the Year, to apparent resuscitator of the Dunk Contest, to slugger of an equipment manager, to highly controversial trade chip, Blake Griffin’s basketball career has had quite the peaks and valleys.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An In-Depth Comparison of the 06-07 Phoenix Suns and 17-18 Houston Rockets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sunsRockets" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An In-Depth Comparison of the 06-07 Phoenix Suns and 17-18 Houston Rockets" /><published>2018-03-09T10:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-03-09T10:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sunsRockets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sunsRockets">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/dantoni/cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cover Nash/Harden&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Game 6 of the 1998 NBA Finals, Michael Jordan’s last game in a Chicago Bulls jersey, the Bulls attempted 67 field goals in the entire game, including only 10 three-point attempts. Fast forward to 2017-18, and the Houston Rockets are &lt;i&gt;averaging&lt;/i&gt; 42.6 three-point field goal attempts per game. In the 20 years since Jordan’s last game, saying that professional basketball has changed would be an understatement. In today’s NBA, the “pace and space” style of play with an emphasis on a primary ball handler surrounded by shooters is the norm; all 30 teams are attempting at least 22 three-point field goals per game compared to the 2004 season, where only one team attempted more than 22 per game. Many of the offensive principles that are prevalent throughout the league can be attributed to current Rockets head coach, Mike D’Antoni. D'Antoni's success with the mid 2000s “Seven Seconds or Less” Phoenix Suns has had a lasting impact on the league today, as many of the same offensive philosophies have been commandeered by other coaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D’Antoni’s two most successful stints as an NBA head coach have been with the Steve Nash-led Suns and the current Houston Rockets, whose offensive play style and shot distribution looks like something from a MIT Sloan Conference research report. This piece compares and contrasts the 2006-07 Suns with this year’s Rockets, trying to find parallels between the two squads. We uncover how similar the two teams truly are and analyze whether the shortcomings of those Suns teams have been solved with the current Rockets team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;PLAYER COMPARISONS&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    Steve Nash/James Harden
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 2017, Rockets head coach Mike D’Antoni praised James Harden as the best playmaker he’d been around. D’Antoni’s comment raised some eyebrows- while Harden is inarguably a great playmaking guard, D’Antoni also had the pleasure of coaching legendary floor general Steve Nash with Phoenix from 2004 to 2008. Since the greatness of a playmaker can be judged on the success of their team, by comparing Nash’s and Harden’s stats in their teams’ best seasons, we can determine whether one was truly the better playmaker under D’Antoni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming off his second MVP season, Steve Nash scored 18.6 points per game in 2006-07. One of the purest shooters the league has ever seen, Nash was a model of efficiency, recording a field goal percentage of 53.2 percent, to go with 45.5 percent from three and 89.9 percent from the free throw line. In fact, Nash was a four-time member of the 50-40-90 club (50% on field goals, 40% on 3-pointers and 90% on free throws over one season), though he narrowly missed that milestone in 2006-07. Nash was able to bury mid-range shots off picks with ease, and, more impressively, would frequently take difficult off-balance threes after running his man off a pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/S732UyJ9fJs?start=233&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nash averaged 11.6 assists per game, which led the league that year. Not only did Nash score efficiently, but he did an excellent job taking care of the basketball, with an assist-to-turnover ratio of 3.08.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to hitting teammates like Amar’e Stoudemire on the roll, Nash was a maestro finishing close to the basket out of the pick-and-roll, shooting 65.9 percent at the rim that season. He was known for his nifty maneuvers such as this double-pump scoop layup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zUXZB-SZRp8?start=131&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advanced statistics further illustrate Nash’s value during the 2006-07 season. His true shooting percentage, which is a comprehensive measure for scoring efficiency, was 65.4 percent. Nash had a player impact estimate (PIE) of 16.5, which means that he contributed 16.5% of his team’s positive achievements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Harden’s contributions as a teammate nearly rival those of Nash’s, with 8.9 assists per game and an assist-to-turnover ratio greater than 2. His plus/minus rating (how the team performs when he’s on the floor) of 7.8 is very similar to Nash’s 8.0, and Harden has an even higher PIE of 19.4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the stats show that Harden is almost as good a passer and ball handler as Nash, scoring the basketball is where Harden distinguishes himself. Not only is Harden leading the league with 31.4 points per game in 2017-18, but he is doing so with elite efficiency. He has a true shooting percentage of 62.4 percent and is knocking down 86.4 percent of his free throws. Harden is attempting nearly eleven three pointers per game, converting 38.4 percent of his tries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The box plus/minus statistic illustrates how many points per 100 possessions a player contributed above the league average. Due to his scoring, Harden’s league-leading box plus/minus of 11.1 dwarfs Nash’s 2006-07 figure of 3.8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nash had a sixth-sense for finding teammates, elite efficiency, and the ability to knock down jumpers. During his prime, he was considered the league’s best point guard and one of its most valuable players. Nevertheless, Harden’s resume as a traditional point guard stacks up well compared with Nash, and Harden is clearly a far more gifted scorer. That scoring ability further opens up the floor for Harden to create opportunities for his teammates. Though D’Antoni’s declaration in favor of Harden was controversial, the statistics give merit to the argument that Harden, the presumed 2017-18 MVP, is the best point guard the coach has seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    Amar’e Stoudemire/Clint Capela
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amar’e Stoudemire was a powerful, athletic finisher around the rim. Pairing him with Nash’s legendary passing ability created many highlight plays, and was one of the biggest parts of the mid-2000s Suns’ success. The pick-and-roll combination of Nash and Stoudemire was impossible for teams to defend because Nash was so good at penetrating and sucking in the defense, that he could easily weave passes to Stoudemire rolling to the basket. And if opposing teams were in fact able to prevent Nash from finding his big man, they’d be leaving Nash’s other teammates open for jumpers. Below is a great example of their chemistry in the pick-and-roll. Nash gets a quick screen from Stoudemire, who slips the screen, quickly rolling to the basket. Nash then weaves the ball behind his back through 3 defenders to hit Stoudemire with a perfect pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zUXZB-SZRp8?start=85&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While not quite the athlete Stoudemire was, Clint Capela plays a similar role for D’Antoni’s Rockets. The Harden-Capela pick-and-roll, where the two have great chemistry, is a favorite in Houston. Harden is so good at scoring in the lane with his seemingly-endless bag of tricks, that both defenders often stick with Harden when he uses Capela’s screens. Once he has drawn Capela’s defender, Harden only needs to lob it up to his center for easy dunks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CTS-_dlnwow?start=28&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    Shawn Marion/Trevor Ariza
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shawn Marion, a versatile wing, was an invaluable part of the Phoenix machine. He was considered a top-20 player in the mid-2000s, making two All-NBA third teams. In 2006-07, he averaged 17.5 points per game on better than 52 percent shooting despite his memorably unorthodox shot mechanics. In addition to his offensive contributions, Marion was an expert wing defender whose greatest value was perhaps his ability to switch onto multiple positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensively, Trevor Ariza is reminiscent of Shawn Marion, athletic at 6-foot-8, and a tenacious wing with the ability to defend guards and forwards. Ariza, while not the volume scorer Marion was, adds value with his career 35 percent three point shooting. This type of wing player with the ability to score and defend is necessary in D’Antoni’s system, evidenced by the fact that both Marion and Ariza logged upwards of 34 minutes a night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    Leandro Barbosa/Eric Gordon
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly every truly great team features a scoring punch off the bench. For the Suns, that was Leandro Barbosa. Coming off the bench in 62 games in 2006-07, when he won Sixth Man of the Year, Barbosa put up 18.1 points per game on 48 percent shooting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Gordon plays the same role for D’Antoni’s Houston squad. The reigning Sixth Man of the Year, he’s averaging 18.5 points on 42 percent shooting, coming off the bench in 30 of 52 games so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    Raja Bell/PJ Tucker
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raja Bell was a two-time All-Defensive team honoree who drew the assignment of the opponent’s best player every night. He also served as the team’s enforcer, and gained a reputation for making some very “physical” plays.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7V8ZukXsWmk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PJ Tucker fills the gutsy, gritty defender role for the Rockets. While he doesn’t carry the “dirty” label that Bell did, Tucker has the reputation of being a physical wing player who isn’t intimidated by anybody in the league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HLhuoUZ3S0k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;OFFENSIVE STYLE&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a coach, it is no secret that defense is not Mike D’Antoni’s main priority. Since day one, D’Antoni has been an offensive-minded coach, with his teams performing most strongly on that end. He famously crafted the “Seven Seconds or Less” Offense, in which his players, led by Steve Nash, would push the pace and try to score very quickly. At the height of the offense’s prominence, the 2006-07 Phoenix Suns ranked 3rd in pace in the NBA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a decade later, Mike D’Antoni coaches another distinguished offense with a supremely talented, primary cornerstone in James Harden. While Harden has, in many ways, filled the Nash role in the D’Antoni offense, D’Antoni has adapted his offense to today’s NBA landscape to maximize its success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, the NBA now shoots more threes than ever, with the amount of three-pointers taken steadily increasing every season. The Suns attempted 24 three-pointers per game in the 2006-07 season. This ranked second in the league at the time; in today’s NBA, they would rank 27th out of all teams, with only the Kings, Wolves and Knicks trailing. As seen through these charts, while the 2006-07 Suns scored only 26.1% of their points from beyond the arc, three-pointers comprise 40.9% of Houston’s scoring. Even though the Rockets still have 20 games left in the season as of this writing, they have made 963 three-point field goals, which is 22.7% more than the 785 that the 2006-07 Suns had in the entire season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/dantoni/byShot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Points by Shot&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, to adapt to this team’s strengths, Mike D’Antoni has let James Harden play to his own offensive strengths, not restricting him to the same style of play that Nash had. As previously mentioned, Harden is a markedly better scorer than Nash ever was. While Nash was a strong scorer, he was never as prolific as James Harden, who employs a variety of dribble moves to doom his defenders. His specialties include a deadly Euro step and step back jumper that have put him in the 96.7th percentile in isolation scoring this season. Just look at how he put Wesley Johnson on skates this past week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yrjWseovjXw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harden does not only score in isolation, though. As illustrated by the chart below, his offensive repertoire is extremely diverse, and he still retains the D’Antoni tradition of scoring creatively out of the pick-and-roll; well enough to put him in the 61.5th percentile of scoring by being the ball-handler in the pick-and-roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/dantoni/plays.png&quot; alt=&quot;Harden Plays&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key difference between the offensive systems of the 2006-07 Suns and this year’s Rockets is the presence of Chris Paul. In Nash’s stints with the Suns, he never had the luxury of playing with another all-time-great guard who could help shoulder some of the offensive load. However, in Harden and Paul, D’Antoni has two superstar guards at his disposal, which makes the Rockets a very scary team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/dantoni/table.png&quot; alt=&quot;TABLE&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in the table above, these two are elite in scoring in many different ways. More importantly, though, the two seem to fill in some of the holes within each other’s games. For example, while Chris Paul is a below average transition player in the league at about the 43rd percentile, Harden is above average at about the 57th percentile. And though Harden is a below average scorer in post-up situations at the 43rd percentile, Paul is above average at around the 62nd percentile. Their synergistic relationship will help them in the playoffs, when they can run a variety of plays that adapt to each of their strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Harden-Paul tandem can serve up some devastating situations for a defense to handle. Take this play against the Bucks as an example, where DeAndre Liggins has two choices: close out hard on Paul, who is shooting 38% from 3 this season, or prevent an open Harden, who is also shooting 38% from 3 this season, from shooting a 3-pointer. He is damned either way, and Paul buries the wide-open jumper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fz7MnXJ5bL4?start=45&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;FRONT OFFICE&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the players and the coaching staff of a team are the main catalysts for overall success, the importance of a reliable front office, including a competent general manager and a deep-pocketed owner, cannot be overlooked. Just look at Kevin Garnett’s time in Minnesota, LeBron James’ first tenure with the Cavs, or even Anthony Davis’ situation with the current Pelicans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006 offseason, then-Suns GM Steve Kerr did very little in terms of upgrading the roster. He signed Jalen Rose and Jumaine Jones that offseason to fill in open slots at the end of the Suns bench. The Suns decided to rely on their six key players from the previous season (Nash, Stoudemire, Barbosa, Marion, Bell, and Diaw).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, Morey made a conscious effort to improve his team with a plethora of offseason acquisitions. On top of signing Harden to a monster contract extension and acquiring PJ Tucker, Tarik Black, and Luc Mbah a Moute over the summer, he also added arguably one of the best point guards in NBA history in Chris Paul. During the season, Morey also signed Gerald Green and claimed Joe Johnson after he was bought out by the Kings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Suns, the lack of impactful acquisitions was a major factor in their limited rotation. Mike D’Antoni has always taken flak for playing his main guys too many minutes and not utilizing his bench, and this trend was epitomized by the 06-07 Suns. The Suns played six players (the five starters and Barbosa) over 31.1 minutes per game. Besides the those six, no one else cracked more than 18.1 minutes per game. Conversely, with all their acquisitions, the Rockets rotation goes nearly 10 deep, with each of those 10 guys averaging over 22 minutes per game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/dantoni/sunsMins.png&quot; alt=&quot;Suns Minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/dantoni/rocketsMins.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rockets Minutes&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Suns, the lack of depth did not affect them very much in the regular season as they won 61 games, but their lack of depth hurt them in the postseason. As expected, the Suns relied even more heavily on their top six guys in the playoffs: Shawn Marion, who was already one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/leaders/?Season=2006-07&amp;SeasonType=Regular%20Season&amp;StatCategory=MIN&quot;&gt;league leaders in regular season minutes per game&lt;/a&gt;, averaged over 41 minutes in the playoffs. In the first round the Suns easily beat a weak Lakers team. However, in the second round against the third-seeded Spurs, the Suns’ lack of depth was apparent. The two teams split the first four games of the series, but the turning point came at the end of Game 4 when the Spurs’ Robert Horry shoved Nash into the scorer’s table. This led to a skirmish on the court with multiple technical fouls, and Stoudemire and Diaw received Game 5 suspensions for leaving the Suns bench during the altercation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/t3LjDlMd12g?start=45&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a team that relied so heavily on its starters, it was crushing to lose two of its main rotation players. On top of that, Jalen Rose or Jumaine Jones trying to fill the shoes of Stoudemire and Diaw was only going to exacerbate the issue further. It can be argued that Diaw and Stoudemire’s recklessness in getting suspended cost the Suns the series, but at some point the lack of depth needed to be addressed by the front office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Morey has shown that he learned from his team’s underachievement in last year’s playoffs, the trends among the league’s other top teams, and mistakes made by previous teams like the 2006-07 Suns. One of the main concerns from the previous season was that Harden was worn out heading into the playoffs. Whether it was injury, fatigue, or simply pressure getting the best of him, Harden was not the MVP candidate that he was in the regular season in the2017 playoffs. To address this issue, Morey brought in Chris Paul to take some of the ball handling duties off of Harden. On top of that, Paul, who has long been considered one of the best leaders in the NBA (though maybe not in his last couple seasons with the Clippers), brings a locker room presence to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://bleacherreport.com/articles/2737286-kevin-mchale-says-james-harden-not-a-leader-for-rockets&quot;&gt;team that needed a vocal leader&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next area that Morey addressed was bringing in spot-up shooters who could fit into the Rockets drive-and-kick offensive scheme. PJ Tucker, Gerald Green, Luc Mbah a Moute, and Joe Johnson are all guys who don’t need the ball much on offense and can knock down spot-up threes off of Harden and Paul dribble drives. D’Antoni has done a much better job this season of monitoring minutes for his top guys and utilizing his deeper bench, which is the fourth-best in the league according to &lt;a href=&quot;http://bleacherreport.com/articles/2748208-nba-metrics-101-ranking-top-10-benches-in-the-nba&quot;&gt;Bleacher Report&lt;/a&gt;. It will be interesting to see how D’Antoni manages minutes in the playoffs and whether he trusts the role players that Morey acquired in a seven game series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important reasons why the Rockets placed heavy emphasis on building their bench and acquiring skilled “three and D” type players is specifically to beat the Warriors. After the Warriors dismantled the Cavs in last year’s Finals en route to a 16-1 playoff record, Morey mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thedreamshake.com/2017/6/13/15792650/daryl-morey-we-have-something-up-our-sleeve-houston-rockets&quot;&gt;&quot;increasing the risk profile”&lt;/a&gt; in order to beat a team like the Warriors. The Rockets now have three legitimate isolation players (Harden, Paul, Joe Johnson) who they can rely on for buckets in playoff games that slow down and require strong half-court execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of defense, guys like PJ Tucker (who will almost certainly provoke Draymond Green into a fight at some point in a series), Mbah a Moute, and Gerald Green can be used to switch onto Kevin Durant or Klay Thompson. On top of that, Chris Paul, one of the best defensive point guards in the NBA, has always relished the chance to guard Steph Curry. As well as the Rockets have performed in the regular season, the true measure of their team and Morey’s decision making will come in a playoff series against the Warriors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;CONCLUSION&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By all measures, this year’s Rockets are a superior team to the 2006-07 Suns. Morey has eliminated roster depth concerns, and alleviated postseason stress on James Harden by adding a second bona fide superstar guard, a luxury Steve Nash never had. The Rockets are loaded with pieces specifically intended to stop the Warriors potent offense, and it has worked to this point- Houston won the season series against Golden State, 2-1. Houston also has several players capable of scoring in isolation possessions down the stretch in slower-paced playoff games, which was an area where the Suns struggled. It remains to be seen, however, whether these calculated improvements will propel the Rockets past several other formidable championship contenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        All statistics courtesy of NBA.com and basketball-reference.com.
	Images courtesy of Getty Images
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ronaq Virdi, Nikhil Sharma, and Ben Messinger</name></author><summary type="html">In Game 6 of the 1998 NBA Finals, Michael Jordan’s last game in a Chicago Bulls jersey, the Bulls attempted 67 field goals in the entire game, including only 10 three-point attempts. Fast forward to 2017-18, and the Houston Rockets are averaging 42.6 three-point field goal attempts per game. In the 20 years since Jordan’s last game, saying that professional basketball has changed would be an understatement. In today’s NBA, the “pace and space” style of play with an emphasis on a primary ball handler surrounded by shooters is the norm; all 30 teams are attempting at least 22 three-point field goals per game compared to the 2004 season, where only one team attempted more than 22 per game. Many of the offensive principles that are prevalent throughout the league can be attributed to current Rockets head coach, Mike D’Antoni. D'Antoni's success with the mid 2000s “Seven Seconds or Less” Phoenix Suns has had a lasting impact on the league today, as many of the same offensive philosophies have been commandeered by other coaches.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An In-Depth Analysis of Cristiano Ronaldo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cristiano" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An In-Depth Analysis of Cristiano Ronaldo" /><published>2018-03-08T23:00:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-03-08T23:00:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cristiano</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cristiano">&lt;p&gt;
    One of the greatest players of this generation, Portuguese and Real Madrid forward Cristiano Ronaldo has been the topic of discussion among football pundits. The five time Ballon d’or winner has been struggling in the 2017-18 season to replicate his incredible goal scoring performances from previous seasons. With its star player facing a slump, Real Madrid is also going through a rough patch this season, currently sitting in 3rd place, 15 points off the current leader, Barcelona. As things stand, Real Madrid could be facing its worst finish in a long time, having finished outside the top 2 only once in the last 10 years. One could argue that Real Madrid and Ronaldo are not performing poorly by any means, as a top 4 finish and being in a commanding position in the round of 16 of the Champions league is no small feat. However, for a club with successive Champions League titles and for a player that averages over 25 goals a season for Real Madrid, these recent performances have been far from outstanding. Critics have pointed out several explanations for Ronaldo’s unforeseen decline, such as age, poor management, and lack of support from teammates. This article takes a closer look at noticeable changes in Ronaldo’s game over the past eight years and whether or not they are really indicative of personal decline.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/ronaldo1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ronaldo&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Cristiano Ronaldo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
    Adapting His Game
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    As he has gotten older, Cristiano Ronaldo has adapted his game in a way that maximizes his output given his changing physical abilities. In his early years, he showed a lot of flair, but recently, has become more of a clinical striker, getting into the right positions and converting opportunities with his right foot, left foot or head. The following showcases a notable change in playstyle, as he is relying less on using his pace and agility to dribble past his opponent:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dribbles/Offsides per Game&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    His percentage of successful dribbles per game has steadily decreased since joining Real Madrid for the 2009-10 season. Roughly 84.2% of the variation in dribbles per game each season is explained by Ronaldo’s aging alone. Through this period, he has also been caught offside more often every year. This, unlike the reduction in the number of dribbles, may have a direct negative effect on his contribution to his team.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The increase in frequency of an offside shows that he has been positioning himself closer to the defensive line, and often starts his run early in an effort to beat defenders. A possible explanation for this is that he cannot sprint past defenders like he used to, and thus feels the need to make his run early in order to give him the best chance, resulting in more offsides called against him. Another possibility is his change in positioning himself on the field. In recent years, his role has changed from a winger into a more of a complete forward, if not a striker. As a result, he spends more time up the pitch rather than tracking back, looking to make runs to get into a good shooting position. As a winger, his job was not solely to score goals, and he would therefore play deeper on the field. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/ronaldo2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Frustrated Ronaldo&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Interestingly, the graph below shows that Ronaldo has been dispossessed fewer times per game:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Disposessions Per Game&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    This supports the idea that he has transitioned from a playmaker into a striker and goal scorer. This is definitely an improvement for him as he is less likely to make rash decisions and thinks before attempting a risky dribble. However, while this is a positive change in his game, this stat is skewed by the fact that he is also less likely to attempt a dribble, therefore considerably reducing his risk of getting dispossessed. Ronaldo has failed fewer dribbles over the years, but has also made fewer dribbles in total, leaving it questionable as to whether such a change is really an improvement. However, with his waning abilities in pace and dribbling, it is likely a conscious decision that still helps him compete at the highest level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Further supporting the idea of his changing playstyle are the changes in where he generally takes his shots from each game:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Shot Location Per Game&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Ronaldo’s percentage of shots in the 6 yard box has gone up by approximately 50% since the 2010-11 season, while the percentage of shots he takes in the penalty area has also gone up by roughly the same amount (54%). The number of shots he takes outside the box has severely declined since 2010 and he is taking a much greater percentage of his shots per game inside the penalty area and six yard box. This reflects Ronaldo’s transformation into more of a “poacher” as he more often decides to take shots closer to the goal. While it may seem that this is merely representative of maturity in Ronaldo’s game since he is taking more calculated high-percentage shots, the number of shots he takes per game has consistently hovered around the 6.5-7 mark:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Shots Per Game&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Ronaldo has not necessarily reduced the number of shots he takes to be more efficient; he just takes them from farther up the pitch. As he has aged, Ronaldo has transformed from a pacey winger who engages in playmaking into a more of a striker who focuses on positioning himself in order to create the best goalscoring opportunities. As seen below, he has reduced the amount of passes he makes per game, presumably because he is responsible for receiving the passes and finishing chances rather than creating them:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Passes Per Game&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    This raises a question as to whether he is becoming a more one-dimensional rather than a complete player adept in all areas of attacking. However, his goal-scoring abilities have been almost unparalleled in the last few years, to the point that it is trivial to criticize him based on his passing or dribbling abilities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/ronaldo3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Triumphant Ronaldo&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Despite the sharp increase in offsides calls against Ronaldo, none of the data that we have examined thus far has truly suggested a decline in his play in recent years. His shot conversion rate, however, has been at an all-time low this season:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Shot Conversion Rate&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    This is clear-cut evidence that there has been decline in his attacking. A good portion of the change in his play can be attributed to his individual evolution with his fading abilities, but some of it should be attributed to the fact that there has been a drop in his overall level of play, at least in the Spanish La Liga. In the UEFA Champions League, Ronaldo continues to be a top threat:

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs7.png&quot; alt=&quot;UCL Goals per Game&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    He is scoring 1.6 goals per game, doubling his 2016-2017 ratio of 0.8, and is currently leading all scorers in the competition: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs8.png&quot; alt=&quot;Competition&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Ronaldo’s play in La Liga, and likely overall, has taken a hit, but his play in the Champions League this season suggests that his game certainly has not fallen off a cliff of any sorts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
    What About His Supporting Cast?
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/ronaldo4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Friends&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Soccer is a team sport, so it would be unfair to strictly analyze Ronaldo’s growth by only looking at individual numbers. It is important to also take into account the ten other men who take the field with him and their overall level of play. While Ronaldo has been the spearhead of Real Madrid’s attack, its success in previous years came from world class players in all positions. For example, the midfield of Luka Modric, Toni Kroos, and to an extent Isco and Casimero has been instrumental in their play. The defence consists of players such as Sergio Ramos, Marcelo, and Dani Carvajal, each arguably the best in the world at their role. With their quality, it is incorrect to credit only Cristiano Ronaldo for their successes and to blame him for their failures. Despite its quality, Real Madrid is far behind its fierce Catalonian rivals and have declined so sharply that they have no glimpse whatsoever of the La Liga title. Here is a graph of its scoring over the years:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs9.png&quot; alt=&quot;Goals Scored Per Game&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Real Madrid’s scoring per game has fallen from nearly to 2.8 goals to less than 2.5, which is its lowest over this 7 year period. The team has also conceded more than twice as many goals per game as the current leaders Barcelona:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs10.png&quot; alt=&quot;Goals Conceded Per Game&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    It has conceded the same amount of goals per game as it did in its 2017 championship campaign, suggesting that the backline has not let the team down this season. In this regard, there seems to be an improvement from Barcelona’s side, going from conceding 0.97 goals per game to 0.49, rather than a decline from Real Madrid, which has remained fairly consistent. In terms of goals scored however, both Real Madrid and Barcelona have gone down from the 2016-17 season. This may just be an indication of overall improvement in the defensive capabilities of the league. If this is the case, the fault could still lie with Real Madrid’s defence, which has failed to adapt to this trend, as they are conceding just as many goals as they did last season. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The average goals conceded per game last season was 1.47 with teams keeping clean sheets 26% of the time, while this season’s average goals conceded per game dropped to 1.35 with the clean sheet percentage increasing to 31%. Real Madrid’s clean sheet percentage has increased from 26% to 30% over the year, while both Barcelona and Atletico Madrid show much greater increases, with Barcelona going from 34% to 59% and Atletico going from 53% to 63%. While the blame cannot be pinpointed on the team’s defence, it has failed to keep up with the rest of the league. However, another statistic about Real Madrid's attack reveals a steep drop:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs11.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scoring Breakdown Per Game&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Last year, the team had scored in every game in the La Liga. This year however, they have failed to score in 6 games (22%), with 11 games remaining in the regular season. Although their goals per game ratio has not dropped by much, it could be concluded that Real Madrid’s goals per game statistic has been skewed by its scoring big in certain games while failing to score in others. For example, they have scored 4+ goals 6 times this season. This graph corroborates that they tend to score multiple goals in games they win, but also fail to score occasionally. Therefore, this is indicative of a drop in consistency, which appears to be the team’s biggest downfall this season, for it has already lost more games so far this season than it did in the entirety of last season. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    A lot of Real Madrid’s failures lie in its attacking capabilities. With Ronaldo facing a dip in form this season, the decline in his play and the team’s attack are probably related. While it can be argued that he has not been receiving much support in the attack, Ronaldo’s lack of contribution towards Real Madrid’s attack plays a major part in their poor showing in La Liga. However, with soccer being the team sport that it is, several players such as the midfielders who supply the attackers, and arguably the defence, who fail to keep up with the top teams in the league should also share the blame.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
    How Does Ronaldo Fare with the Rest of La Liga?
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    When compared to the rest of La Liga’s elite players, Ronaldo’s modifications of his overall playstyle are much more apparent. Here are his shooting numbers, aerial duel numbers, and overall attack score stacked up against Gareth Bale, Lionel Messi, Luis Suarez, and Antoine Griezmann:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs12.png&quot; alt=&quot;Competition&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs13.png&quot; alt=&quot;Per game averages&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Ronaldo’s shot accuracy is the lowest of the five, but he has compensated by utilizing more of his aerial game as he leads the five players in percentage of aerial duels won this season at an efficient clip of 61.22%. Additionally, Ronaldo’s inside shots per game have increased substantially to 5.24 inside attempts. This is indicative of Ronaldo becoming more of a poacher, as he now turns to headers and close range shots in the box for scoring goals. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/ronaldo5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Competition Faces&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Despite his steady decrease in percentage of outside shots in each season, Ronaldo still ranks second among the five La Liga stars, trailing only Messi in outside shots per game this season. However, his inside shooting has not taken a hit either, as his per-game average of 0.76 is still on par with the likes of Messi and Suarez. Furthermore, Ronaldo’s attack score, which is the offensive aspect of a performance score that quantifies a player’s positive influence in the game by taking all his attacking events into consideration (shots, crosses, take-ons, etc), is still one of the highest in the league: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/graphs14.png&quot; alt=&quot;Overall Attack Score&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    His attack score of 46.10 is second only to Messi, who is 2 years younger. Relative to the rest of the league, it is evident that Ronaldo can still compete at an elite level in La Liga even at 33 years of age. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/cristiano/ronaldo6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Number 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Cristiano Ronaldo is past his prime as a footballer, but it is unfair to create an equivalency between that and poor play. A declining Ronaldo is still one of the top players in La Liga and in the world, especially as he continues to be a top threat in the UEFA Champions League. When discussing great athletes, it is easy to constantly hold them to their own lofty standards because there really is not much else to compare them to. By his own standards, Ronaldo’s game has definitely taken a step back, but he is doing as good a job can be done in fighting the aging curve. His high soccer IQ and experience have let him adapt his game to one that is more suited to his physical abilities at 33. Cristiano Ronaldo will continue to be a fantastic player for the foreseeable future, and Real Madrid isn’t going away anytime soon.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        Sources: whoscored.com, soccerstats.com, worldfootball.net, squawka.com
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Kevin Hahn, Kathir Ilango, and Subash Sundar Raman</name></author><summary type="html">One of the greatest players of this generation, Portuguese and Real Madrid forward Cristiano Ronaldo has been the topic of discussion among football pundits. The five time Ballon d’or winner has been struggling in the 2017-18 season to replicate his incredible goal scoring performances from previous seasons. With its star player facing a slump, Real Madrid is also going through a rough patch this season, currently sitting in 3rd place, 15 points off the current leader, Barcelona. As things stand, Real Madrid could be facing its worst finish in a long time, having finished outside the top 2 only once in the last 10 years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TJ McConnell Should Not Be In the NBA</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mcconnell" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TJ McConnell Should Not Be In the NBA" /><published>2018-03-01T23:00:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-03-01T23:00:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mcconnell</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mcconnell">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mcconnell/tj.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bearded Hockey Player&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;TJ McConnell&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Quite frankly, TJ McConnell shouldn't be in the NBA. He has proven us wrong time and time again; he started his college career at Duquesne, he wasn't drafted, he was picked up as a rotation player on the worst team in the league, and he's a short point guard who can't shoot threes. That's not to say that he's a bad player; he averages 24.5 minutes per game on a Sixers team likely to make the playoffs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    His unlikelihood of making a difference in the NBA started on draft night. The likelihood of an eligible college basketball players getting drafted is 1.1%, but he was the third or fourth most likely to be drafted from a strong Arizona team with two first round picks in Stanley Johnson and Rondae Hollis-Jefferson, and another undrafted player who at one point was signed by the Dallas Mavericks, Brandon Ashley. Looking at the summer after that draft makes his current situation even more unreal. In the NBA, undrafted players have a chance of being drafted to summer league rosters; those rosters are composed of players drafted over the last two years, undrafted free agents, d-league players, and overseas players. Out of all players eligible for the draft, 8% will make a summer league roster, some of who will not get to play in a single game. 90% of the summer league rosters are competing for generally less than 50 roster spots. 24 teams field summer league rosters, and these teams average around 15 players each. So around 324 players for a generously given 50 spots means that, on a good year, around 15% of the players who are invited to the NBA Summer League might make an NBA team. Combining the odds of anyone making the summer league (not exactly how it works since McConnell was a solid college player but to show how unlikely it is for aspiring athletes to make it to the NBA), he had a 1.2% chance of getting a training camp invite after leaving college. The Summer League isn't always financially stable. Players are paid $127 a day for housing, food, travel, and anything else they need, and are not injury protected.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mcconnell/charts.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bearded Hockey Player&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;TJ McConnell's Low Odds&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    McConnell signed with the 76'ers at the end of the Summer League. After he was signed, training camp began, where he still had to live on the $127/day salary. During the training camp of his rookie season, he was one of six point guards on the roster, and the one who was guaranteed the least amount of money. Yet again, even though he had the smallest odds of staying on the team, McConnell found a way to make the cut. Of those six, he was one of four on the final roster, and averaged the second most mpg of them, at 20, through the season. The following season, the Sixers made many roster moves and ended with three uninjured point guards, planning to play them in this order, Jerryd Bayless, Sergio Rodriguez, and finally McConnell would get any time that remained. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    McConnell started 51 of 82 games that season.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    McConnell has been taken out of his starting role this season as Ben Simmons is healthy and Markelle Fultz is developing, but McConnell's game and path to the NBA reflect Philadelphia's slogan--- &quot;Trust the Process&quot;. Being a 6'1, white male also decreases his odds. Being white gives him a 3 in 1 million chance of reaching the NBA, compared to 67 out of 1 million if he was African American. Also, his small 6'1 frame means he had a 1 in 100,000 chance of playing in the NBA, whereas if he was a foot taller that'd be 1 in 7 (NY Times). Thus far through his career, he shoots 34.6% from three, in large thanks to shooting over 50% from deep this year. He is still not in the top 100 3-point shooters in the league, and is behind more than 22 other point guards in this statistic. Shooting seems to be a necessity for other players around his size, a group headlined by current stars like Stephen Curry, Kyle Lowry, and Kyrie Irving and a group of vets sticking in the league like Jason Terry and Jose Calderon. McConnell isn't a star in their caliber, but his averages of 24 mpg, 6.7 ppg, 5.3 apg, 3.1 rpg, 1.4 spg while shooting 47% is a far cry from barely making the NBA. These stats aren't even that far from his college levels of 31.8 mpg, 10.2 ppg, 5.4 apg, and 3.9 rpg. In all 3 of his seasons he has placed in the top ten in steal percentage, in 2015-2016 and 2016-2017 seasons he was top ten in assist percentage, and had the sixth most steals and eighth most assists last season.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    As I said earlier, TJ McConnell shouldn't be in the NBA. But the Sixers are lucky he is; he is an instrumental asset that they found during their dark years that lives up to his nickname of &quot;floor general&quot;, especially when he is leading the squads second line. He transferred from Duquesne to Arizona telling his dad that he had to take a shot to make a run in the NCAA tournament, and ended the discussion saying he knew it was unlikely, but why not him for the NBA. What made him different from all the guys there? I think it is evident what makes him different. His heart. Most players, especially those so statistically unlikely to make the NBA, would think they'd play four years at Duquesne and be done. Or after going undrafted take the money overseas. Or be satisfied playing garbage minutes and taking DNP's until people get injured. Or throw a fit when they get taken out of a starting role they did so much to earn. Every part of his path he had to play his best and shine, and I think his other nickname sums up all of his performances at which he could have been cut. McClutchell. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
            Sources: NCAA, HoopsHype, NBCSports, NYTimes, Basketball-reference
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Zane Winston</name></author><summary type="html">Quite frankly, TJ McConnell shouldn't be in the NBA. He has proven us wrong time and time again; he started his college career at Duquesne, he wasn't drafted, he was picked up as a rotation player on the worst team in the league, and he's a short point guard who can't shoot threes. That's not to say that he's a bad player; he averages 24.5 minutes per game on a Sixers team likely to make the playoffs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Joe Thornton: The Bearded Legend</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/joeThornton" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Joe Thornton: The Bearded Legend" /><published>2018-02-27T23:00:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-27T23:00:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/joeThornton</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/joeThornton">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/cover_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bearded Hockey Player&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Bay Area News Group&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Throughout his 20 years in the National Hockey League (NHL), Joe Thornton has proven time and time again that he is one of hockey’s best players. Drafted first overall in the 1997 NHL Draft by the Boston Bruins, Thornton was highly-touted, but nobody thought he would turn out to be such a legendary player. With a large frame and an insane ability to distribute the puck to his teammates, he has been and continues to be remarkably consistent. As a result, he has won numerous awards, including the Hart Memorial Trophy (League MVP), the Art Ross Trophy (Most Points), 6 All-Star Team nominations, and a gold medal at the 2010 Olympics with Team Canada. Plus, he has been on a playoff team in sixteen seasons, and he made his first Stanley Cup appearance in the 2016 season with the San Jose Sharks. Aside from his skill, he is near the top in terms of toughness. Despite suffering a severe MCL and ACL injury to his left knee before last year’s playoffs, Thornton still participated in a playoff series against the Edmonton Oilers. Even after surgery in the offseason, he returned to the ice only five months later. As a result, he has come back and played well this season for the Sharks, but another knee injury in January has sidelined him for the foreseeable future. Although it’s unfortunate that Thornton is out, his absence provides a good opportunity to realize how important he is to his team and how good the 38-year-old has been throughout his career.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/graph_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Points&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Speaking to his consistency, Thornton has continued to produce scoring numbers even into the later stages of his career. Ever since his career-best 2005-2006 campaign when he was traded to the San Jose Sharks, Thornton has averaged an amazing 1.01 points per game for San Jose over his 13-year career with them, the best rate in franchise history. His franchise-best 745 assists has largely propelled his amount of points, as his ability to share the puck is uncanny. To add, Thornton’s latest all-star selection came in the 2015-2016 NHL season, where he put up 19 goals and 63 assists for 82 total points and added a plus-minus of 25, his second-best mark in a season, all at the age of 36. Looking more broadly, Thornton has had one of the best individual statistical performances in all of the league since 2000. Seen by the scatterplot above, Thornton has amassed 1319 points over 1276 games since the turn of the millennium, good for a cumulative total of 1.03 points per game. Amazingly, he possesses the most total points out of anyone to play at least 500 NHL games since 2000, and during that span, he has played the 4th most games in the NHL. This ability to stay on the ice is impressive considering the physical nature of the sport, yet Thornton is one of the toughest guys you will find. After all, he has played in at least 85% of his team’s games in all but his rookie season, when he was only 18 years of age. It looks like this will be his second year without participating in 85% of the games, but his dedication to the sport and his willingness to compete should have him back on the ice come playoff time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/table_3_2.png&quot; style=&quot;float: left; width: 30%&quot; alt=&quot;Table&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/table_3.png&quot; style=&quot;float: left; width: 30%;&quot; alt=&quot;Table&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/table_3_3.png&quot; style=&quot;float: leftt; width: 30%;&quot; alt=&quot;Table&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;clear: both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;    &lt;figcaption&gt;hockey-reference.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking at Thornton from the perspective of an NHL historian years from now, Jumbo Joe would be considered an all-time great. First of all, Joe is in 21st place for total games played all-time in the NHL with 1493, so he’s approaching the 1500 milestone. That puts him in 3rd position among active players, trailing only former Sharks teammate Patrick Marleau (1557 as of 2/25), and former Calgary Flames great Jarome Iginla (1554). Also, he ranks 12th in assists on the all-time NHL assist leaders list with 1030 of them, only three behind Hall of Famer and Pittsburgh Penguins legend Mario Lemieux. Hopefully he can come back in time this season to beat Lemieux’s mark, as it will only be a few games before Thornton eclipses him. Among active players, Thornton’s assist total is unmatched, as he is far ahead of the next highest total of 821 from Henrik Sedin. And when you take into consideration adjusted assists, a stat that normalizes statistics from different eras to make players from different generations more comparable, Thornton jumps even higher on the list, going to 5th place with 1135 career adjusted assists. He places 1st among active players in this category as well, with the nearest competitor also being Henrik Sedin with 912 adjusted assists. Plus, Thornton ranks 16th in career points with 1427 of them, as he trails Hall of Famer Teemu Selanne by 30 points for 15th place. In fact, in all of the above categories, the people Thornton trails are either Hall of Famers or Future Hall of Famers, so Jumbo Joe will most certainly be a lock for the Hall once he hangs up his skates.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The consistency of Joe Thornton cannot be overstated. In addition to being one of the NHL’s most durable players, his production has been remarkably steady over the last decade-plus:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/graph_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rolling Averages&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Primarily a playmaker, Thornton’s assist numbers per game have almost always been higher than his goals per game. What stands out in this plot is that the black line, his points per game, has never dipped below 0.5 in any of these 20 game stretches of his career since the 2004-05 lockout. Every player goes through ups and downs; whether it’s a slump caused by bad luck/off-ice distractions, or an increase in scoring after being placed on a new line that meshes well. The fact that Thornton has been able to remain consistent for so long speaks to a longevity attribute that very few players in NHL history can claim to possess. The slight downward trend can be explained by his aging, but it is nowhere near the drop off most players experience in their early-30s. At 38, Joe Thornton is still a top-6, first powerplay unit quality player.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another testament to Thornton’s consistency is an examination into the points scored against all NHL teams.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/graph_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Career Points&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, three teams in particular shouldn’t be paid much attention; Thornton has played his entire career with the Boston Bruins and the San Jose Sharks, and the Vegas Golden Knights are a new expansion team who are in their inaugural season. When you exclude these three teams, Thornton has scored at least 30 points against every NHL team. This is quite impressive, given that each team in the league plays the majority of their games in their respective conference. However, the recent realignment of the divisions and conferences in 2014 puts some of the data out of context, but the scheduling distribution is still roughly the same. For instance, according to NHL.com, teams in the Pacific Division, like the San Jose Sharks, have to play 29 games (35.37%) within their division, 21 games (25.61%) within the Western Conference but outside of their division, and 32 games (39.02%) in the Eastern Conference. This arrangement, of course, is due to traveling convenience, so teams in the East Coast don’t square off against the Sharks as often. Therefore, it makes sense that Thornton has racked up over 70 points against longtime division rivals like the Arizona Coyotes, the Los Angeles Kings, and the Anaheim Ducks, but has “merely” put up just under 40 points against cross-country foes like the Florida Panthers, the Philadelphia Flyers, the Carolina Hurricanes, and the New York squads (Islanders and Rangers). Now, to be fair, Thornton did spend some time with the East Coast Boston Bruins, but he has only played 532 games, or 35.63% of his NHL career, with them. This is why his totals are weighted more towards his time with the Sharks, who he has played for in the other 961 games of his career. In summary, despite the changing nature of the game with realignments and what not, Thornton has produced against every team he has faced, regardless of how frequently he plays an opponent.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How has he been able to remain at an elite level for so long? The answer lies in the type of player he is. Hockey IQ is a characteristic that defines how well one can ‘see’ and understand the game. Skaters with high hockey IQ think two or three steps ahead. They know what they are going to do with the puck before it comes to them. They know where everyone is on the ice, and where they will be. Joe Thornton is the epitome of a high hockey IQ player. Because it is largely a mental quality, the effects of aging may be less impactful on him than a similar-caliber talent who relies on speed and quickness, traits that deteriorate significantly with age. Combine this sense for the game with innate physical tools and toughness, and you begin to see why Thornton is such a special player. Unfortunately, no one is immune to injury, and Jumbo has suffered a couple significant ones over the past year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In early April of 2017, near the end of last year’s regular season, Joe Thornton was injured in a collision with Vancouver forward Michael Chaput. He sat out the final few games before returning for Game 3 of San Jose’s first round series against Edmonton. The Sharks lost in 6. It was later revealed that Thornton had played through a torn ACL and MCL in his knee. Head coach Peter DeBoer noted it was as “courageous an effort as I’ve ever seen.” Jumbo had knee surgery over the summer and was back on the ice for the start of this season. Fast forward three months to a home game against Winnipeg. He got tangled up with teammate Mikkel Boedker and fell awkwardly, sustaining an MCL injury to his other knee. There is no timetable for his return. The Sharks are heading into the final stretch of the season fighting for their playoff lives. They are second in the Pacific division, but also just two points ahead of 9th place Calgary. With 19 games remaining (as of Feb. 26), every point is critical. How have the Sharks fared in their last 16 games without Thornton compared to their first 47 with him?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/graph_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;With and Without&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Objectively worse. Their offense is suffering, as goals per game has dipped a couple tenths, and they are allowing more goals per game without him. Even worse, the Sharks’ powerplay percentage has gone way down as well. Of course, we cannot attribute every significant difference to the absence of Thornton. 16 games is a rather small sample size, and there are a myriad of other factors to take into account, such as strength of schedule, puck luck, other lineup changes, and more. But San Jose is playing .500 hockey without their anchor up front, and that will not be good enough if the team hopes to return to the playoffs for the 12th time in 13 years. GM Doug Wilson may have realized this, as the franchise traded for Evander Kane at the trade deadline. Kane is a 26 year-old winger in his prime whose 20 goals and 40 points place him second and third, respectively, on the Sharks roster. Perceived ‘character issues’ have followed the Vancouver native throughout his career, but you cannot deny his talent. He should be able to thrive both on and off the ice in a blue-collar organization like San Jose. Additionally, playing without Thornton for a long stretch like this allows management to see what the team might look like in the post-JT era. After all, age gets the best of everyone. With two significant knee injuries in the past year, Thornton has likely began to evaluate just how much longer he can go. An unrestricted free agent this summer, he’s not even guaranteed to come back to the Sharks for another season.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But the legacy he has crafted in San Jose, and throughout his career for that matter, is substantial. He’s a six-time All-Star, Olympic Gold medalist, Hart Trophy recipient, and future first ballot Hall of Famer. The only thing missing is a Stanley Cup, and unfortunately this draws the attention of the all-to-familiar crowd who judge players based on the number of championships they have won. There is still time for him to bring the city of San Jose its first, but the Sharks are not the same feared contender of years past. Thornton could opt to leave and chase a Cup in the twilight of his career, which would be a bittersweet ending for Sharks fans. When he finally does retire, he will be celebrated in San Jose. Number 19 will forever hang in the rafters.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Veroulis and Joey Maurer</name></author><summary type="html">Throughout his 20 years in the National Hockey League (NHL), Joe Thornton has proven time and time again that he is one of hockey’s best players. Drafted first overall in the 1997 NHL Draft by the Boston Bruins, Thornton was highly-touted, but nobody thought he would turn out to be such a legendary player. With a large frame and an insane ability to distribute the puck to his teammates, he has been and continues to be remarkably consistent. As a result, he has won numerous awards, including the Hart Memorial Trophy (League MVP), the Art Ross Trophy (Most Points), 6 All-Star Team nominations, and a gold medal at the 2010 Olympics with Team Canada.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixture Congestion and Playing Styles vs Injuries in European Football</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fixturecongestion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixture Congestion and Playing Styles vs Injuries in European Football" /><published>2018-02-07T14:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-07T14:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fixturecongestion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fixturecongestion">&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/main_photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winter Soccer&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;In England, every team plays 5 matches in the last week of December and the first week of January as part of a traditional festive fixture schedule, that brings great revenue to TV companies and to the Premier League itself. Source: Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, debate over fixture congestion in English football has increased, both on social media and by so-called sports pundits and former players on television. A key contributing factor to this debate is the increase in number of foreign mangers (mostly from continental Europe and South America) in the English Premier League over the last 5 years. Not only are these managers used to fewer matches (and winter breaks) in their home nations, they also bring in radically different styles of play that demand higher levels of fitness from the players. This article takes a closer look at the main reasons behind injuries by looking at patterns in other top European leagues over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fixtures and Winter Breaks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following table gives an overview of the number of winter break and rest days across the top 5 European leagues. An important point to note is that Spain’s ‘rest-day’ statistics are skewed by the presence of the two super-clubs Real Madrid and FC Barcelona (two teams with excellent squad depth and great medical facilities). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/rest_days.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winter Break Days&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top 6 teams in England play 4.65 games more than their counterparts in other countries. While this might not seem like a great deal, when compounded with the lack of a winter break and the lack of an ‘extra’ rest day, English teams are at a big disadvantage. Moreover, English teams play 26.5% of their total fixtures in the months of December and January and have 3.7 rest days on average. Meanwhile, their foreign counterparts play 16.6% of their fixtures over the two months and enjoy 6.6 rest days, in addition to having the luxury of a winter break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This difference becomes especially apparent in the second half of the season, when English teams accumulate most of their injuries. This is highlighted by the fact that there is a general trend over the last 5 years in the Premier League that has seen the number of soft tissue injuries rise by 45% and the total number of injuries rise by 13% in the months of December and January (according to injury data analyst Ben Dinnery). On the other hand, German and Spanish teams accumulate roughly the same number of injuries in the second half of the season as they do in the first half of the season (5% and 6% increase respectively).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This puts them at a disadvantage when they compete in continental competitions such as the UEFA Europa League and the UEFA Champions League, and is often cited by many Premier League managers, most notably, Pep Guardiola and Arsene Wenger, for England’s poor performance in European competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/fig1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bar graph of Injuries&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1: Total number of injuries (2016-17 season)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A counter-argument to the introduction of the winter break in England is the fact that Boxing Day and New Year Premier League fixtures have been a tradition since the post-war period. In addition, television companies and the Premier League itself make huge revenues from the festive fixture period by scheduling matches in a staggered fashion (one after the other), which often leads to Premier League teams playing 2 matches in less than 48 hours and in some cases, 3 matches in just 6 days. In addition to creating fixture congestion, this creates an unequal playing field as some teams enjoy longer rest periods between matches compared to their opponents. For example, in the 2017-18 season, Leicester City played 4 matches in 213 hours, while Arsenal played the same number of matches in 294 hours, a difference of more than 3 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;t is up to the Premier League to decide whether to value its own revenue by remaining spectators and watch its teams exit the continental competition at an early stage or help to support its clubs’ performance in continental competition by including a winter break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Playing Styles and Squad Rotation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is intuitive that a high-intensity style of football that focuses on pressing, possession recycling and winning the ball in the opponents’ half of the field requires higher levels of fitness from players as opposed to a low-block, deep-defending, counter-attacking style of football. The former style, employed by teams such as Arsenal, Tottenham Hotspur and Liverpool is one of the factors for a poor injury record, as is suggested by the graph below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/fig2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Number of Injuries Timeline&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Number of injuries (longer than 10 days) per season&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, simply correlating the number of injuries per season with a team’s playing style can be misleading due to long-term injuries and contact injuries in games which skew the data significantly. This is not to say that the managers of teams who like to play this way are blameless, however, since it is their responsibility to buy players who are less-injury prone and employ better squad rotation strategies to circumvent this issue. A good example of a manager who has managed to successfully implement his high-intensity style with a low injury record is Tottenham Hotspur’s Mauricio Pochettino. This is evident from the graph above, which shows that Tottenham Hotspur’s injuries have decreased from the season he took over (2014-15) to last season (2016-17). Over the last three years, the Argentine manager bought physically robust players that not only fit his style but are less-injury prone such as Victor Wanyama, Toby Alderweireld and Heung-Min Son. In addition, in the 2016-17 season, he regularly rotated his full-backs Danny Rose and Kyle Walker with Ben Davies and Kieran Trippier and his midfielders, which led Tottenham Hotspur to have the highest points tally of any Premier League team in the second half of the season, when most of their rivals began to suffer dips in their performance and fitness levels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/player.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Injury Prone Soccer Player&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Injury-prone Arsenal midfielder Abou Diaby only made 22 appearances over four years for the club due to a succession of long-term injuries. Such injuries must be taken into context when assessing a club’s injury record.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, both fixture congestion and playing styles have a clear impact on injuries. The introduction of a winter break in the English Premier League would be much welcomed, especially by managers of the top 6 clubs. Playing style is certainly a factor but is very much secondary to fixture congestion. While the issue of playing styles can be resolved simply by having larger squads and employing better rotation strategies, the issue of fixture congestion is one that can change only if it garners the support of the members of the hierarchy of the FA and the Premier League and will benefit all clubs, regardless of their playing styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Sources:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;physioroom.com and Ben Dinnery’s excellent reports on injury data analysis were used to write this piece. An interesting and more comprehensive report on injury trends in the Premier League can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jltspecialty.com/~/media/files/sites/specialty/insights-sport/jlt_sp_premier_league_injury_index.pdf?la=en-gb&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Salil Akundi</name></author><summary type="html">Over the last few years, debate over fixture congestion in English football has increased, both on social media and by so-called sports pundits and former players on television. A key contributing factor to this debate is the increase in number of foreign mangers (mostly from continental Europe and South America) in the English Premier League over the last 5 years. Not only are these managers used to fewer matches (and winter breaks) in their home nations, they also bring in radically different styles of play that demand higher levels of fitness from the players. This article takes a closer look at the main reasons behind injuries by looking at patterns in other top European leagues over the years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NBA Midseason Reflections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/nbamidseason18" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NBA Midseason Reflections" /><published>2018-02-05T14:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-05T14:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nbamidseason18</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/nbamidseason18">&lt;p&gt;The All Star lineups have been announced, most teams have played well over 45 games, we finally have a team openly tanking, and the Cavs all hate each other. So with that it's safe to say that the midway point of the NBA season has come and now would be a great time to reflect on the past couple months of the 2017-2018 season. By now everyone knows how great the Warriors are, how dysfunctional LeBron's team is, and that the Sacramento Kings are once again irrelevant. I wanted to take this time to deviate away from the major storylines in the season thus far and analyze some trends, statistics, coaching decisions, and quite simply things that really stand out to me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Houston's Unstoppable Harden, CP3, and  …. Capela? Trio&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the season Darryl Morey said it best when he mentioned that teams would have to increase their risk profile if they wanted to compete with the Warriors. He followed through with his proclamation when he acquired Chris Paul this summer in a move that many people questioned with the classic &quot;there's only one ball&quot; argument. So far the trade has paid off for Morey and the Rockets have clearly been the second best team in the league and have even beaten the Warriors twice this season. 50.6% of the Rockets field goal attempts are coming from three and James Harden is again having an MVP caliber season (if the season ended today, Harden's 29.6 PER would be one the top 30 single season PER performances in the NBA history). Despite all that, the most alarming fact about the 2017-2018 Houston Rockets is that they are 19-0 when Harden, Chris Paul, and Clint Capela play. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite their current record, Harden's MVP campaign, and this trio's +57 plus/minus, all that matters for the Rockets is how they perform in the playoffs. For the past 2 seasons, this Rockets squad has done what all great Mike d'Antoni teams do: underachieve in the playoffs. So far the two victories against the Warriors have been a great sign for the team. They had an outrageous 41, 50, and 37 three point field goals attempted respectively in each of the three games and the best sign was how well Chris Paul played in the last two games. It will be interesting to see how long this trio can keep up their streak, but more importantly how this team competes deep in the playoffs (unless, of course, they choke in the second round versus the Spurs again).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Carmelo's Falling Off&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    By this point in the season every sports show and radio host has talked about how OKC needs to break up their trio and more importantly bench Carmelo. Early in the season the team was clearly dysfunctional; Westbrook had trouble deciding when to go into &quot;2016-2017 Highest Usage Rate in NBA History&quot; mode or whether to defer to his teammates. Paul George was uncomfortable playing off ball, which was something he rarely did in Indiana and Carmelo was doing his normal routine spending seven to eight seconds holding the ball, followed by a series of jab steps all while his other four teammates watched an eventual contested 17 footer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-qRdXc11jqE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The team has turned it around after their lackluster 8-12 start and are currently sitting at fifth in the West. Definitely the biggest adjustment was that Carmelo took a back seat to Westbrook and George. Carmelo ranks 156th in the league with a PER of 14.51. Whatever your opinion of Carmelo is, seeing his name on a list below Tyler Cavanaugh and Jerian Grant is unexpected to say the least. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbamidseason18/chart1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Carmelo Drop-off&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Basketball-Reference&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    My purpose for bringing up Carmelo's regression this season is not to make him the scapegoat for the Thunder's slow start, but instead to analyze how the league has changed as a whole. Carmelo, whether you love or hate his game, is undoubtedly one of the most talented scorers (and underrated clutch performers) in NBA history. His post game and midrange allowed him to score effortlessly in his career en route to 25,000 points. But in a league where the Warriors have more than five players that can guard every position, the Rockets are shooting 42.8 three point shots a game and the overall pace of offenses throughout the league has gone up, Carmelo's offensive play style no longer has a place. Teams that have a dynamic ball-handler (Lebron, Westbrook, Harden) are full of spot up shooters and defensive minded players. Carmelo is a solid shooter (45% FG% and 34.7% 3FG% for his career) but has never been considered a spot up shooter and discussing his defense (or lack there of) is just laughable. The league just doesn't have space for a 33-year-old stretch four that plays no defense, who kills eight seconds off the shot clock before making any move on offense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Conversely, DeMar DeRozan has been a great example of a player who has evolved his game this season to fit the current play style in the NBA, particularly in terms of 3 point shooting. DeRozan has always been known for his midrange game and footwork in the post. But this season much of the Raptors success has to be attributed to DeRozan's willingness and effectiveness shooting the three.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbamidseason18/chart2.png&quot; alt=&quot;DeRozan aka Kobe&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;DeMar DeRozan's career 3 point shooting (Source: Basketball-Reference)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Unless Carmelo is willing to change his game and act more as a spot up shooter for Westbrook and George, we may have seen the last of Carmelo as an elite NBA scorer. Looking at his 156th rank PER is not an indictment on Carmelo, but more so a reflection on how the NBA has evolved and how the ball stopping wing player is no longer effective in the league today. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Timberwolves and the Andrew Wiggins Question&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The Timberwolves currently sit at the fourth seed in the West and finally appear to be utilizing their talent effectively. Typically with Tom Thibodeau teams defense and heavy minutes for starters is the norm. For instance he orchestrated the defensive schemes for the Celtics back in 2008-2009 and created a strong defensive foundation during his time in Chicago. Complaints that he plays his starters too many minutes have been well documented throughout his time as head coach. If you need more convincing take a look at the following chart (or just ask Derrick Rose about his knees).   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbamidseason18/chart3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Spooky Wolves Stats&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Three Minnesota players are in the top 20 in minutes per game. (Source: NBA.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    It is evident that during Thibodeau's time in Minnesota and Chicago, his players have consistently been among the league leaders in minutes per game. For instance Luol Deng, during his time on the Bulls, never averaged less than 37.9 minutes per game from the four seasons spanning 2009 to 2013 (though I think Deng is doing just fine now that the Lakers are paying him $18 million a year to stay at home). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    However, with the Timberwolves what really interests me is not the heavy minutes or defense, but instead the team's offense. Early in the season Towns and Wiggins were the two highest scorers for the team and Butler was definitely taking a step back offensively. The team hovered around .500 early on in the season. Around December (conveniently when rumblings about Jimmy Butler and Taj Gibson calling out Towns' effort on defense surfaced) the team started to turn around mostly because Butler started to take the lead role as the primary scorer on offense. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbamidseason18/chart4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jimmy G. Buckets stats&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Jimmy Butler's scoring increase by month (Source: ESPN.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    What remains the biggest question is how the team plans to use their $150 million forward, Andrew Wiggins. The Timberwolves are performing better with Butler leading the offense and Wiggins settling more as a spot up shooter and cutter to the basket. However, with Wiggins shooting only 32.2% from three and struggling on the defensive end (even though he was projected to be a great defender out of Kansas), it begs the question of how Thibodeau plans on using Wiggins going forward. Would he consider trading Wiggins for some solid role players to fill out the bench and therefore lessen the minutes for Butler and Towns? I would not advocate trading away a 21 year old with the potential that Wiggins has, but it will be interesting to see how Wiggins fits in with the Butler-led offense going forward and into the playoffs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Hook shots are cool again?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Three pointers are cool, fancy layups and 3-point plays are great, but sometimes I wish the NBA did not feel so one dimensional in terms of teams only shooting threes or shots in the paint. Of course, if the team has the personnel of the Warriors or Rockets it makes sense to shoot almost 50% of your shots from three, but when I watch the league it feels like many front offices and coaching staffs are trying to fit players in a system that doesn't fit their playing style. For example, there's no reason that a team like Dallas or Chicago, with their personnel, should be shooting over 30 threes per game. It would be great to see some more midrange game, more post-ups and attention to great footwork. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    One of my favorite aspects of the season is seeing the resurgence of the running hook shot. Watching players like Kyle Kuzma and Ben Simmons attempt the shot exemplifies the skill and finesse moves that make the NBA great. The running hook shots that stick out to me this season are not the traditional baby hook shots that many post players shoot today (the one where the player gets the ball at the block about 5 feet from the basket, takes a couple power dribbles to the center of the key, and flings a mini hook shot). The shots that I am referring to are the ones where the offensive player starts with the ball outside the paint, takes 3 to 4 dribbles and floats in a high arching shot like Kuzma and Simmons in the videos below. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cq956iN-zlU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/f8XTJYhAB4w&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    In the modern NBA, watching teams like the Rockets that live off dribble drives for three pointers (or that stand around while Harden flails his arms to draw fouls) can get repetitive. It has been refreshing to see young players show off their skill by attempting and converting finesse shots like the running hook. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The second half of the season will surely bring more drama and excitement on top of what has already been a great season. There has already been so many storylines (the Rockets/Clippers (fake) fight, Jason Kidd getting fired) and the trade deadline will hopefully bring many more. Going forward it will be interesting to see what teams will challenge the Warriors out West and whether the Celtics or Raptors will finally dethrone Lebron in the East. But with all that said, does anybody really see a team that will beat the Warriors four times out of seven games? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        (Sources: Basketball-Reference, ESPN, NBA.com)
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ronaq Virdi</name></author><summary type="html">The All Star lineups have been announced, most teams have played well over 45 games, we finally have a team openly tanking, and the Cavs all hate each other. So with that it's safe to say that the midway point of the NBA season has come and now would be a great time to reflect on the past couple months of the 2017-2018 season. By now everyone knows how great the Warriors are, how dysfunctional LeBron's team is, and that the Sacramento Kings are once again irrelevant. I wanted to take this time to deviate away from the major storylines in the season thus far and analyze some trends, statistics, coaching decisions, and quite simply things that really stand out to me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An In-Depth Analysis of Stan Wawrinka</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wawrinka" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An In-Depth Analysis of Stan Wawrinka" /><published>2018-01-27T22:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-27T22:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wawrinka</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wawrinka">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/wawrinka.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stan Wawrinka&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Stan Wawrinka hoisting his first ever U.S. Open trophy (Photo by Elsa/Getty Images)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    In the era of the Big Four, tennis has seldom seen a Grand Slam Championship claimed by a player not named Novak Djokovic, Roger Federer, Andy Murray, or Rafael Nadal. The Big Four have won 50 of the last 58 Grand Slam tournaments, dating back to the 2003 Wimbledon. Ever since then, the spotlight in men’s tennis has only shifted between these four champions. With a combined career record of 3443-782 (81.5%) and a combined total of $377,087,356 in prize money, the Big Four have dominated tennis in a way never before seen in the sport. However, despite such dominance, it may be time to start considering that world tennis may really have a Big Five.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Of the 8 Grand Slam trophies that weren’t hoisted by a member of tennis’ elite quartet, only one player has won more than one: Stan Wawrinka. Winning the 2014 Australian Open, 2015 French Open, and 2016 U.S. Open, all against the incumbent ATP world number 1 (each a Big Four member), Wawrinka has made an interesting case to be categorized with the rest of the Big Four. In the Winter of 2017, at the age of 32, Wawrinka nearly opted to retire after a knee surgery that ended his 2017 campaign. If he were to retire, where would his career stack up against those of the Big Four? Looking closely at Wawrinka’s career, it is clear that he has not exhibited the same dominance as the Big Four, but his level of play at times may be the closest resemblance to a member of the Big Four since the group took the reigns of the men’s game in 2003.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Consistently Inconsistent&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    A late bloomer, Stan did not win his first Grand Slam until he was 28 years old. Up until that point, he had only ever made it to one semi-final of a Grand Slam (U.S. Open, 2013). By the time he captured his first Slam, the Big Four already had total control of the sport, having won a combined total of 38 Slams. Wawrinka has not been able to make up for this late arrival to the party, for he has not won more Grand Slams than any member of the Big Four:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    With Djokovic, Federer, and Nadal in double digits and Murray winning the Wimbledon twice alongside his U.S. Open title, it is clear that Wawrinka should not be placed above any member of the Big Four in terms of Slam success. While he may have as many Slam titles as Andy Murray, there are other aspects of the careers of the Big Four that put them in a league of their own, apart from Wawrinka.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/novak.png&quot; alt=&quot;Novak Djokovic&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Novak Djokovic hoisting the ATP World Tour Finals Trophy (from bettingtips365.net)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The ATP World Tour is comprised of many singles tournaments apart from Grand Slams. Alongside the four Slams, the tour each year contains 9 ATP Masters 1000 tournaments, 13 ATP 500 series tournaments, and 40 ATP 250 series tournaments throughout the year. The Big Four have dominated on all of these levels, while Wawrinka pales in comparison:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Total ATP Titles&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Although Wawrinka has won as many Slams as Murray, Murray and the rest of the Big Four have displayed unparalleled victory throughout their careers in all other phases of the tour as well. But a comparison of total singles titles still does not cover the substantially large gap between the Big Four and Wawrinka. Any top rated player can win a singles title with a week or two of exceptional tennis (most tournaments are just one week long), so it is also important to consider success in individual marquee matchups as well as the quality of opposition that the Big Four and Wawrinka have played. Here are the winning percentages of these five men against players who were ranked in the top 10 at the time of the match:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Winning Percentage&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The Big Four win well above 50% of such matches, while Wawrinka is below 40%. To place these percentages and overall significance of performances in individual matches into grand perspective, one only needs to turn to the Elo ratings. The Elo ratings rate players solely on the quality of their opposition in every match throughout their careers, irrespective of the round or tournament that each match took place. Here are the cumulative Elo rankings of active men’s tennis players:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elo&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Players ranked by Elo&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The Big Four live up to the name, as they are the top four Elo ranked players on tour by more than 100 points. Wawrinka, however, sits at ninth place, once again miles behind any kind of Big Five.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/winners.png&quot; alt=&quot;Winners&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Big Four have been able to defeat one another in Grand Slam finals (from howtheyplay.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Despite his lacking in every comparison with the Big Four thus far, to truly put himself in a position to be on the same level as the Big Four, Wawrinka must at least be able to compete against them in individual matchups. If he has a strong track record against the Big Four over his career, he may have a case to make. Placing Wawrinka in a group of five along with the members of the Big Four, here are the win percentages of each of these five men against the other four: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/stats.png&quot; alt=&quot;Win Percentage&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The Big Four have competed against one another relatively well, with Djokovic, Federer, and Nadal winning above 50% of these matches and Murray winning 37.9%. Wawrinka has not come close to matching that level of competition against them, winning merely 22.6% of his matches against the Big Four and having a losing record against every one of them. But even this poor showing in individual matches against the Big Four is still not the most glaring issue when considering Wawrinka’s place among them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The word that many people associate with the Big Four is “dominance”. Federer, Nadal, Djokovic, and Murray have not only dominated the sport for over a decade, but also consistently done so. This is where Wawrinka’s biggest shortcoming becomes clear. In the last thirteen years, no player outside of the Big Four has held the coveted ATP World Number 1 ranking. Each of the Big Four have not only reached the top of the ATP rankings, but have also held that spot for a substantial amount of time. Wawrinka is still yet to even be ranked number 2 in the world (his career high ranking is number 3 on 27 January 2014): 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/weeks1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Weeks at Number 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The World Number 1 ranking does not simply answer the question “Who is the best tennis player in the world?”. It answers the question of which player has demonstrated the most consistency across all phases of the ATP tour in a given calendar year. The Big Four have all done this for large chunks of weeks, sometimes years, at a time. The rankings are updated every Monday of the year, but Wawrinka has never hit the number 1 mark once. This signifies his lack of consistency and ability to keep up the brilliant tennis that he has put on display at times. Tennis is a taxing sport. Mentally and physically, fatigue can lower players’ performance levels as the year-long grind of tournaments and frequent traveling eventually catches up to them. Wawrinka may understandably be a victim of such fatigue as each tournament passes, but the Big Four have proven to be immortal to such things. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/wimbledon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wimbledon Winners&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Left to right: Federer, Nadal, Djokovic, and Murray each holding the prestigious Wimbledon Championship trophy (from tt.tennis-warehouse.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    In essentially every phase of the sport, the Big Four are in a world of their own, far away from every other player on Earth, and that includes Stan Wawrinka. There was never a Big Five and there likely will never be one in this golden age of men’s tennis. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/vilas.png&quot; alt=&quot;Guillermo Vilas&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;(By Verhoeff, Bert / Anefo)  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/kodes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jan Kodes&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;(from Getty/Pat Scala) &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/stanslice.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stan Slicing a Ball&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;(from kodes-tennis.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    While he may not be near the Big Four in any way, Wawrinka is certainly the closest to knocking on the door, for he has set many interesting and accomplished records in tennis history. He is the only player to have won multiple Grand Slam titles in Slams that featured all members of the Big Four. Although the number 1 ranking continues to elude Wawrinka, he may possibly go down as the greatest player to have never reached the apex of men’s tennis. The only man to have not only amassed more Grand Slam titles but also to have never been ranked world number 1 is Argentine player Guillermo Vilas (left), who won 4 Grand Slam titles and only reached a career-high ranking of 2, despite significant controversy. By the end of his career, Vilas had made 8 Grand Slam finals, facing similarly high qualities of opposition with the likes of Bjorn Borg, Jimmy Connors, and Mats Wilander. Intriguingly, Wawrinka can be thought of as the modern version of Guillermo Vilas in men’s tennis. Neither Vilas nor Wawrinka have won a Wimbledon title. Both have excelled on clay, possess a one-handed backhand, and a baseline-dominant play style. The following charts below show that both have enjoyed relatively similar success in Grand Slam tournaments. Unlike Wawrinka’s late blossoming, Vilas’ came during his mid-to-late twenties:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Vilas&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/vilasrecord.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vilas record&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Wawrinka&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/stanrecord.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stan's record&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wawrinka is the first player in the Open Era since Jan Kodeš (right) to have won 3 Grand Slam singles titles without ever being ranked higher than world number 3. Kodes never won a U.S. Open, let alone even played in an Australian Open. Furthermore, Kodes never beat an incumbent world number 1 in any of his 3 Grand Slam championships. Here is a rankings trendline of the three players by age:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/atpchart.png&quot; alt=&quot;ATP Rankings&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    A potential Wimbledon title in the future for Wawrinka would not just make him the first of these 3 players to complete the Career Grand Slam, but also make him only the 9th man in history to do so.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/stanwins.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stan Winning a Clay court title&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;(from tennisworldusa.org)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    There is no doubt that Wawrinka is a fantastic tennis player and a champion in his own right. To compare him to the Big Four would be a disservice to him, as the seemingly unfair control that the Big Four have had over tennis make his very significant accomplishments seem far less significant. He does not belong with the Big Four, but the fact that he has accomplished as much as he has in such an era says a lot about his ability to make the most of the hand that he has been dealt. Looking ahead, Stan Wawrinka’s days on the ATP tour might be numbered, but his inconsistency and unpredictability may just result in even more unprecedented success in an already decorated career.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
            Sources: ATP, tennisabstract.com
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Kathir Ilango and Kevin Hahn</name></author><summary type="html">In the era of the Big Four, tennis has seldom seen a Grand Slam Championship claimed by a player not named Novak Djokovic, Roger Federer, Andy Murray, or Rafael Nadal. The Big Four have won 50 of the last 58 Grand Slam tournaments, dating back to the 2003 Wimbledon. Ever since then, the spotlight in men’s tennis has only shifted between these four champions. With a combined career record of 3443-782 (81.5%) and a combined total of $377,087,356 in prize money, the Big Four have dominated tennis in a way never before seen in the sport. However, despite such dominance, it may be time to start considering that world tennis may really have a Big Five.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One-on-one: Tyreke Evans works his way back to relevance, Nicolas Batum having worst season since rookie year</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/oneonone" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One-on-one: Tyreke Evans works his way back to relevance, Nicolas Batum having worst season since rookie year" /><published>2018-01-25T22:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-25T22:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/oneonone</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/oneonone">&lt;h4&gt;Tyreke Evans&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oneonone/reke.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tyreke Evans&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Tyreke Evans has shattered expectations in the 2017-2018 NBA season. (Justin Ford/USA Today Sports)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        In 2010, Tyreke Evans appeared to have a bright future ahead in the NBA-- he was named Rookie of the Year after joining Michael Jordan, LeBron James, and Oscar Robertson as the only rookies to average 20 points, 5 rebounds, and 5 assists. But in recent years, Evans' career had taken a turn for the worst. He missed 99 games between 2015 and 2017 with right knee issues. Last season, on an expiring contract, he was included in the package New Orleans sent to Sacramento in the DeMarcus Cousins trade. Evans recorded season lows in points and minutes across 40 games with New Orleans and Sacramento. In the offseason, Memphis inked the versatile 28 year-old guard to a team-friendly one-year, $3.3 million deal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Now halfway through the season, Evans is looking like one of the biggest steals of the summer. Evans has experienced a revival with the Grizzlies, putting up 19.8 points, 5.1 rebounds, and 4.6 assists per game. Not only are his counting stats up from previous years, but his player impact estimate (PIE) is at a career high, and ranks ninth in the league, according to NBA.com. PIE measures a player's positive contributions compared to their team's total positive contributions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        The resurgence of Evans' well-rounded game isn't due to him receiving more minutes with his new team-- this season he's logging 30.9 minutes per game, the fourth lowest mark of his nine year career. And the University of Memphis product's usage rate is only three percent higher than his career average.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Part of Evans' elevated performance can be attributed to him being healthy. After missing an average of nearly fifty games the past two seasons, he's sat out just one contest this season due to hip soreness. This extended stretch of good health has enabled Evans to settle in and find a groove.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oneonone/herecomesaustinrivers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tyreke Evans and Austin Rivers&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Tyreke Evans has excelled at the point guard position while Mike Conley has been sidelined. (AP Photo/Michael Owen Baker)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        While Evans has been healthy, Memphis' franchise point guard Mike Conley has not had the same good fortune. With Conley in street clothes for 30 games so far, Evans has stepped into the lead guard role for interim head coach J.B. Bickerstaff without missing a beat. Taking advantage of the wealth of offensive opportunities in Conley's absence, Evans' two-point, three-point, free throw, and effective field goal percentages of 46.7/40.6/79.0/53.7 are all within the top two seasons of his career. Illustrating how elite Evans has been with the basketball, he ranks fourth in pick-and-roll efficiency, trailing only James, Steph Curry, and Bradley Beal.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
        With the losses piling up and the Grizzlies effectively out of contention for the Western Conference eighth seed, Evans' name has been heard on the rumor mill for weeks as the trade deadline approaches. His shooting and ability to defend three positions could make him an attractive target for legitimate contenders like Cleveland and Boston looking to level the field with Golden State. Evans' scoring and expiring contract make him worth a look for teams trying to make the leap into contention like Oklahoma City, Minnesota, and Denver. Whether he winds up getting moved or stays put in Memphis, Evans' play has hushed his critics for now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Nicolas Batum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oneonone/batum.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nicolas Batum&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Nicolas Batum has underperformed ever since he signed his 5 year contract in 2015. (Joe Murphy/Getty Images)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Nicolas Batum has seemed to be at the edge of being a breakout star for the majority of his career. He came out of the 2011-2012 campaign at 23 years old, averaging 14 points per game (2 above his career average), shooting 45% from the field, adding 4.6 rebounds and 1.5 assists per game. The French swingman's promise was affirmed before the 2012-2013 season, when Portland was forced to match Minnesota's four year, $46 million offer to retain him. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Batum has flown under the radar for much of the last few years, not having reached max contract status or contributed to a legitimate title contender. He has solid career averages of 12 ppg, 5.3 rpg, 3.7 apg, and 31.6 minutes per game. He ranks 42nd in career minutes per game among active players, ahead of All-Stars Anthony Davis, Giannis Antetokounmpo, and Tony Parker. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        In 2014-15, Batum had a down year, averaging only 9.4 points but adding 5.9 rebounds and 4.8 assists. Despite the drop off in scoring, Charlotte believed he had the potential to be a key contributor, and rewarded the then-26 year old with a 5 year, $120 million contract. The large payday makes Batum's regression this season even more stark. In almost every statistical category, this season's numbers are below his career averages- 2 less points per game, 1 less rebound per game, and his shooting percentage has fallen by 3 percent. Compared his first two years in Charlotte, this year Batum is averaging 4.1 less points, 2 less rebounds, 1.2 less assists, and 3.4 less minutes per game. His three point percentage has dropped under 30% for the first time in his career, and his free throw shooting has declined by nearly 5%.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Advanced stats like player efficiency rating (PER), which standardizes all NBA players' stats so that the average is 15, serve as an even stronger indicator of Batum falling short of expectations. His PER this year is 11.4, a career low, even 1.5 below that of his rookie season, and ranks in the high 30s for all shooting guards. This is the first season his box plus minus has been below 1, currently at -0.3, meaning he provides his team 0.3 less points per 100 possessions than the statistically-modeled league average player. Batum has a true shooting percentage (calculated to account for the higher point value of three pointers and lower value of free throws) 3% lower than the worst full season of his career. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oneonone/batum2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nicolas Batum Hurt&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Nicolas Batum injured his left elbow during a preseason game against the Pistons. (AP Photo/Carlos Osorio)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Charlotte certainly hopes Batum's rocky start to this season was simply a fluke caused by injuries early on. He missed the first month of the season with a left elbow injury, and missed two additional games due to lingering issues with the elbow. Even being healthy since late November, since his return Batum is still is only averaging 10 points per game.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Another possibility for Batum's lackluster showing thus far is Charlotte's play style. Batum is playing most of his minutes at shooting guard, which usually means a larger lineup with fewer shooters on the floor. While he was surrounded by snipers in his Portland tenure, Batum has always been aggressive slashing to the basket. But the lack of spacing and clogging of the lane caused by bigger lineups this year with Charlotte has made it more difficult for Batum to attack the rim. This has been evidenced by his decrease in trips to the free throw line, attempting half as many per game than last year. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        The Hornets are facing a dilemma with their $120 million man. Should they let him try to ride out this slump, demote him to a bench role to see if he plays better against opposing second units, or must they package him with an asset to unload his burdensome contract? Facing other questions, including whether to keep Kemba Walker, expect Charlotte to be active around the February 8th trade deadline.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
                Sources: Basketball-reference, ESPN, NBA
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Messinger, Zane Winston, Albert Pan</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>