<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-03-10T16:00:12-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bruin Sports Analytics</title><author><name>Bruin Sports Analytics</name></author><entry><title type="html">On the Road Again: The Myth of Neutrality in NHL Scheduling</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/nhl_scheduling" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the Road Again: The Myth of Neutrality in NHL Scheduling" /><published>2019-03-10T15:48:34-07:00</published><updated>2019-03-10T15:48:34-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nhl_scheduling</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/nhl_scheduling">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhl_scheduling/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The Canadian Press&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the NHL season inching closer to the playoffs, the format of the regular season is perhaps not the first thought on most fans' minds. However, this year's notable lack of inter-conference parity has drawn attention from casual and knowledgeable fans alike -- the point cutoff to make the playoffs in the Eastern Conference is currently on pace to be a relatively standard 96 points; the Western Conference, on the other hand, is on pace to have an 83 point cutoff. This would easily be the lowest bar to qualify for the postseason in the salary cap era. An 83 point team under most circumstances has well below a winning record, and would be over six games back from the eighth seed in the East. These anomalies beg the question: what factors influence a team's record at the end of the season?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhl_scheduling//pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although skill contributes the most to a team's end-of-season record, there is always some element of luck involved. Most of the luck is &quot;earned luck,&quot; the type of luck you see when a player hits the inside of the post on a breakaway right before the other team heads down the ice and scores. It's unlucky, but if the players aim had been one centimeter better the score would've reflected it. Another type of luck has nothing to do with the on-ice play at all. In fact, it is created before the season even starts, in the form of team schedules. There is no doubt that NHL scheduling is flawed at least slightly, but it is harder to determine the extent of which it is flawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that the NHL schedule is imperfect is by no means a groundbreaking claim. A perfect schedule is a rabbit hole theoretically and impossible logistically. It is, however, entirely possible to create a better schedule than the one currently in use. It should be asked, of course, what makes one schedule &quot;better&quot; than another? There are two important attributes: game balance and overall fairness. Ideal game balance would have both teams in each individual game having a theoretical 50% probability to win without regard to the actual skill of the teams. This sounds easy enough, but practically this is never true. The home team, on average, wins about 55% of NHL games, and on some nights one team will have played the prior evening and flew in the same day with little rest. Even with functionally identically-skilled teams, true 50% win probability does not really exist. Thus, focus must be placed on overall fairness of the schedule as well. Does it matter much that the home team wins more on average than the away team if, at the end of the season, each team has played the same number of home and away games? The goal of schedule-making should be to first maximize game balance, and what randomness is left over should be minimized by the overall fairness of the season. How well does the NHL achieve these goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, game balance is greatly impacted by the existence of home/away games. Of course, there is no way to feasibly prevent the impact of playing on home ice, but it should be noted that not all away games are created equal. Growing up as a southern California hockey fan, I would frequently hear disdain for how the Los Angeles Kings and Anaheim Ducks were treated &quot;unfairly&quot; by the schedule-makers. Southern California fans dread road trips. As a general rule, the road trips that teams in the Western Conference take tend to be long and drawn out. Eastern teams, on the other hand, experience short, frequent road trips that alternate with short homestands. Analysis of this distinction between Western and Eastern teams is not necessary; it is clear that the number and length of road trips taken by different teams is decidedly unequal, as seen below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhl_scheduling//pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of road trips a team must take in a season varies from as few as 12 to as many as 24. The schedules these teams are given before the season begins cause drastically different playing experiences. The announcement that the NHL was expanding into Seattle in upcoming years brought this issue to light. Due to its location, Seattle would clearly be expected to be placed in the NHL's Pacific division. However, the Pacific, along with the Metropolitan and the Atlantic divisions, already contains eight teams, while the Central division only has seven. To facilitate Seattle, the Arizona Coyotes were selected to be moved from the Pacific division to the Central; however, this change angered Coyotes fans, as the move would result in a significant increase of travel time over the course of a season, likely resulting in longer average road trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine the effect of these differences, I gathered data from every regular season game in the salary cap era (that is, the 2005-06 season and beyond). The length of the road trip was introduced into the data by assigning a number to each of the 31,042 games (Note that each game was counted twice, once from the perspective of the home team and once from the away team). If the game was played at home, it was assigned a 0. The first game of each road trip was assigned a 1, the second game was assigned a 2, etc. Both the win-rate and average goal differential were determined for each group of games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhl_scheduling//pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, despite the clear difference in the experiences of playing the first and last game of two-week long road trips that cover upwards of seven different cities in two countries, the numbers do not show any sort of trend that would suggest a team is more or less likely to win any given away game. The goal differential shows similar results:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhl_scheduling//pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NHL, be it by design or by luck, has generated a system that, despite different teams playing under completely different travelling schedules, does not sacrifice overall season fairness. Fans' intuition that the southern California teams were punished by being forced to play much longer road trips than other teams was incorrect. The length of road trips does not affect team win-rate. The anger of Arizona Coyotes fans can be at least partially squelched. In similar fashion and with similar results, the length of homestands was also analyzed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhl_scheduling//pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhl_scheduling//pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it is certainly encouraging to know that the manner in which a team's home and away games are composed in a season is not particularly important with regards to overall fairness, it is still clear in these charts that the balance of individual games is not at all perfect. It might not matter where the previous games were played, but regardless, the home team scores on average a third of a goal more than their opponents and, as a result, win a bit over 55% of their games. On top of the regular advantage stemming from just playing at home, the NHL provides minor advantages in the rules to the home team, such as the ability to make the last line change at every whistle. Despite this, the home-ice advantage has made less and less of an impact over recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhl_scheduling//pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the importance of home games on the decline and the influence of road trip length nearly nonexistent, it seems fair to say that the NHL has produced a remarkably unbiased schedule. This would not be entirely correct. One variable that has a historically strong effect on team win-rate is the number of days a team gets to rest in between games. There is little difference between the performance of teams after one, two, or even five days of rest, but when teams have to play games with no day of rest in between, win-rate drops by about 5%. These back-to-back games are a byproduct of the logistics involved in creating 82-game seasons for 31 different teams that each have their own arenas scattered across a continent -- the arenas often having other events or even one or two other professional teams that occupy scheduling time. Though unavoidable, we would expect that the NHL would have each team play the same amount of back-to-back games. This is not the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhl_scheduling//pic_8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in the chart, the number of back-to-back games a team plays in a season can vary from as little as nine to as many as sixteen. The amount of these games is also distributed rather uniformly; it is not as if there are several teams with the same number and only a few differ. Back-to-back games in a season grants some teams a points expected value which can be multiple points higher than other teams before even factoring in skill. This is a league where it is commonplace for teams to miss the playoffs by a single point -- just look at the Florida Panthers and the St. Louis Blues last season. The failure to standardize back-to-back games is much more impactful to seasons than it reasonably should be. Because they cannot be avoided, the NHL should more strictly adhere to two strategies to minimize their effect: make each team play the same number of back-to-backs, and more frequently schedule teams on back-to-backs to play each other. The first maximizes the overall fairness of the season, and the second cancels out the negative effect altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, while a perfectly balanced schedule is the dream of many fans and analysts alike, it is unlikely the NHL deems maximal balance a priority. The divisional realignment of the 2013-14 season highlights the blatant disregard for unbiased scheduling. Even with a theoretically perfect schedule, it is of little benefit when the top two teams in the league are forced to play each other in the second round of the playoffs. Such a scenario has become almost expected in the last few years, and with the massive discrepancy between divisions seen this year and the plans to continue the format in the upcoming expansion, future considerations toward maximum game balance from the NHL seem grim. Nevertheless, it does not take complete realignment of formats to help fix the NHL schedule, but a change of philosophy. Even if the league does not care much about the vastly different playoff pictures of the two conferences, the schedules for the 2019-20 season should be made with reduction in back-to-back games in mind. Since the data shows that a consistent travel schedule is not necessary to create a level playing field , the NHL could take more risk with the schedule by varying the length of homestands and road trips in an attempt at making the overall season more equitable and minimizing the effect of the &quot;schedule losses&quot; resulting from back-to-back games. But until the NHL is willing to make such changes, the old adage remains; all is fair in love and war, but, for now at least, not in hockey.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Dunham</name></author><summary type="html">With the NHL season inching closer to the playoffs, the format of the regular season is perhaps not the first thought on most fans' minds. However, this year's notable lack of inter-conference parity has drawn attention from casual and knowledgeable fans alike -- the point cutoff to make the playoffs in the Eastern Conference is currently on pace to be a relatively standard 96 points; the Western Conference, on the other hand, is on pace to have an 83 point cutoff. This would easily be the lowest bar to qualify for the postseason in the salary cap era. An 83 point team under most circumstances has well below a winning record, and would be over six games back from the eighth seed in the East. These anomalies beg the question&amp;#58; what factors influence a team's record at the end of the season?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Happens to Jim Harbaugh in Big Games?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Harbaugh" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Happens to Jim Harbaugh in Big Games?" /><published>2019-02-13T22:45:43-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-13T22:45:43-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Harbaugh</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Harbaugh">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image9.png&quot; alt=&quot;pic 1&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing the 2010 NFL season with a losing record yet again, the San Francisco 49ers finally decided it was time for a new head coach. They needed to win games to become relevant again and, more importantly, they needed to bring life back to a fan base that had not had a winning team since 2002. So they went with a man whom they thought could bring all of that to the table: Jim Harbaugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having coached a dominant Stanford football team for years in the Pac-12, the former quarterback was primed for a head coaching job in the NFL. He brought an energy and intensity that the Forty-Niner Faithful had not seen for a very long time and in his first season, he took the Niners to the playoffs with a record of 13-3. They ultimately lost the NFC championship game to the New York Giants, but Harbaugh was the Coach of the Year and the Niners were once again in the mix of legitimate contenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image15.png&quot; alt=&quot;pic 2&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very next season, after the injury of his starting quarterback midway through the season, Harbaugh saw an opportunity for even more growth and engineered the most versatile offense in the NFL with Colin Kaepernick, a hot talent from Nevada, at the wheel. The Niners eventually found themselves in Super Bowl XLVII against the Baltimore Ravens, where they would come within five yards of the trophy but eventually lose to the AFC champs. They were back in full form in 2013 but once again fell just short, this time in the NFC Championship to the Seattle Seahawks. After an injury-riddled 2014 campaign and issues within the front office, Harbaugh and the Niners organization decided to mutually part ways, but Harbaugh still had a lot of coaching left in him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image10.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made one of the biggest splashes in college football when he announced that he would be coaching at his alma mater, the University of Michigan. With the school's excitement through the roof, Harbaugh took the losing Wolverines to the Big Ten Championship game where he would lose to the dominant Ohio State University, but go on to win the Citrus Bowl against Florida. Each year for the next three years, Harbaugh's season ended with the same result: a loss in the Big Ten Championship to Ohio State followed by a loss in a bowl game, which brings us to the present day. Jim Harbaugh is clearly an exceptional football coach, but one glaring pattern hovers over that excellence: he's never won the big game, whether it be a Super Bowl, a national title, or even a Big Ten title. So, the big question here is rather simple: why? What goes wrong for him year after year that keeps him from entering the circle of championship head coaches? Football is certainly a random and difficult sport, but considering how close he has come for so many years, it's intriguing that he may walk away from his coaching career with nothing but a Citrus Bowl trophy. To derive any kind of explanation for this, it's important to try and have a complete understanding of exactly what kind of coach Jim Harbaugh is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image13.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;The Steroid Effect&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it is in the college or professional ranks, Harbaugh has demonstrated the ability to tremendously increase the quality of his team upon arrival:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image11.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immediate spike in regular season wins from the year before Harbaugh's arrival to his first year as head coach is clear with both the Niners and the Wolverines. There are of course many factors not related to coaching that could have caused this; often times a team can experience a turnaround as a result of some key personnel changes or recovering injured players that significantly improve the roster heading into the next season. But a closer look shows that Harbaugh was able to take squads with few expectations and low ratings, and raise their quality to elite levels. Below is a chart of the ratings of all NFL teams based on roster and performance as per this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pro-football-reference.com/blog/index4837.html?p=37&quot;&gt;Simple Rating System&lt;/a&gt; in 2010 versus in 2011 (Harbaugh's first year in San Francisco):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the dashed line representing no change in a team's quality from 2010 to 2011, Harbaugh's 49ers exceeded their previous season's performance more than any other team in the NFL. Their SRS improved by 14.1 points, 2 points more than the next best improvement. And four years later, the exact same thing happened in Ann Arbor. Below is the same metric, this time from 2014 to 2015 (Harbaugh's first year at Michigan) with all CFB teams from the Power Five Conferences shown:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the 49ers being in the unpredictable league that is the NFL and Michigan having a drastically new roster from year to year (as is the nature of college sports), the one thing that these clubs had in common in their sudden jolts of success was Jim Harbaugh. They didn't just improve in Harbaugh's first year; they were among the highest-rated teams in their respective leagues, with the Niners being ranked 2nd in the NFC and Michigan being ranked 12th in the country. It is no coincidence that Harbaugh was the head coach as they both suddenly went from irrelevance to championship contention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Late Season Failure&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being in championship contention is one thing and being a champion is another. Despite doing the former in an impressive fashion, Harbaugh has never really been able to do the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In football, all games are subject to many factors that have absolutely nothing to do with coaching. From injuries to terrible refereeing to crowd noise, there are many ways for a football team to lose that do not result from coaching decisions. It's entirely possible that Jim Harbaugh is just the most unlucky coach of the decade when it comes to high-stakes football games, but that seems unlikely and rather bland. Thankfully, upon research, there &lt;i&gt;does&lt;/i&gt; appear to be something interesting happening with Harbaugh's play calling in big games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Splitting offensive play calling in the most basic way, passing and running, the charts below show the play selection of NFL teams and Big Ten teams in the Jim Harbaugh eras:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Football is played differently in the professional ranks versus in college and the game in general has evolved over the last 8 years, but one thing is clear: Jim Harbaugh loves running the ball. The Niners under him were one of just two teams in his era that ran the ball more than they threw it. It's the focal point of his offense and he's been more committed to it than almost every other team in his league in both the NFL and NCAA. But when it comes to important games (playoff games, Big Ten title games, and bowl games), that commitment seems to disappear:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image14.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harbaugh has coached 8 big games with the Niners and 8 with Michigan. With both teams, 7 of those 8 games featured a running percentage lower than every regular season game that year. A man who called running plays 52.3% of the time with the Niners and 59.1% of the time with the Wolverines dropped to 44.1% and 44.8% respectively in big games. This pattern is simply too glaring to ignore, and upon deeper research into these big games, an even more conclusive pattern is uncovered regarding key drives in these games. For the purpose of this article, we define a 'key drive' as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A drive on which a team must score points, whether it is to take a late lead, maintain a late lead, stay in the game, and/or reverse the momentum of the game&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A drive where the clock is not yet a factor that affects play calling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of importance is the fact that by this definition time is not a factor, so a run percentage is not skewed by the fact that when time is low, a coach will either be more inclined or less inclined than usual to run the ball depending on the score. It is also important to note that there are multiple drives per game that can be considered key drives as per the provided definition. Since the point here is to simply look at the more important drives of these important games, only one key drive from each of Harbaugh's big games is listed below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image12.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examining his run percentage in these specific drives, his apparent tendency to call significantly fewer running plays in big games becomes even more clear:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While nothing can be determined with absolute certainty in football, the pattern here is quite clear. In important games Harbaugh runs the ball far less than usual, and in the important moments of those important games he runs it even less than &lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt;. The 44.1% and 44.8% that he dropped to in big games with the Niners and Wolverines respectively became 22.3% and 24.1% in those key drives. In a couple of those drives, he didn't even run the ball at all. While Harbaugh has still won big games this way, it's not sustainable because it's simply not his identity, hence his failure every year to go all the way. He seems to get way more trigger-happy on the big stage, wanting to put the ball in his quarterback's hands and move it through the air in large chunks rather than methodically move it on the ground as he's used to doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/harbaugh/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's actually rather suiting. Jim Harbaugh can be described as an incredibly powerful steroid; he enters the locker room of a mediocre team and injects an intensity and attitude that immediately turns those players into winners. He wins games with old school football and dares the opposition to stop him. But when he gets to the big dances, he falls victim to himself. Perhaps his throwing the ball far more than usual in big games is the result of a million other small factors that just happen to create this coincidental pattern. But knowing Jim Harbaugh, it really isn't. It's the curse of his nature as a head coach. The very intensity and daring that brought him there undoes him as he goes one step too far, trying to win the game at the same speed with which he changed his team's fortunes when he took over. Jim Harbaugh's general coaching success can be attributed to many things, but a cool head has never been one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Ohio State head coach &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.espn.com/college-football/story/_/id/25449933/ohio-state-buckeyes-head-coach-urban-meyer-retire-coaching-rose-bowl&quot;&gt;Urban Meyer retiring&lt;/a&gt; and Clemson and Alabama not going away anytime soon, there is nothing left for Harbaugh at Michigan. It would be surprising if he's not on the move again soon, and it will be interesting to see where he ends up. The word &quot;overrated&quot; has become constantly associated with Jim Harbaugh's name, but the fact is that great football coaches are rare and there are NFL teams as well as colleges that would hire him in an instant. He may not have a great track record in postseason play, but he knows the game, he's animated on the sideline, and he winds up on national television more often than not. The entertainment value coupled with the guaranteed appearance in important games is too good to deny. Regardless of the end results, football needs Jim Harbaugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: sports-reference, pro-football-reference, ESPN&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kathir Ilango</name></author><summary type="html">After finishing the 2010 NFL season with a losing record yet again, the San Francisco 49ers finally decided it was time for a new head coach. They needed to win games to become relevant again and, more importantly, they needed to bring life back to a fan base that had not had a winning team since 2002. So they went with a man whom they thought could bring all of that to the table&amp;#58; Jim Harbaugh.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Anthony Davis and the Pelicans Failed</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/adPelicansFailure" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Anthony Davis and the Pelicans Failed" /><published>2019-02-09T14:45:54-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-09T14:45:54-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/adPelicansFailure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/adPelicansFailure">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ad_pels/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having one of the top-five players in the NBA, the New Orleans Pelicans struggled for seven years to surround &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203076/&quot;&gt;Anthony Davis&lt;/a&gt; with enough talent to consistently make the playoffs. In 2015, the Pelicans - without &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/201950/&quot;&gt;Jrue Holiday&lt;/a&gt; - were swept by the first iteration of the current Warriors Dynasty. Davis's only other postseason appearance came in 2018, when the Pelicans upset the 3-seed Portland Trailblazers in a stunning sweep. Although the Pelicans lost to the Warriors again in the next round, their second round exit was viewed as a success after the enormous loss of DeMarcus Cousins in late January due to a ruptured Achilles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Pelicans' success did not continue into the 2018-2019 season. After the Pelicans dropped to 22-28 and 5.5 games out of the playoffs, &quot;The Brow&quot; decided he had seen enough and requested a trade.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ad_pels/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pelicans &quot;entertained&quot; several trade offers from the Los Angeles Lakers, but ultimately decided to keep Davis until the offseason when the Celtics can enter the bidding, hoping for more lucrative offers. Davis has made it clear he intends to play for the Pelicans the rest of the season since he is still under contract, and the Pelicans &quot;plan to allow Davis back into the lineup for the rest of the season&quot;, according to Wojnarowski. Despite this, the Pelicans are still six games out of the 8-seed and behind the Kings, Lakers, Mavericks, and Timberwolves. Unless the Pelicans go an a magical run, they will likely still miss the playoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest explanation for the Pelicans' struggles this season is a constant plague of injuries to key rotation pieces. Davis, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/202703/&quot;&gt;Nikola Mirotic&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203901/&quot;&gt;Elfrid Payton&lt;/a&gt; all sustained serious injuries, missing 14, 23, and 36 games so far this season, respectively. They have only deployed one of their ideal fives of Payton, Holiday, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/202734/&quot;&gt;E'Twaun Moore&lt;/a&gt;, Mirotic/&lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203944/&quot;&gt;Julius Randle&lt;/a&gt;, and Davis in 11 games this season and were 7-4 in such games (the Pelicans dealt Nikola Mirotic to the Milwaukee Bucks on the morning of the NBA trade deadline on February 7).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But every team encounters injuries - the Nuggets led the West for most of the first half of the season despite injuries to &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203914/&quot;&gt;Gary Harris&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203115/&quot;&gt;Will Barton&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/200794/&quot;&gt;Paul Millsap&lt;/a&gt; because of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bruinsportsanalytics.com/jokicrisingstar&quot;&gt;brilliance of Nikola Jokic&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/201935/&quot;&gt;James Harden&lt;/a&gt; took injuries to &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/101108/&quot;&gt;Chris Paul&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/201569/&quot;&gt;Eric Gordon&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203991/&quot;&gt;Clint Capela&lt;/a&gt; in stride and averaged 43.6 (!) points per game in January. However, most (if not all) NBA experts would agree that Davis is a better two-way player than Jokic and Harden, so how did the Pelicans fall to the 13-seed in the Western Conference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason is the Pelicans lacked much of any depth this season beyond Davis, Holiday, Randle, and Mirotic. The Pelicans' bench only scores 30.7 points per game, ahead of only the Rockets and Warriors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E'twaun Moore was scorching from three in October and November, but has been in a major slump since. &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203121/&quot;&gt;Darius Miller&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1628402/&quot;&gt;Frank Jackson&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/204025/&quot;&gt;Tim Frazier&lt;/a&gt; have averaged 31, 20, and 17 minutes over the Pelicans' last 15 games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One bright spot is that &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1626143/&quot;&gt;Jahil Okafor&lt;/a&gt; has stepped up admirably in Davis's absence and improved his defense from &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/202683/&quot;&gt;Enes Kanter&lt;/a&gt; levels of unplayable to sneakily impressive. Opponents are shooting only 48.4% on shots within 6 feet of the rim against Okafor (a better mark than &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203497/&quot;&gt;Rudy Gobert&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1626167/&quot;&gt;Myles Turner&lt;/a&gt;, and Davis), per NBA.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pelicans' second best player, Jrue Holiday, is averaging 20.9 points, 8 assists, and 5.1 rebounds per game this season. In the last nine games without Davis, Holiday has kept the Pelicans in every game, with five of their six losses in that span decided by only six points or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When either Davis or Holiday sat out this season, the Pelicans had an abysmal point differential (points scored - points allowed): -5.1 when Holiday played without Davis and -21.4 when Davis played without Holiday. The Pelicans had a net rating[1] of 10.1 and an offensive rating of 115.3 when both Holiday and Davis shared the floor, ranking 15th and 7th in the NBA, respectively, out of 84 pairs of teammates who have played at least 1000 minutes this season, per NBA.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ad_pels/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pelicans' inability to surround Davis with consistent talent the last seven years is a result of a series of poor decisions and win-now moves. For example, in 2015, the Pelicans resigned &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/201600/&quot;&gt;Omer Asik&lt;/a&gt; to a five-year, $60 million deal and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/201582/&quot;&gt;Alexis Ajinca&lt;/a&gt; to a four-year, $20.2 million contract, severely depleting their cap space. In 2016, the Pelicans let Eric Gordon and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/201583/&quot;&gt;Ryan Anderson&lt;/a&gt; leave in free agency to become key rotation shooters for the Houston Rockets. The Pelicans also signed &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203524/&quot;&gt;Solomon Hill&lt;/a&gt; for $48 million over four years, further restricting their cap space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only first round pick New Orleans has drafted in that span was &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1627741/&quot;&gt;Buddy Hield&lt;/a&gt; in 2016, who the Pelicans proceeded to trade at the trade deadline in 2017. Hield is currently having a breakout season with the Sacramento Kings, canning 3.4 three pointers per game (behind only &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/201939/&quot;&gt;Stephen Curry&lt;/a&gt;, James Harden, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/202331/&quot;&gt;Paul George&lt;/a&gt;) on 45.5% shooting from behind the arc. Hield is a consistent threat from deep, something the Pelicans have desperately lacked around Anthony Davis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pelicans did make some good moves. Trading for DeMarcus Cousins was an unexpected gamble that looked promising until Cousins ruptured his Achilles. In the summer of 2017, the Pelicans signed &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/200765/&quot;&gt;Rajon Rondo&lt;/a&gt; to a one-year deal. Shortly after Cousins tore his Achilles, the Pelicans traded for Nikola Mirotic, who seamlessly paired alongside Anthony Davis. The quartet of Rondo, Holiday, Mirotic, and Davis propelled the Pelicans to a 20-11 record and the 6-seed in the Western Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the 2018 offseason, the Pelicans did not re-sign Rondo or Cousins (who signed with the Warriors after not receiving other serious offers), instead signing Payton and Randle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main issue with the Pelican's 2018-2019 roster was three of their best four players are most comfortable playing power forward or center, so Alvin Gentry hesitated playing Mirotic, Randle, and Davis all at the same time. In the few games between Mirotic's return and Davis's finger injury, the Pelicans experimented with an enormous lineup, featuring all of Holiday, Mirotic, Davis, and Randle at the same time. In the 58 minutes those four shared the court, the Pelicans had a net rating of 17.1 (the Warriors' lineup of Curry, Klay Thompson, Kevin Durant, and Draymond Green have a net rating of 15.1 this season). Had the Pelicans not been decimated by injuries and continued deploying their ultra-big lineup, they may have remained closer in the playoff race and Davis may have waited to divulge his desire to be traded. Instead, the Pelicans were forced to look towards the future and traded Mirotic to the Bucks for four future second round picks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ad_pels/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ad_pels/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ad_pels/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other reason for the Pelicans' struggles this season is an absurd inability to execute in close games. The Pelicans have lost 22 out of the 32 games in which the score is within five points with five minutes or less remaining, the second-worst winning percentage ahead of only the last place New York Knicks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these &quot;clutch situations&quot;, the Pelicans have been outscored by 59 points (second-worst), have a -21.5 net rating (second-worst), an offensive rating of 86.4 (worst), shot 35.6% from the field (worst), and shot 14.8% from three (worst).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pelicans foul opponents too much, with opponents attempting 7.2 free throws for every 10 field goal attempts in clutch situations, per NBA.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ad_pels/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Davis returning to the lineup, some Pelicans fans might be hoping for a magical run that lifts New Orleans back into the playoffs and changes Davis's mind about wanting a trade. ESPN's BPI Playoffs Odds estimates the Pelicans have a 9.5% chance at making the playoffs, while FiveThirtyEight projects the Pelicans to have a 12% chance of making the playoffs. If the Pelicans can stay healthy and perform better in close games, Anthony Davis is the superstar who could pull off such a ridiculous feat with only 27 games remaining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most likely ending to this fiasco is the Pelicans missing the playoffs and reopening trade discussions with teams around the draft and free agency. The Celtics hold the best potential return for Davis if they include &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1628369/&quot;&gt;Jayson Tatum&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203935/&quot;&gt;Marcus Smart&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/201143/&quot;&gt;Al Horford&lt;/a&gt;, and multiple future first round picks. The Lakers &quot;kitchen sink&quot; offer of &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1627742/&quot;&gt;Brandon Ingram&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1628366/&quot;&gt;Lonzo Ball&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1628398/&quot;&gt;Kyle Kuzma&lt;/a&gt; and their own first round picks will most likely still be available. Another team not on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ShamsCharania/status/1092505032199688192&quot;&gt;Davis's list&lt;/a&gt; may shock the league and go all-in for a year to convince Davis to resign. Regardless, the Pelicans must maximize the return on their superstar, and when they get the next &quot;Anthony Davis&quot;, they better not waste it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Statistics updated through February 6, 2019&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;________________&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Net rating is one of the best indicators of a team's success, representing the difference between a team's offensive rating and defensive rating, where offensive and defensive ratings are the number of points scored and the number of points allowed per 100 possessions, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chad Shimozaki</name></author><summary type="html">Despite having one of the top-five players in the NBA, the New Orleans Pelicans struggled for seven years to surround Anthony Davis with enough talent to consistently make the playoffs. In 2015, the Pelicans - without Jrue Holiday - were swept by the first iteration of the current Warriors Dynasty. Davis's only other postseason appearance came in 2018, when the Pelicans upset the 3-seed Portland Trailblazers in a stunning sweep. Although the Pelicans lost to the Warriors again in the next round, their second round exit was viewed as a success after the enormous loss of DeMarcus Cousins in late January due to a ruptured Achilles.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goalkeeper Passing- What’s been done so far</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Goalkeeper-Passing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goalkeeper Passing- What’s been done so far" /><published>2019-01-27T07:10:47-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-27T07:10:47-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Goalkeeper-Passing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Goalkeeper-Passing">&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Background&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true that a goalkeeper's main job is to keep the ball out of the net. However, in the modern game, where margins are much tighter and errors are easily punished, it is a valuable advantage for a goalkeeper to be an adept passer of the ball. This is particularly useful when a team plays a style with the intent of creating spaces to attack by drawing the opposition to press high, such as the style employed (with success, in the past with Napoli) by Chelsea manager Maurizio Sarri. It is no coincidence, either, to see big clubs spending record sums of money on goalkeepers these days, goalkeepers that are not just shot-stoppers, but also excellent footballers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pssPXUABhb8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Napoli playing out from the back to create one-on-ones higher up the field. Note how deep Napoli's center-backs are in the build-up and how the goalkeeper Pepe Reina shows composure under pressure to pass the ball instead of simply lumping it upfield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;It's more than just the goalkeeper&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, we thought it might be handy to develop a tool that determines how good of a footballer a goalkeeper is. It is too simplistic to say that goalkeepers with better passing success rates are better at passing than those with lower rates. This is because of two reasons: firstly, there are lots of other factors at play such as the play style of the team (building out from the back vs direct play), quality of the opponents in pressing high up the pitch, the starting formation of the team (for example, 3-5-2 vs 4-4-2 vs 4-3-3) among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the success rate of a pass depends on multiple factors- the ability of the passer, the awareness of the receiver to adjust his angle and body shape to receive the pass and the general positioning of the team. In addition, the completion of a pass per se cannot classify it as a 'good' pass. For example, the weight of the pass from the passer could be too weak or too strong, which would not allow the receiver to take a good touch and could lead to loss of possession. One possible way of accounting for this would be to determine how many passes were completed after the first pass and weighting subsequent passes accordingly. However, the issue with this is that a loss of possession in turn could be due to a bad decision of the passer or a mistake by the receiver or neither- in the case of very good pressing or a poor structure of positional play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clip below taken from a match between Liverpool and Leicester City in 2017 shows one example of poor positional play and spatial awareness. When the ball is played from the goalkeeper to the defender, the defender has no real options for a pass except for a pass back to his own goalkeeper. He instead takes the risk to pass it forward, expecting his midfielder to move into the space. However, the midfielder is too late to arrive, allowing Leicester City to capitalize and score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/4SZHv7FsDRKhNo3tX0&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; frameBorder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/4SZHv7FsDRKhNo3tX0&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool we propose takes the aforementioned factors into account and attempts to remove any bias that may occur as a result of those factors. This is a challenge because soccer, more so than other sports, is a chain of events, with decisions often being made based on the game state. For example, a team leading 1-0 in the 85th minute of a game is likely to play less expansively than if the same team were winning 3-0 at that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often forgotten is the fact that in sport, we are dealing with human beings and not machines. Like most human beings, players are prone to dips in confidence when things go against them. It is often seen that when teams are on a losing streak, they tend to play more conservatively. Likewise, when teams are on a winning streak, not only do they take more risks, but their passing also becomes quicker and sharper. In our opinion, our tool should reward those players that maintain a consistent level of passing, regardless of how the team as a whole performs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's have a closer look at how the formation of a team can affect the passing options a GK has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/pass/image2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;StatsBomb&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a simple example, the picture above (courtesy of StatsBomb) shows how the passing options a goalkeeper has is determined by the starting formation of the team. In this particular match, Leicester City played in a 4-2-3-1 starting formation, while Wolverhampton Wanderers played in a 3-4-1-2 starting formation. We see that Kasper Schmeichel, the Leicester goalkeeper, played more passes to his wing-backs and towards his striker Jamie Vardy. Meanwhile, Rui Patricio, the Wolves goalkeeper, played almost all his passes to his three center-backs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the use of the word 'starting' formation. This is because teams often change formation during games in order to adapt to various scenarios. Moreover, in the modern game, team shape is fluid and constantly changing- for example, a team could start with a 4-3-3 formation but defend in a 4-4-2 formation instead to give the full-backs more protection. The example below (courtesy of Opta) from a match between Liverpool and Manchester City in 2017 shows Liverpool changing formation from a 4-3-3 to 3-4-2 after Sadio Mane was sent off. Once again, we see a similar difference in passing networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/pass/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the case of Arsenal (who played 33% of their games this season with 3-4-3) was considered, a similar pattern was found wherein the passing networks (too messy to show here!) showed thicker lines from the goalkeeper to the center-backs when a 3-4-3 formation was used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we take a look at 'distance and direction' of a pass. Most sources of statistics only differentiate between 'short' and ''long' passes. However, our research shows that pass accuracy fluctuates widely based on direction as well. This also has to do with the fact that some goalkeepers in the league are naturally right-footed, while others are left-footed. Moreover, some goalkeepers, such as Alisson, prefer to throw the ball out more, whereas others such as Kepa, prefer to use their feet. To make a distinction, we decided to split the pitch into 8 different zones, as demarcated by the red lines shown below. Passing networks are then looked at on a game-by-game basis to determine the 'weaker' side and passes into each of these 8 zones are weighted accordingly, from most difficult (wide-high-center) to least difficult (own-low-center).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/pass/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Other Issues and Future Plans&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the issues we faced was the lack of available data. While commonly used metrics such as passing percentages and starting formations are readily available, others such as ways to measure 'pressure' or speed of distribution are not. (We note here that more extensive data is available solely for the FIFA World Cup 2018. However, we decided against using our model for the World Cup since it is well accepted within the football community that teams in an international tournament do not have as developed of a style of play compared to club teams due to lack of preparation time. Moreover, the sample size of games is extremely small.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, as the picture below shows, most sources of data do not differentiate between passes that are intended towards a specific player and hopeful punts up the pitch. This meant that we had to review video footage of games in order to determine these ourselves. Fortunately, the StatsZone app provides a slider which lets us determine each minute a goalkeeper passed the ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/pass/image5.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following examples will illustrate the difficulty of distinguishing between a pass and a punt just from numbers. In this clip taken from a match between Huddersfield Town and Manchester City in 2018, we see that all Manchester City players, except for the striker, Sergio Aguero are either being man-marked or put under pressure. Ederson, the goalkeeper, then thinks quickly plays a pass specifically intended for Aguero, who then scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/4YY9flqqBwhBf4i5NZ&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; frameBorder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/4YY9flqqBwhBf4i5NZ&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This clip, taken from a match between West Ham United and Burnley, shows an example of a hopeful punt upfield from Joe Hart, as he is being put under pressure by a Burnley attacker. Hart gets given the assist, but it is fair to say that he did not really mean it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/fejrDebQuLKE25rlw6&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; frameBorder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/fejrDebQuLKE25rlw6&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help us solve this (and other issues), we developed a little app using R Shiny (screenshot below). Punts and passes are color-coded differently, but both are retained since we would like to use 'punts up the pitch' to help us determine the goalkeeper best suited to a 'long-ball team'. The tool also helps us categorize passes by zones of the pitch that they are played into, as described earlier and calculates a metric weighted based on the difficulty of a pass into a particular zone and the opponent/playing style being used. At present, the weights we have chosen are somewhat arbitrary. However, in the future, we plan to come up with an unbiased overall metric for goalkeeper distribution based on empirical weights. More on this will be described in a blog-post that will be published in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/pass/image6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sources and Credits&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to credit a number of sources. StatsBomb, Stats Zone and Opta were used for passing networks and visualizations. The mock pitch tool was inspired by Ben Torvaney's 'soccer event tracker'. Full match videos from the 2016-17 soccer season onwards (this would probably interest a lot of people!) were found on fullmatchsports.com/fullmatch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to write to me at &lt;a href=&quot;salil1999@gmail.com&quot;&gt;salil1999@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; if you have any suggestions or ideas on other metrics we could add to our model or any thoughts in general!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Salil Akundi</name></author><summary type="html">It is true that a goalkeeper's main job is to keep the ball out of the net. However, in the modern game, where margins are much tighter and errors are easily punished, it is a valuable advantage for a goalkeeper to be an adept passer of the ball. This is particularly useful when a team plays a style with the intent of creating spaces to attack by drawing the opposition to press high, such as the style employed (with success, in the past with Napoli) by Chelsea manager Maurizio Sarri. It is no coincidence, either, to see big clubs spending record sums of money on goalkeepers these days, goalkeepers that are not just shot-stoppers, but also excellent footballers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Impact of Pitches Seen on Offensive Production</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/PitchesOffensiveProduction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Impact of Pitches Seen on Offensive Production" /><published>2019-01-23T18:11:15-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-23T18:11:15-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/PitchesOffensiveProduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/PitchesOffensiveProduction">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/pitch_off/cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the effects of a major knee surgery suffered during a September 2016 matchup vs. the &lt;i&gt;Toronto Blue Jays&lt;/i&gt;, and a reinjury that was followed by a second surgery in April of 2017, the 2018 season came and went with Boston Red Sox second baseman Dustin Pedroia compiling thirteen total plate appearances; he accumulated just a single hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the Boston Red Sox went on to capture their 9th World Series Championship, the team's first since 2013 and 4th since 2000, they had to do so without contributions from the 2007 American League Rookie of the Year and 2008 AL MVP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team's journey through the playoffs this past season featured series wins against the 100-win Yankees 3-1, the 103-win Astros 4-1, and the NL Champion, 92-win Dodgers 4-1. The team, without Pedroia in the lineup, had to instead rely on a platoon at second base that featured utility man Brock Holt, natural third baseman Eduardo Nunez and 36-year old midseason acquisition Ian Kinsler (who, as of December 14th, 2018, is no longer on the team).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pedroia, the face of Boston's franchise until the arrival of 2018 MVP Mookie Betts, is locked up under contact until 2022. Signing for 8 years, $110 Million during the summer of 2013, even Pedroia indicated a sense of uncertainty about his longevity to reporters, stating &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/mlb/redsox/2013/07/24/red-sox-dustin-pedroia-finalize-110m-8-year-deal/2583911/&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1548303230749000&quot;&gt;I don't know if I'll be done by then, man&lt;/a&gt;&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a league where the average age of a player on a given team lands between a minimum of 26.2 (Chicago White Sox) and a maximum of 30.3 (Toronto Blue Jays), the Red Sox must decide whether to implement the 35-year old Pedroia immediately into the starting lineup as the everyday second baseman for 2019, or stick with the Brock Holt (30yrs)/Eduardo Nunez (31yrs) platoon at the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.boston.com/sports/boston-red-sox/2018/06/07/dustin-pedroia-injury-red-sox-future&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1548303230750000&quot;&gt;The Boston Herald's Jason Mastrodonato reports that there exists just six full-time position players 35 or older in the major leagues this past year -- of which five are designated hitters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In complying with this statistic, it would certainly be easy for the Red Sox to maintain the playoff platoon, or turn to a younger substitute in the form of Michael Chavis (23), Marco Hernandez (26) or Tzu-Wei Lin (24). With that being said, it will be difficult for the club to sit Pedroia on a regular basis as a result of his previous success in the league, his leadership value, and the fact that the team still owes him roughly 40 million dollars on his current deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watching Red Sox games throughout the years, Dustin Pedroia can be seen taking the first pitch of many at-bats, even though the offering will often come directly down the heart of the plate. In contrast to pitches later in his at-bats, Pedroia acts generally unprepared for the first delivery, doing minimal set-up before the pitch is fired, as if he has no intention to swing at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/r7TbWAOhZXo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As our research indicates, there may exist a different offensive approach that can keep Pedroia relevant in the Red Sox lineup by boosting his productivity at the plate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below we have two graphs: one showing Pedroia's year by year Offensive Wins above Replacement and the other Pedroia's Pitches seen Per Plate Appearance average (P/PA) for each season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/pitch_off/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/pitch_off/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking in depth at the statistical side of Pedroia's production, it became noticeable that some sort of trend exists between an increasing average of Pitches Seen per Plate Appearance and a decreasing yearly Offensive Wins Over Replacement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then conducted a significance test, comparing Pedroia's &lt;b&gt;P/PA&lt;/b&gt; during his &lt;b&gt;2008 MVP season&lt;/b&gt; (in which he saw his 2nd highest oWAR and his lowest P/PA) to his &lt;b&gt;average career P/PA&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The t-test, satisfying all conditions of normality, independence, and randomization, indicated a low enough p-value, and therefore established a significant difference in Dustin Pedroia's plate approach in his 2008 MVP season compared to the rest of his career as a whole. This suggests an explanation for the differences seen in production levels year-to-year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For further evidence into the relationship, we developed a line graph comparing the two variables to each other, placing oWAR on the y-axis, and P/PA on the x-axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation of a line of best fit produced the following graph:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/pitch_off/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not a perfectly negative correlation, the slope of -1.45 and R-squared value of 0.017 indicate that P/PA is a factor that impacts oWAR, but is not the &lt;b&gt;only&lt;/b&gt; influencer that determines Pedroia's offensive production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is evidenced through the t-test and analytical graphs, Dustin Pedroia has often experienced more success when he sees less pitches per each individual plate appearance. We equate the term &quot;success&quot; numerically with the value of oWAR in order to develop a clear understanding of his offensive productivity and results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WAR is the value (in wins) lost by a team if a player gets injured, and thus replaced, in a given season. The point of WAR isn't meant to be an exact measure, but rather an estimate of a particular player's value to their team. Below are the attached equations that are used to calculate both a player's total WAR and their oWAR:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;WAR = (Batting Runs + Baserunning Runs + &lt;b&gt;Fielding Runs&lt;/b&gt; + Positional Adjustment + League Adjustment +Replacement Runs) / (Runs Per Win)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;oWAR= (Batting Runs + Baserunning Runs + Positional Adjustment + League Adjustment +Replacement Runs) / (Runs Per Win)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is shown by the bold term, the lone difference between WAR and oWAR is that oWAR does not include the amount of fielding runs that the player has saved/contributed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of Pedroia's increased success at the plate with a decreased number of pitches seen, it would be advantageous to &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;move Pedroia down towards the bottom of the order&lt;/span&gt;, but still &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;keep him in the everyday lineup&lt;/span&gt;. In reference to his positioning in the batting order, often times, the role of batters at the top of the order is to tire out the starting pitcher by seeing more pitches. For the Red Sox to maximize both team success and individual success, an ideal spot for Pedroia to bat in the batting order would be the &lt;i&gt;7th spot&lt;/i&gt;. The 7th position, taken up by hitters such as Jason Kipnis (CLE), Dexter Fowler (STL), and Daniel Murphy (WSH/CHC) is often given to older, yet still impactful players, who hit mostly for contact at this point in their careers. This spot in the order would allow Pedroia to be more aggressive early in the count, giving him a better chance to make a difference when provided with everyday playing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Red Sox Manager Alex Cora should be careful about his usage of Pedroia at second base on a regular basis. Instead, using Pedroia in the DH spot semi-regularly will maximize his chances to produce offensively without wearing him down, a beneficial move with respect to his injury-filled past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pedroia's production at second base, indicated by his dWAR (Defensive Wins Above Replacement) seemingly peaked in the 2014 season, when it maxed out at a career high of 2.5 and won him his 3rd Gold Glove Award. Since then, in seasons in which he has eclipsed 90 games, he has posted dWAR's of 0.0, 1.8 and 0.1. His diminishing value at second base shows that the Red Sox would not be taking a serious hit by playing a replacement once or twice in a given series, and would, by placing him in the DH spot, retain his health for both when he does play second, and for his frequent plate appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, seeing less pitches in each at bat will also limit Pedroia's opportunity for injury at the plate (less pitches seen, less chance to get HBP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dustin Pedroia, still an offensive weapon for the Boston Red Sox should be provided regular playing time, whether at DH or at second base, for seasons to come. With his playing time, Pedroia should make an effort to restore his approach highlighted during his 2008 MVP year, as an aggressive hitter early in the count.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Max Blane</name></author><summary type="html">Due to the effects of a major knee surgery suffered during a September 2016 matchup vs. the Toronto Blue Jays, and a reinjury that was followed by a second surgery in April of 2017, the 2018 season came and went with Boston Red Sox second baseman Dustin Pedroia compiling thirteen total plate appearances; he accumulated just a single hit.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Constructing My All-Time NBA Lineup Through K-Means Clustering, Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/nbaclust2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Constructing My All-Time NBA Lineup Through K-Means Clustering, Part 2" /><published>2019-01-15T10:57:31-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-15T10:57:31-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nbaclust2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/nbaclust2">&lt;style&gt;
div.a {
  text-indent: 5%;
}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbaclust2/cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Nell Redmond, The Associated Press&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;If you haven't read my first article on the topic, check it out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=http://www.bruinsportsanalytics.com/kmeansallnba&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1547585749397000&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I wrote an article where I used k-means clustering to help choose five NBA players from 1980 to the present to constitute an all-time starting lineup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly, the feedback was great, and people were able to understand the process I went through to choose my starting 5. However, I also got some negative feedback, and would like to address some of that here. While I received the typical &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.reddit.com/r/nba/comments/a1xzs1/bruin_sports_analytics_constructing_my_alltime/eatn2go&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1547585749398000&quot;&gt;lol Draymond&lt;/a&gt;&quot; comments, I also got some constructive criticism on my methodology that certainly calls for response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a few comments on how my lineup does not factor in era strength. While it is true that the strength of competition vastly varies throughout different eras, I would like to think that by only using All-Stars from the 1979-80 era to the present, I eliminate a good deal of the confoundment across eras. Though some mid-to-lower tier players might have had more success if they played in a different decade (e.g., Jahlil Okafor), I am of the opinion that elite players are elite, regardless of the era they play in. To say that my lineup of Magic Johnson, Michael Jordan, Larry Bird, Draymond Green and Shaquille O'Neal would get &quot;rekt&quot; because era strength was not considered is, frankly, a bit unreasonable. I understand that a lot of those older players played in a time where the league was just not as talented, fast, etc., but saying players like Magic and Jordan would not be as good had they played today completely ignores the superior skill, talent and work ethic these players possessed that made them the legends that they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, some negatively reacted to my use of advanced stats, since &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.reddit.com/r/nba/comments/a1xzs1/bruin_sports_analytics_constructing_my_alltime/eatryyf&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1547585749400000&quot;&gt;it's easy to play to maximize an analytic after it is created&lt;/a&gt;&quot;, and thus invalidating the use of advanced analytics on players from different periods of the game. However, if we look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.basketball-reference.com/about/ws.html&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1547585749400000&quot;&gt;how some of these advanced statistics are calculated&lt;/a&gt;, it is clear that players and data from all eras are carefully considered when regressing various statistics to produce the target advanced statistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, let's look at some of the top 10 players in my dataset for some popular advanced statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Win Shares:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbaclust2/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Value Over Replacement Player:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbaclust2/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Offensive Box Plus-Minus:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbaclust2/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Defensive Box Plus-Minus:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbaclust2/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is not the most precise way to show this, we can see that for many of the popular advanced metrics, there is a decent amount of variation in players from different time periods when focusing on the cream of the crop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a broad sense, I feel that the disagreements here are a matter of individual perspective on whether it is fair to compare statistics over time despite disparities in league strength and playing style. While I generally agree that many of these statistics confound due to time, I think that the structure of my project mitigates that enough to still be considered valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'd like to switch gears to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.reddit.com/r/nba/comments/a1xzs1/bruin_sports_analytics_constructing_my_alltime/eatryyf&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1547585749405000&quot;&gt;suggestions&lt;/a&gt; I got about finding more statistical ways to choose players from the clusters. I will admit that I could have at least considered some more math-y methods, even if I still ended up choosing players I saw fit for an all-time lineup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my original article, I did list players that were closest to the centroid in each cluster; we can consider players from this group in a possible lineup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also used a random forest method to tease out important features that distinguished players in each cluster from players in the entire dataset. For reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;margin-left: 2em;&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To further investigate, I carried out a method recommended by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://medium.com/square-corner-blog/so-you-have-some-clusters-now-what-abfd297a575b&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1547585749406000&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; to extract feature importance in clusters. First, I constructed a random forest model that predicted the probability of every player belonging to the 7th cluster. Then, using a built-in function in the randomForest library in R, I saw which variables were most important in construction of the model. This showed me that in determining whether a player was in the 7th cluster or not, the two most important variables were 2 Pointers Attempted Per Game and 3-Point Attempt Rate (percentage of field goal attempts that were 3-pointers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what the plot that shows variable importance in the randomForest library looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbaclust2/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To approach lineup construction in a more scientific method, I decided to perform this random forest process on each cluster, then arrange the players in each cluster in descending order of their most important feature, and finally, pick the player with the highest value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the closest-to-centroid and random forest methods, these are the players we end up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbaclust2/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be blunt, these groups of players do not stack up to the starting five that I assembled. However, lineups created from both collectives would be incredibly fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Closest-to-Centroid group, I would probably pick Marques Johnson, Chris Mullin, Peja Stojakovic, Charles Barkley and Chris Bosh. This would be an electrifying lineup; we would have the first ever point-forward (and fellow Bruin) in Johnson running the show, two elite sharpshooters on the wing in Mullin and Stojakovic, one of the greatest and most uniquely talented players of all time in Barkley at the 4 and an underrated, elite defensive big who could stretch the floor and occasionally make a nifty move in the post in late-career (*sad react*) Bosh. This team would also have a distinctive defensive identity, as the shortest player here is Barkley at 6'6&quot;. Unfortunately, Mullin and Stojakovic would almost certainly have trouble defending on the wing; despite their size and length, neither were known as the most lockdown guys in their days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Random Forest group, I would pick out Steph Curry, Derrick Rose, George Gervin, Shawn Marion and Hakeem Olajuwon. On the offensive end, this lineup would be so ridiculously entertaining to watch. At the guard slots, we would have the greatest shooter to ever grace basketball in Curry and one of the quickest, most explosive athletes to play in the NBA in Rose (ignoring injuries *sad react*). The wings would consist of the smoothest scorer out there in The Iceman and the amazingly athletic Marion, who would compete with Curry on this team for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v%3D-H0EjcoMZRk&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1547585749420000&quot;&gt;prettiest jump-shot&lt;/a&gt;. And finally, lurking in the paint, we have the crown jewel of this team: Hakeem Olajuwon. As arguably the greatest center in NBA history, Hakeem would make defenders look &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v%3DhW4uXlRGAF0&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1547585749420000&quot;&gt;silly&lt;/a&gt; with his silky post-moves on a nightly basis. While this team would be absolutely unstoppable on the offensive end, they would certainly struggle on defense. Despite having the all-time leader in blocks manning the paint (Olajuwon) and a marvelous, versatile defender available to switch on whomever (Marion), this lineup has a pretty subpar defender on the wing in Gervin. And as for the guards, we might as well put turnstiles on the perimeter if our options out there are Curry and Rose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, mostly for defensive reasons, I would still choose my lineup of Magic Johnson, Michael Jordan, Larry Bird, Draymond Green and Shaquille O'Neal over these more scientifically chosen lineups. Regardless, these lineups were important exercises to consider, and definitely added a bit more of a statistical element to my decision, as they gave me perspective on two numerically defined alternatives to my initial choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is likely the end of my work on this project, unless I come back a few months later with a random revelation, or decide to respond to a few more Reddit comments. Thank you for indulging me in this long, arduous, basketball-y journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But again, who is scoring on my team?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to see my code, you can find it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://github.com/nikhil348/K-Means-Article&amp;sa=D&amp;ust=1547585749422000&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Nikhil Sharma</name></author><summary type="html">A few months ago, I wrote an article where I used k-means clustering to help choose five NBA players from 1980 to the present to constitute an all-time starting lineup.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Relievers in Today’s MLB</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/relieversTodaysMLB" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Relievers in Today's MLB" /><published>2018-12-05T09:24:39-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-05T09:24:39-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/relieversTodaysMLB</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/relieversTodaysMLB">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/relievMLB/pic1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Sports Illustrated&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Major League Baseball (MLB), a reliever is defined as any pitcher who is substituted for a starting pitcher to help finish a game. Ideally, even as of a few years ago, relievers were meant to be brought in after the starter had pitched at least 6 or more innings. However, as the game has evolved, relievers have expanded their respective roles. For instance, teams like the Tampa Bay Rays have implemented relievers in a starting role, where the relievers are known as &quot;openers.&quot; Starters, who used to go much deeper in the game, are being pulled in the 5th inning--sometimes earlier--more often than ever. After all, starters are limited to a certain number of pitches, meaning that you'll rarely see pitchers venture into triple-digit pitch counts to prevent injuries that may require Tommy John surgery. Consequently, relievers are being used more often and for longer periods of time. But, the volatility amongst MLB relievers hasn't gone away, which means consistency might be hard to find in a reliever. This variability brings about an important question for MLB front offices: is it worth paying extra for free agent relievers in today's game? Through an examination of past and present player salaries and performance, I will try to see whether inflated salaries for relievers are really worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it frankly, relievers are receiving all-time high salaries. Front offices are willing to spend top dollar on the best arms available, even if this strategy might be a risky proposition. One good example is how the Colorado Rockies spent over $100 million on just their relievers over the 2018 offseason. That was more than twice the amount they spent on starters! In fact, the Rockies were 1 of 7 MLB franchises to commit more money to their bullpen than their starting pitchers this past offseason. To further demonstrate the increasing value of relievers, I looked at top reliever salaries from the 2011 and 2018 MLB seasons on Spotrac.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/relievMLB/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/relievMLB/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we see that the top relievers of 2018 received much more money than their counterparts from 2011. For instance, Aroldis Chapman and Kenley Jansen both earned upwards of $80 million contracts in 2018, while the top breadwinner from 2011, Jake Peavy, earned a mere $52 million contract, even though he also started a fair share of games. Moreover, David Robertson, who earned the 5th-most money of 2018 relievers, equaled the earnings of the 3rd highest-paid 2011 reliever, Francisco Cordero. And if we take into account the context of some of these contracts, the results might even be more revealing. After all, David Robertson isn't even an elite reliever on his own team, as the Yankees arguably have better relievers in Aroldis Chapman, Dellin Betances, and Chad Green, among others. On the other hand, all five names listed from the 2011 season were all top dogs in their respective bullpens. This example gives average fans a better idea of just how drastically reliever salaries have shifted upwards over the past few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to account for the spike in reliever salaries has been their increased usage in games throughout the league. Based on data from fangraphs.com, I created visualizations of total reliever innings pitched and wins from the years 2008-2018 to demonstrate the uptick in reliever usage recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/relievMLB/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2008, relievers completed just over 15,000 cumulative innings, which was still a lot for that era in baseball. Just look at the 2009 to 2014 seasons, where the cumulative innings pitched by relievers didn't even match the 2008 campaign. However, the most recent four seasons all had dramatic upticks in innings pitched for relievers league-wide. As a result, in the 2018 season, relievers nearly posted a whopping 17,500 innings, which is over 2,000 innings more than in 2008. Correspondingly, we saw many of the same trends with reliever wins. First of all, there was a bit of a lull in wins earned from 2008 all the way up to 2014. However, from 2015 to 2018, there has been a gradual increase in reliever wins. In fact, the ascent from 2017 to 2018 is extremely relevant; after a slight dip from 2016 to 2017, the 2018 season had over 100 more reliever wins than the previous campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though reliever usage has definitely increased in recent times, relievers are still extremely volatile. To examine this assumption, I took a look at the 2008 and 2018 seasons for reliever data on fangraphs.com; specifically, I examined earned run averages (ERAs), which are a measure of how effective a pitcher is during his time in games. Since the goal of a pitcher is to allow as few runs as possible, low ERAs are indicative of good pitching. High ERAs, on the other hand, show that the pitcher is rather ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/relievMLB/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make these scatterplots, I first filtered each season's set of relievers by only including those who have pitched at least 60 innings. This still gives a relatively large pool of relievers, but it doesn't have an excessive amount of guys. Then, I plotted with the x-axis being ERA and the y-axis being IP to find the spreads of ERAs and correlations between ERA and IP for both seasons. For the 2008 season, there were 92 qualifying relievers with 60+IP, yet none of them exceeded 90 IP. The ERAs ranged from 1.33 all the way up to 6.08, but the median ERA was 3.515. The standard deviation of the 2008 ERAs was 1.09, which is pretty high given the relatively low median ERA. As for the correlation coefficient between IP and ERA for the 2008 season, it was a mere 0.07, which demonstrates a very weak correlation between the two variables. Therefore, just because a reliever pitched more innings did not mean that he would be more effective in terms of ERA for the 2008 season. As for the 2018 season, there were 89 qualifying relievers with 60+IP, but unlike in 2008, there were three relievers that exceeded 90 innings pitched. The ERAs also had a similarly wide range to the 2008 season, going from a low of 0.78 to a high of 5.42, while the median was a pedestrian 3.23. So, the ERAs for 2018 relievers are slightly lower than those for 2008 relievers, but the ranges are very comparable. The ERAs of 2018 relievers varied with a standard deviation of 0.90, which suggests that the variability of performance amongst relievers has somewhat declined since 2008, but one would question whether this is enough of a dip in the standard deviation of ERAs to forecast a further decrease in reliever volatility. With respect to the correlation coefficient between the 2018 ERAs and IP, it was -0.14, which again suggests a fairly weak correlation between the two variables. Clearly, reliever performance has a similar level of variability in the 2018 season when compared to relievers from the 2008 season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, through an examination of reliever data from recent MLB seasons, we saw that although there has been an appreciable increase in both reliever pay and usage on the diamond, there was still too much variability among ERAs and not enough correlation between usage and effectiveness to suggest that relievers should be paid any more than they currently are being paid. No doubt, relievers are changing the game by taking the weight off starters and even opening games at times; this theory would have been shot down even a few years ago, and there are still a fair share of critics who ascribe to old-fashioned baseball and an aberration for all things analytics. And even though ERAs and standard deviations of ERAs have technically lowered since 2008, the variability from reliever to reliever is still too noticeable for front offices to be handing out such large sums of money to middle-of-the-road bullpen guys. Personally, I'd like to see how relievers do over the next few years before making any snap decisions about whether or not they are as effective as some MLB executives believe. Only time will tell if these relievers are worth all the hype.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Veroulis</name></author><summary type="html">In Major League Baseball (MLB), a reliever is defined as any pitcher who is substituted for a starting pitcher to help finish a game. Ideally, even as of a few years ago, relievers were meant to be brought in after the starter had pitched at least 6 or more innings. However, as the game has evolved, relievers have expanded their respective roles. For instance, teams like the Tampa Bay Rays have implemented relievers in a starting role, where the relievers are known as &quot;openers.&quot; Starters, who used to go much deeper in the game, are being pulled in the 5th inning--sometimes earlier--more often than ever. After all, starters are limited to a certain number of pitches, meaning that you'll rarely see pitchers venture into triple-digit pitch counts to prevent injuries that may require Tommy John surgery. Consequently, relievers are being used more often and for longer periods of time. But, the volatility amongst MLB relievers hasn't gone away, which means consistency might be hard to find in a reliever. This variability brings about an important question for MLB front offices&amp;#58; is it worth paying extra for free agent relievers in today's game? Through an examination of past and present player salaries and performance, I will try to see whether inflated salaries for relievers are really worth it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Russell Westbrook: Point Guard or Shooting Guard?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/russPgOrSg" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Russell Westbrook: Point Guard or Shooting Guard?" /><published>2018-12-04T22:56:44-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-04T22:56:44-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/russPgOrSg</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/russPgOrSg">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Sean Gardner, Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russell Westbrook has become one of the NBA's top players in the past decade. He has been a marvel to watch, as his thrilling athleticism has allowed him to churn out highlight after highlight. On top of his exhilarating play-style, he has become a fan favorite due to his curt interviews and his redemptive MVP season after Kevin Durant so infamously snaked Russ and the Thunder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, his role as a point guard has drawn some ire from basketball fans. Although point guards are generally defined as floor generals who control the offense of the team, Russ has somewhat defied this tradition, as he plays the position with a ball-dominant style that has limited his efficiency. Currently, Russ leads the league in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foxsports.com/nba/stats?season=2017&amp;category=SCORING&amp;group=1&amp;sort=7&amp;time=0&amp;pos=0&amp;team=0&amp;qual=1&amp;sortOrder=0&amp;opp=0&amp;page=1&quot;&gt;field goal attempts&lt;/a&gt; at 21.2 per game, and was the second in the league in &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/players/touches/?Season=2017-18&amp;SeasonType=Regular%20Season&amp;sort=TOUCHES&amp;dir=1&quot;&gt;touches&lt;/a&gt; at 95.3 per game in the 2017-18 season. As a player with such a high usage, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://clutchpoints.com/would-russell-westbrook-have-had-a-better-career-if-he-was-a-shooting-guard/&quot;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt; comes up somewhat frequently: would Russ be better as a shooting guard?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To bring a unique perspective to this debate, we decided to tackle it with a logistic regression model. Logistic regression is a form of regression that predicts a binary dependent variable from an independent variable or a collection of them. We figured that we could consider the classification of a guard as a point guard or shooting guard as a binary regression problem, and create a model around this. Then, we could run Russ's stats through our model and see what it classifies Russ as.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collected advanced and basic statistics of all guards since the 1979-80 season. We chose the 1979-80 season as the starting point because this was the first season where the 3-point line was introduced; thus, all of the advanced statistics for players from that season onwards are complete. To predict the position, we first included all of the 43 predictors in the logistic model. Next, we removed the highly correlated predictors, then conducted a stepwise variable selection process using AIC as our criterion. We ended up with 14 variables that constituted our new model. To check the accuracy of our new model, we split the data into training and testing sets, then calculated the mean squared error of the predictions of testing data. The result showed that our model was 89% accurate in classifying guards as either point guards or shooting guards. After building the classification model, we applied the model onto Westbrook's statistics for each year to classify his position, and the results proved to be very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Our model classified him as a shooting guard only in the 2011-12 season, which is particularly noteworthy, since this is the only season in his career that one of his teams made the NBA Finals. Thus, we decided to focus our deeper analysis on this season and the 2016-17 season, when he won the MVP award. We also chose to mostly examine his offensive traits, since this is the side of the ball where his status as a guard is contentious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental difference between these two seasons is the team that surrounded Russ. Just take a look at how the Thunder's win shares were distributed over these two seasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, he had a lot more talent surrounding him in 2012 than in 2017. With three future MVPs on the squad in Russ himself, Kevin Durant, and James Harden, the 2012 Thunder team was very stacked, and allowed for a more even distribution of contribution throughout the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On any given day, any one of Durant, Harden, or Westbrook could go off and give the opposing defense hell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sCUwuSwmcck&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allowed for some of the most dynamic basketball we have seen in the last few decades. Take &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/R_Voow0DDmg?t=228&quot;&gt;this incredible play&lt;/a&gt; from the 2012 Western Conference Finals against the Spurs. Here, Harden gets the ball on a swing pass and decides to drive into the teeth of the defense. When he sees three Spurs collapse on him, he sneaks an incredibly difficult skip-pass to an open Russ on the wing. Instead of popping the three, Russ blows by the senior citizen Tony Parker, who has no hope in keeping up. Then, he craftily maneuvers around Tim Duncan's attempted charge to finish an insane layup. While Kevin Durant was not directly involved in this play, his gravity plays a massive role in this layup coming to fruition. Note that as Russ goes in for the layup, Kawhi Leonard has two choices: help on the drive and leave Durant wide open from the arc, or stay home on his man. If he helps, he leaves an elite 3-point shooter wide open; if he doesn't help, he gives an elite penetrator a fairly clear lane (which is what happened in this case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;SLAM Magazine&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having these three players on the floor at once opened up so many avenues of attack for Oklahoma City. Either all three could get involved in the play (which often didn't happen because of Scott Brooks's abysmal coaching, but that's material for another article), or two of them could run a nice two-man game with the floor opened up due to the third player. Also, with three marquee players who could bring the ball up and initiate offense, the Thunder did not have to rely solely on Russ to make something happen every possession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Harden and Durant left, this changed dramatically. In his MVP season, Russ's best offensive companions were Enes Kanter, Steven Adams and Victor Oladipo. These players, while good in their own rights, were a far cry from the MVP-calibre talents that were Durant and Harden. As a result, the Thunder ran as Russ ran.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we see here, Westbrook shared a relatively larger piece of the pie for his team in points, assists, and rebounds in 2017 than in 2012. Also, between the two seasons, his assist percentage (the percentage of teammate field goals a player assisted while he was on the floor) nearly doubled, from 29.8% in 2012 to 57.3% in 2017. His usage percentage also increased, but not as dramatically (32.7% to 41.7%). Still, his 41.7% usage good enough to be the highest mark in the league that season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the team to be successful, they had to feed the ball to Russ and let him work his magic. In many ways, this philosophy did work. Watching Russ run the fast-break was (and still is) an absolute delight. Often, Kanter and Adams would either grab rebounds, or box out opponents so that Russ himself could get the ball. Then, Russ would streak down the floor, display some supreme ball-handling talents and either &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Dtb10PeLF2s?t=85&quot;&gt;lay it in with ease&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Jmc4KMDs2CA?t=64&quot;&gt;smash in a scintillating dunk&lt;/a&gt;. In addition to being a lethal scorer on the fast-break, Russ also had great vision in transition, where he could &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5rnCCLRMK-8&quot;&gt;weave the ball through nearly impossible passing lanes&lt;/a&gt; when his team got running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the half-court, Russ also utilized some excellent tools. With his big men, Adams and Kanter, Russ often ran the pick-and-roll, where he could either &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/paJ85RCJDh4?t=1431&quot;&gt;find one of them on the roll&lt;/a&gt; or finish himself, either on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/paJ85RCJDh4?t=84&quot;&gt;mid-range pull-up&lt;/a&gt; that he has mastered or on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/paJ85RCJDh4?t=194&quot;&gt;layup/dunk in the paint&lt;/a&gt;. His vision also assisted him in the half-court game, where he could &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/3KLWle7B8wo?t=65&quot;&gt;find his teammates cutting backdoor with slick passes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Steven Adams, Twitter&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2016-17 season, Russ famously averaged a triple double, won the MVP award and lead the Thunder to 47 wins, keeping his team in the playoff hunt after Kevin Durant left the team in cowardly fashion the previous offseason. However, while they had relative success with Russ at the helm, the Thunder also suffered at the hands of their star. As anyone who watches Westbrook with any regularity knows, he is not always the best decision maker on the floor, as he often barrels into the rim for &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/9TO4yjEfMUg?t=76&quot;&gt;reckless shots&lt;/a&gt;, turns the ball over in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8GnJ7xe-2MY&quot;&gt;extraordinary fashion&lt;/a&gt; or generally just does &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8jz9M4LIRD0&quot;&gt;things that should not be done on a basketball court&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/9TO4yjEfMUg?t=47&quot;&gt;This play&lt;/a&gt; encapsulates many of the criticisms of Russell Westbrook. As the play sets up, you can see some nice action off the ball, as Alex Abrines cuts towards the basket at the top of the key off a nice screen. He is clearly looking at Russ, expecting him to slip the ball in for either an easy layup or a kick-out to Jerami Grant if Klay Thompson helped one pass away. Instead, Russ barrels into the basket and takes an ill-advised layup on three Warriors that gets swatted into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russ's boneheaded decisions certainly hurt his stock as a point guard. Even in his incredible MVP season, while had quite a few &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=raDYzXmmQEA&quot;&gt;memorable late-game moments&lt;/a&gt;, he also had an equal amount of not-so-memorable late-game moments, where he would miss deep, off-balance 3s and heavily contested layups when better shots were available. Though he was the reason OKC won the majority of their games, he was also often the reason they lost the games they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/o5iRmnl4mpU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And as we saw, a team that lived by the Russ and died by the Russ petered out in the first round of the playoffs, losing to James Harden's Rockets in five games. When he was forced to be the ultimate floor general, he stuffed the stat sheet for himself, but his team did not do as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Troy Taormina, USA TODAY Sports&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, he did not have two other MVPs by his side. And, a lot of his decision-making woes existed even in the season when he played more of a &quot;shooting guard&quot; role (according to our model). After Game 2 of the 2012 NBA Finals, when Russ chucked up 26 shots in a loss, Magic Johnson famously called Russ &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thebiglead.com/2017/08/10/magic-johnson-on-russell-westbrook-in-2012-finals-worst-point-guard-in-nba-finals-history/&quot;&gt;the worst point guard in a Championship Finals&lt;/a&gt;&quot; he had ever seen. While his teammates Durant and Harden had 32 and 21 on 54.5% and 63.6% shooting (respectively), Russ only shot 38.4% from the field. For obvious reasons, Magic was angry at the fact that the Russ kept on shooting on an off night instead of feeding the hot hands, as a point guard should do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps those numbers would be easier to stomach if he weren't playing the role of a floor general. Most volume scorers have nights of inefficiency, but also have more leeway in terms of shooting themselves back into the game, since scoring is their main offensive role. However, elite point guards who are expected to run their offense with gravitas and poise should engage their hot players, especially when they are in shooting slumps. Maybe if Russ stuck to the role closer to a shooting guard after the 2011-12 season, he might have been able to hone his scoring skills and avoid the brunt of learning how to become a better facilitator on offense. With a more off-ball role, he could have risen to even higher highs than he already has in his great career. And possibly, if he had done these things, he could have &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2779267-kevin-durant-on-2016-free-agency-meeting-with-warriors-i-needed-that-validation&quot;&gt;convinced Kevin Durant to stay&lt;/a&gt; in Oklahoma City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it might not be too late to fall back on his shooting guard roots. As a point guard, his offense relies heavily on his explosive athleticism. Our classification model shows that as age increases, the proportion of point guards in each age group decreases. After 28 years old, which is around the peak of players' athleticism, guards are more likely to be shooting guards (Russ is 30 years old right now, FYI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Russ passes the peak of his athleticism, his offensive efficiency might decrease if he continues to play the way he does now. Russ possess the qualities to become a good off-ball player, as we saw in his relatively successful 2011-12 &quot;shooting guard&quot; season. Looking more currently, his catch-and-shoot scoring has been improving over the past few years. According to NBA.com, in the 2017-18 season, Russ ranked in the 87.6th percentile in spot-up shooting, with 1.16 points per possession. However, this play-type only made up 4.7% of Westbrook's offensive plays last season. Given his offensive awareness and off-ball scoring ability, if he tries to play more off-ball at the shooting guard position, it might be more efficient for him as a scorer and beneficial for the team.  Even though Kevin Durant and James Harden aren't walking through that door again, OKC has an All-Star in Paul George, a capable point guard in Dennis Schroder, a tank in Steven Adams, a four who is better than Melo in Jerami Grant, and more. The squad has a lot of potential, and Russ can potentially unlock that potential by shifting his play-style a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/russ/pic10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Layne Murdoch, Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As fellow Bruins, we love Russ and want him to succeed more than anything. It would be so heartwarming if Russ could get over the hump of the first round of the playoffs that he hasn't been able to conquer without Durant at his side. He won the MVP award without Durant; now it's time for him to win in the playoffs without him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in out code, you can check it out &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nikhil348/Russell-Westbrook-Guard-Type&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jack Ma</name></author><summary type="html">Russell Westbrook has become one of the NBA's top players in the past decade. He has been a marvel to watch, as his thrilling athleticism has allowed him to churn out highlight after highlight. On top of his exhilarating play-style, he has become a fan favorite due to his curt interviews and his redemptive MVP season after Kevin Durant so infamously snaked Russ and the Thunder.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Effective is a Possession-Based Play Style in the UEFA Champions League?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/possessionPlayStyle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Effective is a Possession-Based Play Style in the UEFA Champions League?" /><published>2018-12-04T22:22:31-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-04T22:22:31-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/possessionPlayStyle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/possessionPlayStyle">&lt;p&gt;In soccer, there is no club competition that rivals the prestige and history of the UEFA Champions League (UCL). Each year, the highest ranked teams from all European leagues automatically qualify or enter the preliminary stages of this tournament. In the end, 32 teams participate in a grueling group stage, where every team plays each other twice. The top two teams from all 8 groups make the first knockout stage. Each knockout matchup has two games, other than the final which has one. As a result, the UCL format generally ensures that the team who wins must consistently play well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To win the UCL, a team must have a strategy that is effective enough to overcome the lengthy group stage, three 2-legged knockout ties, and a high-pressure final match against another top team. Over the years, no system has been as romanticized as one that is possession-based. Teams such as the Netherlands national team of the 70s, the World Cup-winning Spanish national team, and Barcelona in the 21st century have been famed for their successful application of this strategy. More recently, Manchester City has dominated the English Premier League with coach Pep Guardiola, renowned for this system, at the helm. In this article, I will attempt to analyze if a play style centered around possession is truly the best method for guaranteeing success in the UCL. Statistics from the 2017-18 edition of the competition will be used for analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/possStyle/pic1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Real Madrid celebrates their third UCL title in a row - Source: Fox Sports&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Measuring Performance of All Teams&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/possStyle/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;Key for &quot;Stage Reached&quot; Variable&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/possStyle/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before analysis can be performed, there must be a variable present to measure the level of success of teams in the competition. As a result, a quantitative variable is created to indicate the progression of a club. As indicated by the table above, any value equal to or greater than 3 demonstrates that a team qualified for the knockout stage of the 2017-18 UEFA Champions League.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The possession percentage is the most basic way of modeling a team's strategy. The histogram shows that the possession splits of sides will generally remain closer to 50/50, especially as teams in the competition are generally of comparable ability. However, being at or above a possession percentage of 50 seems to almost ensure a knockout round place. Every team that made the quarter-finals, other than Juventus, had at least a percentage of 50. On the other hand, a clear outlier is Benfica, who finished last in their group with a 54.7% possession per game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A comparison between Chelsea and Benfica demonstrates how play style is not the sole deciding factor in team success. Chelsea averaged 47.2% possession per game but scored 2.1 goals per game, whereas Benfica had a measly average of 0.2 goals per game. What this proves is that retaining the ball for the majority of the match means nothing unless a team is able to create and finish opportunities. In theory, greater possession should translate to more chances created, which would lead to more goals being scored. However, the case of Benfica, who finished the group stage with 6 losses in 6 matches, demonstrates that a team's finishing ability also plays a large part in their potential success. Furthermore, the correlation between possession and team success tapers off as the competition progresses. This hints at the notion that teams who can retain the ball well are able to fend off weaker teams, but are not ensured victory against stronger opposition. This is understandable, as top clubs and top players are able to create chances with less opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/possStyle/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick look at the relationship between the amount of shots taken and the stage reached shows that there is not a very high correlation between taking shots and winning matches, as many teams are averaging similar numbers of shots while reaching different stages of the competition. Clearly, both the quality of the shots a team takes and the finishing capabilities of the players must impact the level of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/possStyle/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As predicted, finishing remains a vital part of the game. No team who scored one goal or less made it out of the group stage. Teams who are making the later stages are also scoring more in general. However, as with the analysis of possession percentages, the correlation weakens as the competition progresses towards the knockouts. Performing well in these categories seems to indicate that a team should progress out of the groups, but not necessarily that they will last much longer. The two outliers on the high scoring end of the spectrum are Liverpool, who was a finalist, and PSG, who went out in the first knockout stage. Still, the opposite is not true, as teams who are reaching the latter stages must be performing adequately in terms of these statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Analyzing the Performance of the Finalists&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/possStyle/pic6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Gareth Bale of Real Madrid attempts an audacious goal against Liverpool - Source: Le Parisien&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the final of the 2017-18 UCL, Real Madrid and Liverpool faced off in what turned out to be the former's third straight title, a truly astonishing feat. Real Madrid came in with a squad teeming with experienced stars. Their preferred midfield trio of Luka Modric, Toni Kroos, and Casemiro continually dominated the opposition with their intelligent movement and creative passing. Liverpool found success due to their high-octane offense, featuring speedy players such as Mohamed Salah and Sadio Mane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/possStyle/pic7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The table above displays some interesting points of data. Real Madrid ranks 11th in the number of long balls per game, whereas Liverpool ranks 3rd. This is the one passing statistic in the table that is generally known to have an adverse effect on the overall possession of a team, as long-range passing is riskier and carries a lower rate of success. Furthermore, Liverpool falls out of the top 10 in three of the primary possession statistics. These trends demonstrate that Liverpool ignored the allure of a possession-based style in favor of a fast-paced system. They were clearly effective as well, as the team placed similarly to Real Madrid in the rankings for goals and created shots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A possession-based play style remains a viable option for a team searching for a fruitful strategy, but there is only a certain stage a concentration on this strategy can take a club. Weaker teams can be defeated through dedication to this style, but stronger sides will be able to counterattack more effectively. As a result, knockout round success is difficult to predict based on the metrics provided in this article alone. There is no consistent &quot;winning formula&quot; for success in the Champions League, which is a testament to the difficulty that comes with winning the competition. For the knockout stages, teams must find a system that works best for the players they have. Possession was the primary focus of this article, but deeper studies of counterattacking and defensive approaches would allow for a better understanding of what is truly the best strategy for succeeding in the UCL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source for Data: WhoScored.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Faraz Murshed</name></author><summary type="html">In soccer, there is no club competition that rivals the prestige and history of the UEFA Champions League (UCL). Each year, the highest ranked teams from all European leagues automatically qualify or enter the preliminary stages of this tournament. In the end, 32 teams participate in a grueling group stage, where every team plays each other twice. The top two teams from all 8 groups make the first knockout stage. Each knockout matchup has two games, other than the final which has one. As a result, the UCL format generally ensures that the team who wins must consistently play well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Defense in the Modern NFL (or Lack Thereof)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/defenseNFL" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Defense in the Modern NFL (or Lack Thereof)" /><published>2018-12-03T23:14:48-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-03T23:14:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/defenseNFL</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/defenseNFL">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDef/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ray Lewis Ravens, '85 Bears, and Belichick Giants are some of the greatest defenses the National Football League has ever seen. They were stone walls, high-powered, and champions. Scoring more than ten points against any of these teams was an accomplishment- a win in and of itself. However, scoring less than twenty against any team nowadays is almost always another notch in the loss column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern NFL is chock full of defenses who fail to rise to the occasion, ushering in an era of high powered offense and high scoring games. No matter the reasons for this phenomenon (although we'll get to that later), the transition is apparent and an undeniable fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent game between the Kansas City Chiefs and Los Angeles Rams put this trend on display when the two teams combined for 105 points, 1001 yards, and 56 first downs. This would be absolutely shocking for the football world only a few decades ago. Although that particular scoreline is still the largest of the season, games including Chiefs-Patriots, Saints-Buccaneers, and Browns-Raiders all had score totals of 83, 88, and 87 respectively. As of week 12, games are averaging a record 48.4 total points per game. Even more impressively, four of the seventeen highest scoring games in NFL history have come this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total offensive points have increased dramatically over the last 60 years as indicated by the graph below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDef/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;*The 2018 season is ongoing, thus showing a smaller overall value than previous years.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;So, what is causing this apparent lapse in defensive ability?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One argument centers around NFL rules and officiating. A sudden emphasis on the roughing the passer rule this year has resulted in defensive players displaying caution around the quarterback, allowing offenses to take advantage of the hesitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One prominent example was displayed in primetime when Chiefs linebacker Breeland Speaks let go of Tom Brady after having two arms around him because he &quot;*thought the ball was gone&quot; and did not want to risk getting a penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bYVVmrdv54o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Various NFL defensive players have expressed frustration with this type of officiating. Star Saints Defensive End Cameron Jordan stated that in order to sack a quarterback without receiving a penalty, you must &quot;**put a pillow underneath his head [and] read him a bedtime story.&quot; Hyperbole aside, the numbers seem to back up his sentiment. Even though the &quot;roughing the passer&quot; part of the rule book was completely left alone this offseason, the frequency of the penalty has increased 65% in the first six weeks of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last two decades, a series of rule adjustments that favor receivers in the open field, including the protections of defenseless players and an increased emphasis on defensive pass interference, have also most likely resulted in an increased ability for offenses to earn yards and score. If we take a look at the table below, the ratio of Defensive Pass Interference calls to total pass attempts has narrowed every single year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive Pass Interference in the NFL:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDef/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, defenses around the league might just be really bad. There are plenty examples already this season of defensive players making low effort tackles on runners in the open field, resulting in tremendously long plays and touchdowns. For example, in the Dolphins' game against the Bears in Week 6, quarterback Brock Osweiler threw 380 yards and three touchdowns. This is interesting, considering that all but one of his completions came within 15 yards of the line of scrimmage. This means that most of his total passing yards came from yards after the catch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDef/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;*source: nfl.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This visualization above is a representation of Brock Osweiler's game against the Bears. It displays how far away from the line of scrimmage the receiver catches the ball, disregarding yards after the catch. According to the key, all three of his touchdown passes came from completions within 5 yards of the line of scrimmage. One of these touchdowns was a 43 yard completion over the middle with three missed tackles by Bears defenders in the open field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/B_lzD_jr1HE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The Kansas City Chiefs' record-setting 10-game streak of scoring a touchdown of 50 yards or longer has exposed just how bad defenses are this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third and most potentially potent theory revolves around the gradual transition from run-heavy games to passing gameplans. The switch from majority running to majority passing teams came over 30 years ago when elite quarterbacks rose up to produce far more yards than were previously possible. However, the uptick has not yet stopped, and offenses are still moving more and more away from the run. The graph below displays the number of first downs achieved by each team per game. The trendlines shown have r-values of 0.89 and 0.84 for passing and running respectively, strong linear correlations dictating associations between the years that have passed and the rates of first downs according to these different methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nflDef/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;*source: nfl.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passing in the NFL, in conjunction with the aforementioned rule changes that favor passing, are creating high-scoring and high-yardage games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, defenses are struggling constantly now, and it has become rarer and rarer for them to be successful against modern, high-powered offenses. All important offensive metrics, total yards, total points, and first downs all point towards offenses reaching all-time highs in these categories this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The causes of this phenomenon are three-fold: nfl officiating, limited ability, and a transition from run to pass. The league is changing in what aspects of the game it values, and offense is at the top. It is no surprise as well that NFL ratings are up 5% this year for the first time in over six years. These high-scoring games, while mostly a spectacle of fast playmakers running up and down the field, are very entertaining to the general public. While football purists might be barking on Sportscenter about a return to &quot;real&quot; football, this new game will be the NFL for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sportingnews.com/us/nfl/news/nfl-sunday-night-football-snf-kansas-city-chiefs-linebacker-breeland-speaks-thought-the-ball-was-gone-on-missed-new-england-patriots-tom-brady-tackle/1k78iny4m46ky1mpi8c2puqxbc&quot;&gt;www.sportingnews.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sbnation.com/nfl/2018/10/11/17959362/nfl-roughing-the-passer-rules-defensive-players-quarterback-sacks&quot;&gt;www.sbnation.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Arman Abrishamchian</name></author><summary type="html">The Ray Lewis Ravens, '85 Bears, and Belichick Giants are some of the greatest defenses the National Football League has ever seen. They were stone walls, high-powered, and champions. Scoring more than ten points against any of these teams was an accomplishment- a win in and of itself. However, scoring less than twenty against any team nowadays is almost always another notch in the loss column.</summary></entry></feed>