<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-28T15:41:09-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Bruin Sports Analytics</title><author><name>Bruin Sports Analytics</name></author><entry><title type="html">Joe Thornton: The Bearded Legend</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/joeThornton" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Joe Thornton: The Bearded Legend" /><published>2018-02-27T23:00:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-27T23:00:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/joeThornton</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/joeThornton">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/cover_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bearded Hockey Player&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Bay Area News Group&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Throughout his 20 years in the National Hockey League (NHL), Joe Thornton has proven time and time again that he is one of hockey’s best players. Drafted first overall in the 1997 NHL Draft by the Boston Bruins, Thornton was highly-touted, but nobody thought he would turn out to be such a legendary player. With a large frame and an insane ability to distribute the puck to his teammates, he has been and continues to be remarkably consistent. As a result, he has won numerous awards, including the Hart Memorial Trophy (League MVP), the Art Ross Trophy (Most Points), 6 All-Star Team nominations, and a gold medal at the 2010 Olympics with Team Canada. Plus, he has been on a playoff team in sixteen seasons, and he made his first Stanley Cup appearance in the 2016 season with the San Jose Sharks. Aside from his skill, he is near the top in terms of toughness. Despite suffering a severe MCL and ACL injury to his left knee before last year’s playoffs, Thornton still participated in a playoff series against the Edmonton Oilers. Even after surgery in the offseason, he returned to the ice only five months later. As a result, he has come back and played well this season for the Sharks, but another knee injury in January has sidelined him for the foreseeable future. Although it’s unfortunate that Thornton is out, his absence provides a good opportunity to realize how important he is to his team and how good the 38-year-old has been throughout his career.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/graph_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Points&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Speaking to his consistency, Thornton has continued to produce scoring numbers even into the later stages of his career. Ever since his career-best 2005-2006 campaign when he was traded to the San Jose Sharks, Thornton has averaged an amazing 1.01 points per game for San Jose over his 13-year career with them, the best rate in franchise history. His franchise-best 745 assists has largely propelled his amount of points, as his ability to share the puck is uncanny. To add, Thornton’s latest all-star selection came in the 2015-2016 NHL season, where he put up 19 goals and 63 assists for 82 total points and added a plus-minus of 25, his second-best mark in a season, all at the age of 36. Looking more broadly, Thornton has had one of the best individual statistical performances in all of the league since 2000. Seen by the scatterplot above, Thornton has amassed 1319 points over 1276 games since the turn of the millennium, good for a cumulative total of 1.03 points per game. Amazingly, he possesses the most total points out of anyone to play at least 500 NHL games since 2000, and during that span, he has played the 4th most games in the NHL. This ability to stay on the ice is impressive considering the physical nature of the sport, yet Thornton is one of the toughest guys you will find. After all, he has played in at least 85% of his team’s games in all but his rookie season, when he was only 18 years of age. It looks like this will be his second year without participating in 85% of the games, but his dedication to the sport and his willingness to compete should have him back on the ice come playoff time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/table_3_2.png&quot; style=&quot;float: left; width: 45%&quot; alt=&quot;Table&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/table_3_3.png&quot; style=&quot;float: right; width: 45%;&quot; alt=&quot;Table&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;clear: both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;    &lt;figcaption&gt;hockey-reference.com&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking at Thornton from the perspective of an NHL historian years from now, Jumbo Joe would be considered an all-time great. First of all, Joe is in 21st place for total games played all-time in the NHL with 1493, so he’s approaching the 1500 milestone. That puts him in 3rd position among active players, trailing only former Sharks teammate Patrick Marleau (1557 as of 2/25), and former Calgary Flames great Jarome Iginla (1554). Also, he ranks 12th in assists on the all-time NHL assist leaders list with 1030 of them, only three behind Hall of Famer and Pittsburgh Penguins legend Mario Lemieux. Hopefully he can come back in time this season to beat Lemieux’s mark, as it will only be a few games before Thornton eclipses him. Among active players, Thornton’s assist total is unmatched, as he is far ahead of the next highest total of 821 from Henrik Sedin. And when you take into consideration adjusted assists, a stat that normalizes statistics from different eras to make players from different generations more comparable, Thornton jumps even higher on the list, going to 5th place with 1135 career adjusted assists. He places 1st among active players in this category as well, with the nearest competitor also being Henrik Sedin with 912 adjusted assists. Plus, Thornton ranks 16th in career points with 1427 of them, as he trails Hall of Famer Teemu Selanne by 30 points for 15th place. In fact, in all of the above categories, the people Thornton trails are either Hall of Famers or Future Hall of Famers, so Jumbo Joe will most certainly be a lock for the Hall once he hangs up his skates.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The consistency of Joe Thornton cannot be overstated. In addition to being one of the NHL’s most durable players, his production has been remarkably steady over the last decade-plus:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/graph_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rolling Averages&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Primarily a playmaker, Thornton’s assist numbers per game have almost always been higher than his goals per game. What stands out in this plot is that the black line, his points per game, has never dipped below 0.5 in any of these 20 game stretches of his career since the 2004-05 lockout. Every player goes through ups and downs; whether it’s a slump caused by bad luck/off-ice distractions, or an increase in scoring after being placed on a new line that meshes well. The fact that Thornton has been able to remain consistent for so long speaks to a longevity attribute that very few players in NHL history can claim to possess. The slight downward trend can be explained by his aging, but it is nowhere near the drop off most players experience in their early-30s. At 38, Joe Thornton is still a top-6, first powerplay unit quality player.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another testament to Thornton’s consistency is an examination into the points scored against all NHL teams.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/graph_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Career Points&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, three teams in particular shouldn’t be paid much attention; Thornton has played his entire career with the Boston Bruins and the San Jose Sharks, and the Vegas Golden Knights are a new expansion team who are in their inaugural season. When you exclude these three teams, Thornton has scored at least 30 points against every NHL team. This is quite impressive, given that each team in the league plays the majority of their games in their respective conference. However, the recent realignment of the divisions and conferences in 2014 puts some of the data out of context, but the scheduling distribution is still roughly the same. For instance, according to NHL.com, teams in the Pacific Division, like the San Jose Sharks, have to play 29 games (35.37%) within their division, 21 games (25.61%) within the Western Conference but outside of their division, and 32 games (39.02%) in the Eastern Conference. This arrangement, of course, is due to traveling convenience, so teams in the East Coast don’t square off against the Sharks as often. Therefore, it makes sense that Thornton has racked up over 70 points against longtime division rivals like the Arizona Coyotes, the Los Angeles Kings, and the Anaheim Ducks, but has “merely” put up just under 40 points against cross-country foes like the Florida Panthers, the Philadelphia Flyers, the Carolina Hurricanes, and the New York squads (Islanders and Rangers). Now, to be fair, Thornton did spend some time with the East Coast Boston Bruins, but he has only played 532 games, or 35.63% of his NHL career, with them. This is why his totals are weighted more towards his time with the Sharks, who he has played for in the other 961 games of his career. In summary, despite the changing nature of the game with realignments and what not, Thornton has produced against every team he has faced, regardless of how frequently he plays an opponent.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How has he been able to remain at an elite level for so long? The answer lies in the type of player he is. Hockey IQ is a characteristic that defines how well one can ‘see’ and understand the game. Skaters with high hockey IQ think two or three steps ahead. They know what they are going to do with the puck before it comes to them. They know where everyone is on the ice, and where they will be. Joe Thornton is the epitome of a high hockey IQ player. Because it is largely a mental quality, the effects of aging may be less impactful on him than a similar-caliber talent who relies on speed and quickness, traits that deteriorate significantly with age. Combine this sense for the game with innate physical tools and toughness, and you begin to see why Thornton is such a special player. Unfortunately, no one is immune to injury, and Jumbo has suffered a couple significant ones over the past year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In early April of 2017, near the end of last year’s regular season, Joe Thornton was injured in a collision with Vancouver forward Michael Chaput. He sat out the final few games before returning for Game 3 of San Jose’s first round series against Edmonton. The Sharks lost in 6. It was later revealed that Thornton had played through a torn ACL and MCL in his knee. Head coach Peter DeBoer noted it was as “courageous an effort as I’ve ever seen.” Jumbo had knee surgery over the summer and was back on the ice for the start of this season. Fast forward three months to a home game against Winnipeg. He got tangled up with teammate Mikkel Boedker and fell awkwardly, sustaining an MCL injury to his other knee. There is no timetable for his return. The Sharks are heading into the final stretch of the season fighting for their playoff lives. They are second in the Pacific division, but also just two points ahead of 9th place Calgary. With 19 games remaining (as of Feb. 26), every point is critical. How have the Sharks fared in their last 16 games without Thornton compared to their first 47 with him?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/thornton/graph_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;With and Without&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Objectively worse. Their offense is suffering, as goals per game has dipped a couple tenths, and they are allowing more goals per game without him. Even worse, the Sharks’ powerplay percentage has gone way down as well. Of course, we cannot attribute every significant difference to the absence of Thornton. 16 games is a rather small sample size, and there are a myriad of other factors to take into account, such as strength of schedule, puck luck, other lineup changes, and more. But San Jose is playing .500 hockey without their anchor up front, and that will not be good enough if the team hopes to return to the playoffs for the 12th time in 13 years. GM Doug Wilson may have realized this, as the franchise traded for Evander Kane at the trade deadline. Kane is a 26 year-old winger in his prime whose 20 goals and 40 points place him second and third, respectively, on the Sharks roster. Perceived ‘character issues’ have followed the Vancouver native throughout his career, but you cannot deny his talent. He should be able to thrive both on and off the ice in a blue-collar organization like San Jose. Additionally, playing without Thornton for a long stretch like this allows management to see what the team might look like in the post-JT era. After all, age gets the best of everyone. With two significant knee injuries in the past year, Thornton has likely began to evaluate just how much longer he can go. An unrestricted free agent this summer, he’s not even guaranteed to come back to the Sharks for another season.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But the legacy he has crafted in San Jose, and throughout his career for that matter, is substantial. He’s a six-time All-Star, Olympic Gold medalist, Hart Trophy recipient, and future first ballot Hall of Famer. The only thing missing is a Stanley Cup, and unfortunately this draws the attention of the all-to-familiar crowd who judge players based on the number of championships they have won. There is still time for him to bring the city of San Jose its first, but the Sharks are not the same feared contender of years past. Thornton could opt to leave and chase a Cup in the twilight of his career, which would be a bittersweet ending for Sharks fans. When he finally does retire, he will be celebrated in San Jose. Number 19 will forever hang in the rafters.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Veroulis and Joey Maurer</name></author><summary type="html">Throughout his 20 years in the National Hockey League (NHL), Joe Thornton has proven time and time again that he is one of hockey’s best players. Drafted first overall in the 1997 NHL Draft by the Boston Bruins, Thornton was highly-touted, but nobody thought he would turn out to be such a legendary player. With a large frame and an insane ability to distribute the puck to his teammates, he has been and continues to be remarkably consistent. As a result, he has won numerous awards, including the Hart Memorial Trophy (League MVP), the Art Ross Trophy (Most Points), 6 All-Star Team nominations, and a gold medal at the 2010 Olympics with Team Canada.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixture Congestion and Playing Styles vs Injuries in European Football</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fixturecongestion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixture Congestion and Playing Styles vs Injuries in European Football" /><published>2018-02-07T14:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-07T14:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fixturecongestion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fixturecongestion">&lt;h4&gt;Background&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/main_photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winter Soccer&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;In England, every team plays 5 matches in the last week of December and the first week of January as part of a traditional festive fixture schedule, that brings great revenue to TV companies and to the Premier League itself. Source: Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, debate over fixture congestion in English football has increased, both on social media and by so-called sports pundits and former players on television. A key contributing factor to this debate is the increase in number of foreign mangers (mostly from continental Europe and South America) in the English Premier League over the last 5 years. Not only are these managers used to fewer matches (and winter breaks) in their home nations, they also bring in radically different styles of play that demand higher levels of fitness from the players. This article takes a closer look at the main reasons behind injuries by looking at patterns in other top European leagues over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fixtures and Winter Breaks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following table gives an overview of the number of winter break and rest days across the top 5 European leagues. An important point to note is that Spain’s ‘rest-day’ statistics are skewed by the presence of the two super-clubs Real Madrid and FC Barcelona (two teams with excellent squad depth and great medical facilities). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/rest_days.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Winter Break Days&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top 6 teams in England play 4.65 games more than their counterparts in other countries. While this might not seem like a great deal, when compounded with the lack of a winter break and the lack of an ‘extra’ rest day, English teams are at a big disadvantage. Moreover, English teams play 26.5% of their total fixtures in the months of December and January and have 3.7 rest days on average. Meanwhile, their foreign counterparts play 16.6% of their fixtures over the two months and enjoy 6.6 rest days, in addition to having the luxury of a winter break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This difference becomes especially apparent in the second half of the season, when English teams accumulate most of their injuries. This is highlighted by the fact that there is a general trend over the last 5 years in the Premier League that has seen the number of soft tissue injuries rise by 45% and the total number of injuries rise by 13% in the months of December and January (according to injury data analyst Ben Dinnery). On the other hand, German and Spanish teams accumulate roughly the same number of injuries in the second half of the season as they do in the first half of the season (5% and 6% increase respectively).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This puts them at a disadvantage when they compete in continental competitions such as the UEFA Europa League and the UEFA Champions League, and is often cited by many Premier League managers, most notably, Pep Guardiola and Arsene Wenger, for England’s poor performance in European competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/fig1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bar graph of Injuries&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Figure 1: Total number of injuries (2016-17 season)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A counter-argument to the introduction of the winter break in England is the fact that Boxing Day and New Year Premier League fixtures have been a tradition since the post-war period. In addition, television companies and the Premier League itself make huge revenues from the festive fixture period by scheduling matches in a staggered fashion (one after the other), which often leads to Premier League teams playing 2 matches in less than 48 hours and in some cases, 3 matches in just 6 days. In addition to creating fixture congestion, this creates an unequal playing field as some teams enjoy longer rest periods between matches compared to their opponents. For example, in the 2017-18 season, Leicester City played 4 matches in 213 hours, while Arsenal played the same number of matches in 294 hours, a difference of more than 3 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;t is up to the Premier League to decide whether to value its own revenue by remaining spectators and watch its teams exit the continental competition at an early stage or help to support its clubs’ performance in continental competition by including a winter break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Playing Styles and Squad Rotation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is intuitive that a high-intensity style of football that focuses on pressing, possession recycling and winning the ball in the opponents’ half of the field requires higher levels of fitness from players as opposed to a low-block, deep-defending, counter-attacking style of football. The former style, employed by teams such as Arsenal, Tottenham Hotspur and Liverpool is one of the factors for a poor injury record, as is suggested by the graph below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/fig2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Number of Injuries Timeline&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Number of injuries (longer than 10 days) per season&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, simply correlating the number of injuries per season with a team’s playing style can be misleading due to long-term injuries and contact injuries in games which skew the data significantly. This is not to say that the managers of teams who like to play this way are blameless, however, since it is their responsibility to buy players who are less-injury prone and employ better squad rotation strategies to circumvent this issue. A good example of a manager who has managed to successfully implement his high-intensity style with a low injury record is Tottenham Hotspur’s Mauricio Pochettino. This is evident from the graph above, which shows that Tottenham Hotspur’s injuries have decreased from the season he took over (2014-15) to last season (2016-17). Over the last three years, the Argentine manager bought physically robust players that not only fit his style but are less-injury prone such as Victor Wanyama, Toby Alderweireld and Heung-Min Son. In addition, in the 2016-17 season, he regularly rotated his full-backs Danny Rose and Kyle Walker with Ben Davies and Kieran Trippier and his midfielders, which led Tottenham Hotspur to have the highest points tally of any Premier League team in the second half of the season, when most of their rivals began to suffer dips in their performance and fitness levels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/fixturecongestion/player.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Injury Prone Soccer Player&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Injury-prone Arsenal midfielder Abou Diaby only made 22 appearances over four years for the club due to a succession of long-term injuries. Such injuries must be taken into context when assessing a club’s injury record.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To conclude, both fixture congestion and playing styles have a clear impact on injuries. The introduction of a winter break in the English Premier League would be much welcomed, especially by managers of the top 6 clubs. Playing style is certainly a factor but is very much secondary to fixture congestion. While the issue of playing styles can be resolved simply by having larger squads and employing better rotation strategies, the issue of fixture congestion is one that can change only if it garners the support of the members of the hierarchy of the FA and the Premier League and will benefit all clubs, regardless of their playing styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Sources:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;physioroom.com and Ben Dinnery’s excellent reports on injury data analysis were used to write this piece. An interesting and more comprehensive report on injury trends in the Premier League can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jltspecialty.com/~/media/files/sites/specialty/insights-sport/jlt_sp_premier_league_injury_index.pdf?la=en-gb&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Salil Akundi</name></author><summary type="html">Over the last few years, debate over fixture congestion in English football has increased, both on social media and by so-called sports pundits and former players on television. A key contributing factor to this debate is the increase in number of foreign mangers (mostly from continental Europe and South America) in the English Premier League over the last 5 years. Not only are these managers used to fewer matches (and winter breaks) in their home nations, they also bring in radically different styles of play that demand higher levels of fitness from the players. This article takes a closer look at the main reasons behind injuries by looking at patterns in other top European leagues over the years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NBA Midseason Reflections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/nbamidseason18" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NBA Midseason Reflections" /><published>2018-02-05T14:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-05T14:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/nbamidseason18</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/nbamidseason18">&lt;p&gt;The All Star lineups have been announced, most teams have played well over 45 games, we finally have a team openly tanking, and the Cavs all hate each other. So with that it's safe to say that the midway point of the NBA season has come and now would be a great time to reflect on the past couple months of the 2017-2018 season. By now everyone knows how great the Warriors are, how dysfunctional LeBron's team is, and that the Sacramento Kings are once again irrelevant. I wanted to take this time to deviate away from the major storylines in the season thus far and analyze some trends, statistics, coaching decisions, and quite simply things that really stand out to me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Houston's Unstoppable Harden, CP3, and  …. Capela? Trio&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the season Darryl Morey said it best when he mentioned that teams would have to increase their risk profile if they wanted to compete with the Warriors. He followed through with his proclamation when he acquired Chris Paul this summer in a move that many people questioned with the classic &quot;there's only one ball&quot; argument. So far the trade has paid off for Morey and the Rockets have clearly been the second best team in the league and have even beaten the Warriors twice this season. 50.6% of the Rockets field goal attempts are coming from three and James Harden is again having an MVP caliber season (if the season ended today, Harden's 29.6 PER would be one the top 30 single season PER performances in the NBA history). Despite all that, the most alarming fact about the 2017-2018 Houston Rockets is that they are 19-0 when Harden, Chris Paul, and Clint Capela play. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite their current record, Harden's MVP campaign, and this trio's +57 plus/minus, all that matters for the Rockets is how they perform in the playoffs. For the past 2 seasons, this Rockets squad has done what all great Mike d'Antoni teams do: underachieve in the playoffs. So far the two victories against the Warriors have been a great sign for the team. They had an outrageous 41, 50, and 37 three point field goals attempted respectively in each of the three games and the best sign was how well Chris Paul played in the last two games. It will be interesting to see how long this trio can keep up their streak, but more importantly how this team competes deep in the playoffs (unless, of course, they choke in the second round versus the Spurs again).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Carmelo's Falling Off&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    By this point in the season every sports show and radio host has talked about how OKC needs to break up their trio and more importantly bench Carmelo. Early in the season the team was clearly dysfunctional; Westbrook had trouble deciding when to go into &quot;2016-2017 Highest Usage Rate in NBA History&quot; mode or whether to defer to his teammates. Paul George was uncomfortable playing off ball, which was something he rarely did in Indiana and Carmelo was doing his normal routine spending seven to eight seconds holding the ball, followed by a series of jab steps all while his other four teammates watched an eventual contested 17 footer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-qRdXc11jqE&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The team has turned it around after their lackluster 8-12 start and are currently sitting at fifth in the West. Definitely the biggest adjustment was that Carmelo took a back seat to Westbrook and George. Carmelo ranks 156th in the league with a PER of 14.51. Whatever your opinion of Carmelo is, seeing his name on a list below Tyler Cavanaugh and Jerian Grant is unexpected to say the least. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbamidseason18/chart1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Carmelo Drop-off&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Basketball-Reference&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    My purpose for bringing up Carmelo's regression this season is not to make him the scapegoat for the Thunder's slow start, but instead to analyze how the league has changed as a whole. Carmelo, whether you love or hate his game, is undoubtedly one of the most talented scorers (and underrated clutch performers) in NBA history. His post game and midrange allowed him to score effortlessly in his career en route to 25,000 points. But in a league where the Warriors have more than five players that can guard every position, the Rockets are shooting 42.8 three point shots a game and the overall pace of offenses throughout the league has gone up, Carmelo's offensive play style no longer has a place. Teams that have a dynamic ball-handler (Lebron, Westbrook, Harden) are full of spot up shooters and defensive minded players. Carmelo is a solid shooter (45% FG% and 34.7% 3FG% for his career) but has never been considered a spot up shooter and discussing his defense (or lack there of) is just laughable. The league just doesn't have space for a 33-year-old stretch four that plays no defense, who kills eight seconds off the shot clock before making any move on offense.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Conversely, DeMar DeRozan has been a great example of a player who has evolved his game this season to fit the current play style in the NBA, particularly in terms of 3 point shooting. DeRozan has always been known for his midrange game and footwork in the post. But this season much of the Raptors success has to be attributed to DeRozan's willingness and effectiveness shooting the three.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbamidseason18/chart2.png&quot; alt=&quot;DeRozan aka Kobe&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;DeMar DeRozan's career 3 point shooting (Source: Basketball-Reference)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Unless Carmelo is willing to change his game and act more as a spot up shooter for Westbrook and George, we may have seen the last of Carmelo as an elite NBA scorer. Looking at his 156th rank PER is not an indictment on Carmelo, but more so a reflection on how the NBA has evolved and how the ball stopping wing player is no longer effective in the league today. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Timberwolves and the Andrew Wiggins Question&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The Timberwolves currently sit at the fourth seed in the West and finally appear to be utilizing their talent effectively. Typically with Tom Thibodeau teams defense and heavy minutes for starters is the norm. For instance he orchestrated the defensive schemes for the Celtics back in 2008-2009 and created a strong defensive foundation during his time in Chicago. Complaints that he plays his starters too many minutes have been well documented throughout his time as head coach. If you need more convincing take a look at the following chart (or just ask Derrick Rose about his knees).   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbamidseason18/chart3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Spooky Wolves Stats&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Three Minnesota players are in the top 20 in minutes per game. (Source: NBA.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    It is evident that during Thibodeau's time in Minnesota and Chicago, his players have consistently been among the league leaders in minutes per game. For instance Luol Deng, during his time on the Bulls, never averaged less than 37.9 minutes per game from the four seasons spanning 2009 to 2013 (though I think Deng is doing just fine now that the Lakers are paying him $18 million a year to stay at home). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    However, with the Timberwolves what really interests me is not the heavy minutes or defense, but instead the team's offense. Early in the season Towns and Wiggins were the two highest scorers for the team and Butler was definitely taking a step back offensively. The team hovered around .500 early on in the season. Around December (conveniently when rumblings about Jimmy Butler and Taj Gibson calling out Towns' effort on defense surfaced) the team started to turn around mostly because Butler started to take the lead role as the primary scorer on offense. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nbamidseason18/chart4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jimmy G. Buckets stats&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Jimmy Butler's scoring increase by month (Source: ESPN.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    What remains the biggest question is how the team plans to use their $150 million forward, Andrew Wiggins. The Timberwolves are performing better with Butler leading the offense and Wiggins settling more as a spot up shooter and cutter to the basket. However, with Wiggins shooting only 32.2% from three and struggling on the defensive end (even though he was projected to be a great defender out of Kansas), it begs the question of how Thibodeau plans on using Wiggins going forward. Would he consider trading Wiggins for some solid role players to fill out the bench and therefore lessen the minutes for Butler and Towns? I would not advocate trading away a 21 year old with the potential that Wiggins has, but it will be interesting to see how Wiggins fits in with the Butler-led offense going forward and into the playoffs. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Hook shots are cool again?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Three pointers are cool, fancy layups and 3-point plays are great, but sometimes I wish the NBA did not feel so one dimensional in terms of teams only shooting threes or shots in the paint. Of course, if the team has the personnel of the Warriors or Rockets it makes sense to shoot almost 50% of your shots from three, but when I watch the league it feels like many front offices and coaching staffs are trying to fit players in a system that doesn't fit their playing style. For example, there's no reason that a team like Dallas or Chicago, with their personnel, should be shooting over 30 threes per game. It would be great to see some more midrange game, more post-ups and attention to great footwork. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    One of my favorite aspects of the season is seeing the resurgence of the running hook shot. Watching players like Kyle Kuzma and Ben Simmons attempt the shot exemplifies the skill and finesse moves that make the NBA great. The running hook shots that stick out to me this season are not the traditional baby hook shots that many post players shoot today (the one where the player gets the ball at the block about 5 feet from the basket, takes a couple power dribbles to the center of the key, and flings a mini hook shot). The shots that I am referring to are the ones where the offensive player starts with the ball outside the paint, takes 3 to 4 dribbles and floats in a high arching shot like Kuzma and Simmons in the videos below. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cq956iN-zlU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;1425&quot; height=&quot;641&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/f8XTJYhAB4w&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    In the modern NBA, watching teams like the Rockets that live off dribble drives for three pointers (or that stand around while Harden flails his arms to draw fouls) can get repetitive. It has been refreshing to see young players show off their skill by attempting and converting finesse shots like the running hook. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The second half of the season will surely bring more drama and excitement on top of what has already been a great season. There has already been so many storylines (the Rockets/Clippers (fake) fight, Jason Kidd getting fired) and the trade deadline will hopefully bring many more. Going forward it will be interesting to see what teams will challenge the Warriors out West and whether the Celtics or Raptors will finally dethrone Lebron in the East. But with all that said, does anybody really see a team that will beat the Warriors four times out of seven games? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
        (Sources: Basketball-Reference, ESPN, NBA.com)
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ronaq Virdi</name></author><summary type="html">The All Star lineups have been announced, most teams have played well over 45 games, we finally have a team openly tanking, and the Cavs all hate each other. So with that it's safe to say that the midway point of the NBA season has come and now would be a great time to reflect on the past couple months of the 2017-2018 season. By now everyone knows how great the Warriors are, how dysfunctional LeBron's team is, and that the Sacramento Kings are once again irrelevant. I wanted to take this time to deviate away from the major storylines in the season thus far and analyze some trends, statistics, coaching decisions, and quite simply things that really stand out to me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An In-Depth Analysis of Stan Wawrinka</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wawrinka" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An In-Depth Analysis of Stan Wawrinka" /><published>2018-01-27T22:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-27T22:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wawrinka</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wawrinka">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/wawrinka.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stan Wawrinka&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Stan Wawrinka hoisting his first ever U.S. Open trophy (Photo by Elsa/Getty Images)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    In the era of the Big Four, tennis has seldom seen a Grand Slam Championship claimed by a player not named Novak Djokovic, Roger Federer, Andy Murray, or Rafael Nadal. The Big Four have won 50 of the last 58 Grand Slam tournaments, dating back to the 2003 Wimbledon. Ever since then, the spotlight in men’s tennis has only shifted between these four champions. With a combined career record of 3443-782 (81.5%) and a combined total of $377,087,356 in prize money, the Big Four have dominated tennis in a way never before seen in the sport. However, despite such dominance, it may be time to start considering that world tennis may really have a Big Five.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Of the 8 Grand Slam trophies that weren’t hoisted by a member of tennis’ elite quartet, only one player has won more than one: Stan Wawrinka. Winning the 2014 Australian Open, 2015 French Open, and 2016 U.S. Open, all against the incumbent ATP world number 1 (each a Big Four member), Wawrinka has made an interesting case to be categorized with the rest of the Big Four. In the Winter of 2017, at the age of 32, Wawrinka nearly opted to retire after a knee surgery that ended his 2017 campaign. If he were to retire, where would his career stack up against those of the Big Four? Looking closely at Wawrinka’s career, it is clear that he has not exhibited the same dominance as the Big Four, but his level of play at times may be the closest resemblance to a member of the Big Four since the group took the reigns of the men’s game in 2003.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Consistently Inconsistent&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    A late bloomer, Stan did not win his first Grand Slam until he was 28 years old. Up until that point, he had only ever made it to one semi-final of a Grand Slam (U.S. Open, 2013). By the time he captured his first Slam, the Big Four already had total control of the sport, having won a combined total of 38 Slams. Wawrinka has not been able to make up for this late arrival to the party, for he has not won more Grand Slams than any member of the Big Four:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    With Djokovic, Federer, and Nadal in double digits and Murray winning the Wimbledon twice alongside his U.S. Open title, it is clear that Wawrinka should not be placed above any member of the Big Four in terms of Slam success. While he may have as many Slam titles as Andy Murray, there are other aspects of the careers of the Big Four that put them in a league of their own, apart from Wawrinka.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/novak.png&quot; alt=&quot;Novak Djokovic&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Novak Djokovic hoisting the ATP World Tour Finals Trophy (from bettingtips365.net)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The ATP World Tour is comprised of many singles tournaments apart from Grand Slams. Alongside the four Slams, the tour each year contains 9 ATP Masters 1000 tournaments, 13 ATP 500 series tournaments, and 40 ATP 250 series tournaments throughout the year. The Big Four have dominated on all of these levels, while Wawrinka pales in comparison:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Total ATP Titles&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Although Wawrinka has won as many Slams as Murray, Murray and the rest of the Big Four have displayed unparalleled victory throughout their careers in all other phases of the tour as well. But a comparison of total singles titles still does not cover the substantially large gap between the Big Four and Wawrinka. Any top rated player can win a singles title with a week or two of exceptional tennis (most tournaments are just one week long), so it is also important to consider success in individual marquee matchups as well as the quality of opposition that the Big Four and Wawrinka have played. Here are the winning percentages of these five men against players who were ranked in the top 10 at the time of the match:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Winning Percentage&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The Big Four win well above 50% of such matches, while Wawrinka is below 40%. To place these percentages and overall significance of performances in individual matches into grand perspective, one only needs to turn to the Elo ratings. The Elo ratings rate players solely on the quality of their opposition in every match throughout their careers, irrespective of the round or tournament that each match took place. Here are the cumulative Elo rankings of active men’s tennis players:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Elo&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/graph5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Players ranked by Elo&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The Big Four live up to the name, as they are the top four Elo ranked players on tour by more than 100 points. Wawrinka, however, sits at ninth place, once again miles behind any kind of Big Five.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/winners.png&quot; alt=&quot;Winners&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Big Four have been able to defeat one another in Grand Slam finals (from howtheyplay.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Despite his lacking in every comparison with the Big Four thus far, to truly put himself in a position to be on the same level as the Big Four, Wawrinka must at least be able to compete against them in individual matchups. If he has a strong track record against the Big Four over his career, he may have a case to make. Placing Wawrinka in a group of five along with the members of the Big Four, here are the win percentages of each of these five men against the other four: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/stats.png&quot; alt=&quot;Win Percentage&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The Big Four have competed against one another relatively well, with Djokovic, Federer, and Nadal winning above 50% of these matches and Murray winning 37.9%. Wawrinka has not come close to matching that level of competition against them, winning merely 22.6% of his matches against the Big Four and having a losing record against every one of them. But even this poor showing in individual matches against the Big Four is still not the most glaring issue when considering Wawrinka’s place among them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The word that many people associate with the Big Four is “dominance”. Federer, Nadal, Djokovic, and Murray have not only dominated the sport for over a decade, but also consistently done so. This is where Wawrinka’s biggest shortcoming becomes clear. In the last thirteen years, no player outside of the Big Four has held the coveted ATP World Number 1 ranking. Each of the Big Four have not only reached the top of the ATP rankings, but have also held that spot for a substantial amount of time. Wawrinka is still yet to even be ranked number 2 in the world (his career high ranking is number 3 on 27 January 2014): 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/weeks1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Weeks at Number 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The World Number 1 ranking does not simply answer the question “Who is the best tennis player in the world?”. It answers the question of which player has demonstrated the most consistency across all phases of the ATP tour in a given calendar year. The Big Four have all done this for large chunks of weeks, sometimes years, at a time. The rankings are updated every Monday of the year, but Wawrinka has never hit the number 1 mark once. This signifies his lack of consistency and ability to keep up the brilliant tennis that he has put on display at times. Tennis is a taxing sport. Mentally and physically, fatigue can lower players’ performance levels as the year-long grind of tournaments and frequent traveling eventually catches up to them. Wawrinka may understandably be a victim of such fatigue as each tournament passes, but the Big Four have proven to be immortal to such things. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/wimbledon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wimbledon Winners&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Left to right: Federer, Nadal, Djokovic, and Murray each holding the prestigious Wimbledon Championship trophy (from tt.tennis-warehouse.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    In essentially every phase of the sport, the Big Four are in a world of their own, far away from every other player on Earth, and that includes Stan Wawrinka. There was never a Big Five and there likely will never be one in this golden age of men’s tennis. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/vilas.png&quot; alt=&quot;Guillermo Vilas&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;(By Verhoeff, Bert / Anefo)  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/kodes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jan Kodes&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;(from Getty/Pat Scala) &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/stanslice.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stan Slicing a Ball&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;(from kodes-tennis.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    While he may not be near the Big Four in any way, Wawrinka is certainly the closest to knocking on the door, for he has set many interesting and accomplished records in tennis history. He is the only player to have won multiple Grand Slam titles in Slams that featured all members of the Big Four. Although the number 1 ranking continues to elude Wawrinka, he may possibly go down as the greatest player to have never reached the apex of men’s tennis. The only man to have not only amassed more Grand Slam titles but also to have never been ranked world number 1 is Argentine player Guillermo Vilas (left), who won 4 Grand Slam titles and only reached a career-high ranking of 2, despite significant controversy. By the end of his career, Vilas had made 8 Grand Slam finals, facing similarly high qualities of opposition with the likes of Bjorn Borg, Jimmy Connors, and Mats Wilander. Intriguingly, Wawrinka can be thought of as the modern version of Guillermo Vilas in men’s tennis. Neither Vilas nor Wawrinka have won a Wimbledon title. Both have excelled on clay, possess a one-handed backhand, and a baseline-dominant play style. The following charts below show that both have enjoyed relatively similar success in Grand Slam tournaments. Unlike Wawrinka’s late blossoming, Vilas’ came during his mid-to-late twenties:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Vilas&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/vilasrecord.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vilas record&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Wawrinka&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/stanrecord.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stan's record&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wawrinka is the first player in the Open Era since Jan Kodeš (right) to have won 3 Grand Slam singles titles without ever being ranked higher than world number 3. Kodes never won a U.S. Open, let alone even played in an Australian Open. Furthermore, Kodes never beat an incumbent world number 1 in any of his 3 Grand Slam championships. Here is a rankings trendline of the three players by age:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/atpchart.png&quot; alt=&quot;ATP Rankings&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    A potential Wimbledon title in the future for Wawrinka would not just make him the first of these 3 players to complete the Career Grand Slam, but also make him only the 9th man in history to do so.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/stananalysis/stanwins.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stan Winning a Clay court title&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;(from tennisworldusa.org)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    There is no doubt that Wawrinka is a fantastic tennis player and a champion in his own right. To compare him to the Big Four would be a disservice to him, as the seemingly unfair control that the Big Four have had over tennis make his very significant accomplishments seem far less significant. He does not belong with the Big Four, but the fact that he has accomplished as much as he has in such an era says a lot about his ability to make the most of the hand that he has been dealt. Looking ahead, Stan Wawrinka’s days on the ATP tour might be numbered, but his inconsistency and unpredictability may just result in even more unprecedented success in an already decorated career.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
            Sources: ATP, tennisabstract.com
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Kathir Ilango and Kevin Hahn</name></author><summary type="html">In the era of the Big Four, tennis has seldom seen a Grand Slam Championship claimed by a player not named Novak Djokovic, Roger Federer, Andy Murray, or Rafael Nadal. The Big Four have won 50 of the last 58 Grand Slam tournaments, dating back to the 2003 Wimbledon. Ever since then, the spotlight in men’s tennis has only shifted between these four champions. With a combined career record of 3443-782 (81.5%) and a combined total of $377,087,356 in prize money, the Big Four have dominated tennis in a way never before seen in the sport. However, despite such dominance, it may be time to start considering that world tennis may really have a Big Five.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One-on-one: Tyreke Evans works his way back to relevance, Nicolas Batum having worst season since rookie year</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/oneonone" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One-on-one: Tyreke Evans works his way back to relevance, Nicolas Batum having worst season since rookie year" /><published>2018-01-25T22:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-25T22:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/oneonone</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/oneonone">&lt;h4&gt;Tyreke Evans&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oneonone/reke.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tyreke Evans&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Tyreke Evans has shattered expectations in the 2017-2018 NBA season. (Justin Ford/USA Today Sports)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        In 2010, Tyreke Evans appeared to have a bright future ahead in the NBA-- he was named Rookie of the Year after joining Michael Jordan, LeBron James, and Oscar Robertson as the only rookies to average 20 points, 5 rebounds, and 5 assists. But in recent years, Evans' career had taken a turn for the worst. He missed 99 games between 2015 and 2017 with right knee issues. Last season, on an expiring contract, he was included in the package New Orleans sent to Sacramento in the DeMarcus Cousins trade. Evans recorded season lows in points and minutes across 40 games with New Orleans and Sacramento. In the offseason, Memphis inked the versatile 28 year-old guard to a team-friendly one-year, $3.3 million deal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Now halfway through the season, Evans is looking like one of the biggest steals of the summer. Evans has experienced a revival with the Grizzlies, putting up 19.8 points, 5.1 rebounds, and 4.6 assists per game. Not only are his counting stats up from previous years, but his player impact estimate (PIE) is at a career high, and ranks ninth in the league, according to NBA.com. PIE measures a player's positive contributions compared to their team's total positive contributions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        The resurgence of Evans' well-rounded game isn't due to him receiving more minutes with his new team-- this season he's logging 30.9 minutes per game, the fourth lowest mark of his nine year career. And the University of Memphis product's usage rate is only three percent higher than his career average.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Part of Evans' elevated performance can be attributed to him being healthy. After missing an average of nearly fifty games the past two seasons, he's sat out just one contest this season due to hip soreness. This extended stretch of good health has enabled Evans to settle in and find a groove.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oneonone/herecomesaustinrivers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tyreke Evans and Austin Rivers&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Tyreke Evans has excelled at the point guard position while Mike Conley has been sidelined. (AP Photo/Michael Owen Baker)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        While Evans has been healthy, Memphis' franchise point guard Mike Conley has not had the same good fortune. With Conley in street clothes for 30 games so far, Evans has stepped into the lead guard role for interim head coach J.B. Bickerstaff without missing a beat. Taking advantage of the wealth of offensive opportunities in Conley's absence, Evans' two-point, three-point, free throw, and effective field goal percentages of 46.7/40.6/79.0/53.7 are all within the top two seasons of his career. Illustrating how elite Evans has been with the basketball, he ranks fourth in pick-and-roll efficiency, trailing only James, Steph Curry, and Bradley Beal.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
        With the losses piling up and the Grizzlies effectively out of contention for the Western Conference eighth seed, Evans' name has been heard on the rumor mill for weeks as the trade deadline approaches. His shooting and ability to defend three positions could make him an attractive target for legitimate contenders like Cleveland and Boston looking to level the field with Golden State. Evans' scoring and expiring contract make him worth a look for teams trying to make the leap into contention like Oklahoma City, Minnesota, and Denver. Whether he winds up getting moved or stays put in Memphis, Evans' play has hushed his critics for now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Nicolas Batum&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oneonone/batum.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nicolas Batum&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Nicolas Batum has underperformed ever since he signed his 5 year contract in 2015. (Joe Murphy/Getty Images)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Nicolas Batum has seemed to be at the edge of being a breakout star for the majority of his career. He came out of the 2011-2012 campaign at 23 years old, averaging 14 points per game (2 above his career average), shooting 45% from the field, adding 4.6 rebounds and 1.5 assists per game. The French swingman's promise was affirmed before the 2012-2013 season, when Portland was forced to match Minnesota's four year, $46 million offer to retain him. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Batum has flown under the radar for much of the last few years, not having reached max contract status or contributed to a legitimate title contender. He has solid career averages of 12 ppg, 5.3 rpg, 3.7 apg, and 31.6 minutes per game. He ranks 42nd in career minutes per game among active players, ahead of All-Stars Anthony Davis, Giannis Antetokounmpo, and Tony Parker. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        In 2014-15, Batum had a down year, averaging only 9.4 points but adding 5.9 rebounds and 4.8 assists. Despite the drop off in scoring, Charlotte believed he had the potential to be a key contributor, and rewarded the then-26 year old with a 5 year, $120 million contract. The large payday makes Batum's regression this season even more stark. In almost every statistical category, this season's numbers are below his career averages- 2 less points per game, 1 less rebound per game, and his shooting percentage has fallen by 3 percent. Compared his first two years in Charlotte, this year Batum is averaging 4.1 less points, 2 less rebounds, 1.2 less assists, and 3.4 less minutes per game. His three point percentage has dropped under 30% for the first time in his career, and his free throw shooting has declined by nearly 5%.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Advanced stats like player efficiency rating (PER), which standardizes all NBA players' stats so that the average is 15, serve as an even stronger indicator of Batum falling short of expectations. His PER this year is 11.4, a career low, even 1.5 below that of his rookie season, and ranks in the high 30s for all shooting guards. This is the first season his box plus minus has been below 1, currently at -0.3, meaning he provides his team 0.3 less points per 100 possessions than the statistically-modeled league average player. Batum has a true shooting percentage (calculated to account for the higher point value of three pointers and lower value of free throws) 3% lower than the worst full season of his career. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oneonone/batum2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Nicolas Batum Hurt&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Nicolas Batum injured his left elbow during a preseason game against the Pistons. (AP Photo/Carlos Osorio)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Charlotte certainly hopes Batum's rocky start to this season was simply a fluke caused by injuries early on. He missed the first month of the season with a left elbow injury, and missed two additional games due to lingering issues with the elbow. Even being healthy since late November, since his return Batum is still is only averaging 10 points per game.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Another possibility for Batum's lackluster showing thus far is Charlotte's play style. Batum is playing most of his minutes at shooting guard, which usually means a larger lineup with fewer shooters on the floor. While he was surrounded by snipers in his Portland tenure, Batum has always been aggressive slashing to the basket. But the lack of spacing and clogging of the lane caused by bigger lineups this year with Charlotte has made it more difficult for Batum to attack the rim. This has been evidenced by his decrease in trips to the free throw line, attempting half as many per game than last year. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        The Hornets are facing a dilemma with their $120 million man. Should they let him try to ride out this slump, demote him to a bench role to see if he plays better against opposing second units, or must they package him with an asset to unload his burdensome contract? Facing other questions, including whether to keep Kemba Walker, expect Charlotte to be active around the February 8th trade deadline.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
                Sources: Basketball-reference, ESPN, NBA
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ben Messinger, Zane Winston, Albert Pan</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predictions for the 2018 Australian Open</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ao2018" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predictions for the 2018 Australian Open" /><published>2018-01-25T22:55:20-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-25T22:55:20-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ao2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ao2018">&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ao18/cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;Australian Open 18&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    In a game where individuals, not teams, play one another, parity should rule the day. However, living legends of tennis still remain amidst a flurry of youngsters emerging onto the scene. After eight days of action, the results provided a mix of predictable yet unpredictable results. Big names made it through with relative ease. Among them, Roger Federer and Rafael Nadal, the top two seeds in the tournament, have moved onto the quarterfinals. However, big names fell short, including a first-round exit from Wawrinka, a third-round exit from del Potro, and Chung’s fourth-round upset over Djokovic. The youngsters have also made statements on the court, with impressive wins from Dimitrov, Chung, Edmund, and Sandgren, while veteran players Berdych and Cilic have both put up solid performances to notch the remaining quarterfinal spots. We have chosen four players who have the best shot at being the 2018 Australian Open champion based on the numbers pulled from the ATP (Association of Tennis Professionals) and numbers from their recent matches from ESPN Courtcast. Rankings were based on data involving top 20 matchups within the past 52 weeks played on hard courts. With the stage set for the quarterfinals, we determined that Nadal, Dimitrov, Federer, and Chung stood the best shot of winning it all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ao18/nadal.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rafael Nadal&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    As the #1 seed and one of the fan-favorites, Rafael Nadal will be looking for his second Australian Open title. After all, with respect to serving, he has a knack for not making mistakes and capitalizing on the offensive end. For instance, he ranks 5th in 1st serve percentage at 69.8%, so he consistently forces opponents to return his most difficult serves. As a result, he wins his service games 84.5% of the time, which gives him an 11th place ranking when playing against top 20 players. Nadal’s return game also makes him a superb defender. For example, he ranks 12th in 1st serve return points won with a 29.2% win percentage, so he keeps the ball in play and makes his opponent earn 1st serve points. Similarly, he is 10th in 2nd serve return points won at 51.6%, so he not only returns these serves, but he can become the aggressor even while on defense. For break points saved, he ranks 3rd at a clutch 73.3%.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    In his most recent match against #24 Diego Schwartzman, Nadal won in a grueling 4 sets. Nadal’s serving prowess prevailed, as he had 7 aces despite his opponent ranking 6th in return games won (38.6%). However, one concern that Rafa fans might have going forward is his stamina. The Schwartzman match was very taxing due to the frequency of long rallies and the four hours it took for the match to finish, so Nadal must be feeling the effects of running around under the Australian heat. But, given what he has proven over the years, this should be a minor issue for one of the game’s legends.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ao18/dimitrov.png&quot; alt=&quot;Grigor Dimitrov&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming off an incredible 2017 season, Grigor Dimitrov as the #3 in the tournament is still searching for his first Grand Slam title. The Bulgarian has come onto the scene as of late, as his rapid ascent can be attributed to his youthful energy and skill. After all, his serving has been terrific, as he ranks 8th in 1st serve percentage at 66.0%. With this in mind, it makes sense that Dimitrov ranks 10th in service games won at an 85.4% clip. Aside from being a competent server, he also thrives in the return game. For instance, he ranks 10th in return games won at 22.6%, which shows that he can occasionally get a crucial break. Finally, in the under pressure category, Dimitrov saved 69.2% of his break points, good for 7th overall. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    In the fourth round against the Australian home favorite Nick Kyrgios, Dimitrov won in 4 sets, but it wasn’t easy by any means. Dimitrov had to win 3 tiebreaks to win each of his sets, which is a good sign for his performance in important moments. Also, Dimitrov slammed his way to 64 winners and won 68% of his net approaches, which demonstrates his poise with forehands, backhands, and volleys. However, one area of concern for Dimitrov has to be the amount of double faults that he accrues. After all, he did commit 7 of them against Kyrgios, and he has averaged an unusually high 4.1 double faults per match. If he can keep his serving hiccups in check, he should be a prime contender for the title.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ao18/roger.png&quot; alt=&quot;Roger Federer&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The defending champ, finishing off 2017 as the No. 2 seed, enters the quarterfinal looking for his 20th major title and 6th Australian Open trophy. At age 36, Roger Federer still looks in top shape. Against Fucsovics in the fourth round, Federer fired 34 winners and secured 67% of his 48 net approaches. Even still, Federer’s serve is still his best weapon, winning 83% of first serve points and 76% of his second serve points. These numbers shouldn’t surprise many, as Federer ranks fifth against the top 20 in service games won. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    He doesn’t have that many weaknesses either. Upon significantly improving his backhand, Federer turned what was once a burden against baseline-hugging opponents into a formidable stroke. However, Federer continues to struggle with break-point conversions. Against Fucsovics, Federer had ten opportunities to break Fucsovic’s serve but only converted three of those points. In the past year, he only converted 36.2% of those opportunities, 46th among pros against the top 20. Still, expect Federer’s serve, forehand, net skills, and aggressive nature to propel him further into the tournament.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Against Fucsovics&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;ul class=&quot;articlelist&quot;&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Aces: 6&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Double Faults: 2&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Break points: 3/10 (30%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Winners/Unforced Errors: 34/28&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;1st serve points won: 40/48 (83%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;2nd serve points won: 25/33 (76%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Net points won: 28/42 (67%)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Against Top 20 for past 52 weeks&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;ul class=&quot;articlelist&quot;&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;1st in 1st Serve Points won (79.9%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;5th in 2nd Serve Points won (58.9%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;5th in Service Games won (90.1%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;6th in 1st Serve Return Points won (30.7%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;16th in 2nd Serve Return Points won (50.6%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;9th in Return Games won (23.1%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;46th in Break Points Converted (36.2%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;9th in Break Points Saved (68.6%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;4th in Tiebreaks won (66.7%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;1st in Deciding Sets Won&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Highest “Under Pressure” Rating (ATP)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/ao18/chung.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hyeon Chung&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hyeon Chung was probably was probably one of the more surprising quarterfinalists. After all, the 21 year-old entered his first Grand Slam quarterfinal, pulling the upset of the tournament by defeating his idol Novak Djokovic in the fourth round. The matchup was intriguing, as Chung’s baseline game closely mirrored Djokovic’s dominating playstyle when he was healthy, but he ultimately showed that he will be a force to be reckoned with. Among his weapons, Chung hit 47 winners and won 65% of his first serve points. Even though no part of his game sticks out as a dominating feature, Chung controlled the tempo of a majority of rallies and proved to be the better player under pressure, winning both tiebreaks in the match. At the same time, Chung was extremely efficient in break-point opportunities, stealing six of his ten chances against Djokovic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Against Djokovic&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;ul class=&quot;articlelist&quot;&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Aces: 1&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Double Faults: 2&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Break Points: 6/10 (60%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Winners/Unforced Errors: 47/37&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;First Serve points won: 59/91 (65%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;2nd Serve points won: 21/45 (47%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Net Points won: 12/21 (57%)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Against Top 20 in 2016&lt;/h4&gt;
        &lt;ul class=&quot;articlelist&quot; &gt;
            &lt;li&gt;68 in 1st Serve Points Won (67.7%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;60th in 2nd Serve Points Won (47.2%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;57th in Service Games won (74%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;10th in 1st Serve Return Points won (29.8%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;41st in 2nd Serve Return Points won (46.7%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;20th in Return games won (19.2%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;48th in Break Points Converted (35.2%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;62th in Break Points Saved (56.1%)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;11th in Tiebreaks won&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;5th in Deciding sets Won&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    Perhaps the most glaring weakness of Chung’s game is his second serve. Against Djokovic, Chung only won 47% of his second serve points. Even though he made a solid 67% of his first serves in, expect Chung’s future opponents to capitalize on his 88.8 mph second serves. Even so, Chung’s consistency, precise strikes, and solid groundstrokes, if not flashy, should frustrate many opponents moving forward.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
            Source: ATP
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Veroulis and Stephen Chen</name></author><summary type="html">In a game where individuals, not teams, play one another, parity should rule the day. However, living legends of tennis still remain amidst a flurry of youngsters emerging onto the scene. After eight days of action, the results provided a mix of predictable yet unpredictable results.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An In-Depth Look at NCAA Pac-12 Women’s Soccer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wsoccer18" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An In-Depth Look at NCAA Pac-12 Women’s Soccer" /><published>2018-01-13T18:45:55-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-13T18:45:55-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wsoccer18</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wsoccer18">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets//wsoccer18/soccer.png&quot; alt=&quot;UCLA Women's Soccer&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Courtesy: UCLA&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Women’s collegiate soccer is thriving on the west coast. Less than two months ago, the championship game of the College Cup saw two Pac-12 powerhouses go head-to-head in Orlando, Florida. Stanford emerged with a 3-2 victory over UCLA to secure their second title since 2011 and the conference’s fourth in that seven-year span. Both teams are set up extremely well heading into next season, and the road to a national championship appears to run through California.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    The following is a comprehensive introduction to the statistics of NCAA women’s soccer, focusing specifically on Pac-12 teams during conference play. I scraped and organized the data using Python and did the analysis/visuals in R. A couple issues in the data: Stanford’s website does not list minutes played, so all analysis using the minutes variables excludes Stanford players. Also, Oregon State changed the format of their website before the last conference game, so I was unable to get data from their 1-0 win over Oregon. All warnings aside, let’s jump into it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    Soccer is a particularly hard sport to quantify; there are very few goals per game and very few games in a season. Without passing data or advanced player tracking technology, we do not have much to work with aside from basic counting statistics. Games played, games started, and minutes played can tell us about the usage of a player, while goals, assists, points (goals*2 + assists), shots, and shots on goal represent offensive production. But there are no specific measurements for defense. Using minutes played per game and percentage of games started (GS/GP) as a proxy can tell us how much a coach trusts a player, but it does not directly measure performance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    In short, counting stats cannot be solely relied upon to judge a player’s value. The eye test is more applicable in soccer compared to most other major sports. However, numbers can still be applied in many situations, a few outlined below. Let’s overview the dynamics of the Pac-12 conference teams during the 2017 season.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    Parity in college soccer is relatively low. Stanford was the top team in the country and on a tier of its own in the Pac-12, going a perfect 11-0-0. UCLA and USC followed closely behind, and were legitimate contenders for a national championship. The middle ground of the conference made up schools that at least made the tournament: Arizona, Cal, Colorado, and Washington State. The rest fill out the bottom. A large disparity exists in the talent level between the best and the worst, resulting in few upsets and relatively predictable games. One must be very careful when making comparisons across teams. Here is why:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets//wsoccer18/goalscored.png&quot; alt=&quot;Goals Scored By School&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Notice the large discrepancies. If you’re on a good team, you’re going to have the ball a lot. Teams like Stanford and UCLA dominate possession and get a lot of high quality opportunities (that lead to goals) while limiting their opponent’s. Good players on bad teams simply do not have the quality of teammates around them to facilitate the same volume of scoring chances. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Additionally, positions must be taken into account when comparing players. Forwards and midfielders, for example, often have different roles. Jessie Fleming, a member of Canada’s national team and 2016 Olympian, is often described as the &quot;straw that stirs the drink&quot; for UCLA. She finished fourth on the team with 5 points in 10 conference games (for context, UCLA’s top scorer was Hailie Mace with 15 points in 11 games). Point is that Fleming was not relied upon for offense. She played as a holding midfielder who would control possession and set up the attack from deep. Stanford’s Andi Sullivan holds a similar pedigree as one of the best players in the country, and she did not score at all in conference play. This is why we will not focus too much on offensive numbers, but rather explore other variables that can give more insight.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Enter the usage statistics mentioned above; games played, games started, and minutes played. Generally, good players will start most or all of their games played, and will play a lot of minutes. Of course, there will still be variability between teams and some schools may use players in situations where they otherwise wouldn’t if they had a better option. Still, usage statistics are less volatile and more encompassing than pure offensive numbers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Usage by Class&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    How does the distribution among freshmen, sophomores, juniors, and seniors look? Pretty much how you would expect. The more experienced seniors play the most minutes on average. There are some superstar freshmen and some substitute-level seniors, which is why they all have similar ranges. But the overall trend is the further along in college a player is, the more minutes they are likely to play.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets//wsoccer18/usage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Usage by Class&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Three quarters of freshmen come in as substitutes or only play about half of the game. Also note that freshmen average the least GP per player out of the four classes, meaning they are most likely to serve as ‘healthy scratches’ and not play at all. There is typically an adjustment period between club soccer and college, and it’s hard to displace upperclassmen that know the system and have the experience.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    However, top recruits may be expected to step into a starting role immediately. 10 freshmen started at least 10 games last season. 6 of them were from Stanford, UCLA, or USC. It’s no secret that the top schools usually get the top incoming players. Recruiting is one of the major responsibilities of a coach and is crucial for sustained success. Stanford is a prime example of this. Freshman Catarina Macario was named the ESPNW Player of the Year and took home a myriad of other honors and awards after a historic first season. By sophomore year, many of the top talents have established themselves as starters and the interquartile range condenses leading up to seniors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Games started divided by games played as another useful usage tool as it correlates extremely well with minutes per game played:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets//wsoccer18/gamesplayed.png&quot; alt=&quot;Minutes, Games Played&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Perhaps a model can be made in the future to ‘fill in’ the missing values of Stanford players’ minutes. Just by knowing games played and games started, you can make a pretty accurate guess of minutes per game. Taking into account position and year can paint a clear picture about the usage of a player. An example:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;Player X (UCLA): 10/11 GS/GP, senior, defense&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Her GS/GP ratio is ~90%. Looking at the graph, we can guess she probably plays between 60-80 minutes per game. This implies that she is a regular starter and as she plays defense for UCLA, she occupies a pretty big role on a top team in the conference.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Player X is Mackenzie Cerda. Sure enough, she plays 71 minutes per game and is an experienced starter on the back line for UCLA. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;All-Conference Teams&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    A useful set of information is released at the end of conference play, the All-Pac-12 Conference Teams. Officials for the conference who watch a lot of soccer come together to compile a first team, second team, and third team consisting of 36 players as well as an All-Freshman team of 12. First years are eligible for the All-Conference teams. While this is a subjective ranking, it provides a solid baseline for cohort analysis. Here is a scatter plot distinguishing All-Conference players based on usage and production.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets//wsoccer18/allconf.png&quot; alt=&quot;All-Conference vs. Not&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    It's not the prettiest graph because I had to use the discrete variable of GS/GP to include Stanford, but the takeaway is clear. A crucial requisite for being included in one of the All-Conference teams is that a player must be a regular starter for their school. All of the red stars are to the right of that 80% GS/GP threshold. Being a starter appears to take precedence over points scored, which brings us to the case of Anika Rodriguez.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Rodriguez is a forward for UCLA who was tied for third in the Pac-12 with 14 points during conference play. Surely this warrants an inclusion into one of those 36 spots? Apparently not. Rodriguez started 6 of 10 conference games and played less than 50 minutes five times in that span. Perhaps the committee interpreted this as insufficient importance to her team. Rodriguez was an absolute force during the NCAA tournament and an integral part of UCLA's run to the championship game, but her inconsistent usage during conference play was probably why she did not make any of the teams.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Which begs the question, had she played for a lesser team and still put up good numbers, would she have been included in one of the three teams? I'd lean towards 'yes'. She would clearly be the main offensive threat on a team like Oregon State or Washington and her minutes and GS/GP would shoot up. That is the issue with using a subjective ranking system like this. If you were going by simply 'who are the best 36 soccer players in the conference', the majority would be from Stanford, UCLA, and USC. But usage and playing opportunity clearly hold weight in these All-Conference teams, which can hinder the perceived value of some of the more talented players buried behind superstars on top schools.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    There is a lot more to explore that I will perhaps look at in future projects, such as a deeper analysis into the makeup of teams and how that translates to success over the course of a season. Or the turnover rate (quality of seniors lost/freshmen gained/transfers) and how that relates to placement the following year. And of course, there is always more data to be acquired. And perhaps scraping box scores to examine events in individual games on a per-minute basis, or expanding to other major conferences to get a sense of college soccer as a whole. Suffice to say, this was just scratching the surface of data analysis that can be applied to NCAA women's soccer.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joey Maurer</name></author><summary type="html">Women’s collegiate soccer is thriving on the west coast. Less than two months ago, the championship game of the College Cup saw two Pac-12 powerhouses go head-to-head in Orlando, Florida. Stanford emerged with a 3-2 victory over UCLA to secure their second title since 2011 and the conference’s fourth in that seven-year span. Both teams are set up extremely well heading into next season, and the road to a national championship appears to run through California.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Analysis of Pro Prospects in Bowl Games</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/proprospects2018" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Analysis of Pro Prospects in Bowl Games" /><published>2018-01-09T17:25:17-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-09T17:25:17-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/proprospects2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/proprospects2018">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;max-width: 95%&quot;; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/banner.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pro Bowl Prospects&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Pro prospects nationwide.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    One hot topic for debate among coaches, fans, and analysts who follow college football centers around the role of pro prospects in postseason play (bowl games) and whether or not they should play. This is because several highly touted players have opted to skip their bowl games to protect their health for their future in the NFL. This trend captures a very small portion of players who declare for the NFL Draft, but notable players such as Josh Rosen and Derwin James have skipped their games this year to prevent injuries. While it is unfortunate to see such great talent not on the field one last time, many pro prospects still suit up to play for their school in bowl games. In fact, I am interested to see whether the prospects who did play had a positive or negative impact on their team’s performances during bowl season. After all, even though these players are supremely talented, they might have played cautiously to avoid injury, or they could have been distracted by the possibility of going to the NFL. Whatever the case may be, I plan to look at the performances of the top ten quarterback prospects who played in the postseason (according to WalterFootball.com), as this position arguably has the most impact on the outcome of a game.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/darnold.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sam Darnold&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    To begin, the top quarterback prospect to have played in a bowl game was Sam Darnold of USC. Darnold was unable to perform at the level that he has displayed in the past, as his team was demolished by a ferocious Ohio State defense. The USC offense was only able to muster a measly 7 points in the game, and the touchdown the Trojans did get wasn’t even accounted for by Darnold. The USC star threw for 356 yards with no touchdowns and an interception, which gave him an abysmal 35.0 QBR (quarterback rating), a little more than half of the 68.9 QBR he averaged during the season. Plus, he struggled with being comfortable in the pocket, as he was sacked for a season high 8 times by the Ohio State defense. This performance was exactly the opposite of what he did in the Rose Bowl last year, where he directed a masterful comeback against Penn State. Perhaps this year Darnold was rattled by distractions from scouts and NFL teams, as he declared for the draft shortly after the loss to Ohio State. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/allen.png&quot; alt=&quot;Josh Allen&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    The next prospect to have played in a bowl was Josh Allen of Wyoming, who shined in his post-season action against Central Michigan. Allen led an explosive Cowboys offense to a 37-14 win, as the quarterback threw for an amazing 3 touchdowns on only 11 completions and 19 total attempts passing for a QBR of 79.2. In addition, Allen had a nice 7-yard run that showed off his improvisational skills. His ability to create plays, arm strength, and impeccable size have impressed scouts, who think he is similar to another small-school quarterback, Ben Roethlisberger. His play in this bowl game should improve his draft stock, as it should make up for his struggles in the regular season, where he had a pedestrian 56.2 QBR and had to adjust to a depleted Wyoming roster. Five players, including star running back Brian Hill, were lost to the NFL, so Allen had less weapons on offense than last year. This explains why he threw for 12 fewer touchdowns and over 1,000 fewer yards than last season. However, his most recent performance should make him a top-10 draft pick. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/jackson.png&quot; alt=&quot;Lamar Jackson&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Perhaps one of the most electrifying players in all of college football is Lamar Jackson of Louisville, last year’s Heisman Trophy winner. The dual threat quarterback put up similar numbers offensively in comparison to last year, as he had 28 passing touchdowns and 18 rushing touchdowns in 2017, while he had 30 passing touchdowns and 21 rushing touchdowns in 2016. However, Jackson’s play dropped off in the bowl game against Mississippi State. In a losing effort, Jackson only led his offense to 6 second-half points, which contributed to their losing effort. Although Jackson thrived on the ground with 158 rushing yards for one touchdown, it was through the air where he struggled mightily. After all, he threw for a mere 171 yards with only 13 completions and a 41.9% completion percentage, which yielded a 47.4 QBR. Even worse, he threw 4 interceptions, and one was when Louisville was driving to take the lead late in the fourth quarter. This performance should bring up questions about Jackson’s decision making skills when throwing the ball, which could hurt his draft stock and make him a mid-round pick. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/mayfield.png&quot; alt=&quot;Baker Mayfield&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Next up is this year’s Heisman winner, Baker Mayfield of Oklahoma. A former walk-on, Mayfield has elevated his level of play dramatically over the past three years, as he has led Oklahoma’s prolific offense in the pass happy Big 12 Conference. This year, Mayfield’s numbers were insane, as he threw for 43 total touchdowns against just 6 interceptions, which gave him a stellar 89.7 QBR on the season. Unfortunately, this level of play did not translate to the national semifinal game against Georgia, where his team lost in double overtime 54-48. Mayfield’s offense started out strong, as the team scored on its first four possessions against the talented Georgia defense. But Mayfield could only orchestrate one touchdown drive throughout the second half and both over-times, which allowed Georgia to climb out of a 17-point first half deficit. Georgia’s halftime adjustments on defense seemed to stymie Mayfield and the Sooners, which isn’t a good sign for Mayfield since he will be facing much tougher defenses at the next level. Mayfield ended the game with a 64.0 QBR, his worst rating in a game all season. Nevertheless, looking at his whole body of work this season, he deserves to be a first-round pick. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/lock.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drew Lock&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Moving on, there is Drew Lock of Missouri, who struggled for the most part against a mediocre Texas defense that ranked 108th out of 129 FBS teams with 257.9 passing yards allowed per game. Not to mention, but Texas’s top safety DeShon Elliott sat out the game to prepare for the NFL Draft. So, coming into the game, the Missouri offense clearly had a mismatch with a mediocre Texas team. Lock was largely responsible for Missouri’s 15th best offense in the nation with 37.5 points scored per game. After all, he had a magnificent season with 44 passing touchdowns and 3964 yards through the air. Therefore, it was a surprise to see the explosive Missouri squad only muster 16 points and 269 yards passing, especially when they had just won six games straight with 45+ points scored in each of those contests. Lock didn’t have the inspired performance many scouts expected, as he threw just 18 completions on 34 attempts with one touchdown and one interception, which gave him a disappointing 48.0 QBR for the game. The only thing that can explain this result is the change in offensive coordinator for Missouri, but even this is a poor excuse for what should have been an easy win for Lock and the Tigers. Looking at the big picture, this effort should downgrade his draft stock and make him a mid-round pick.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/rudolph.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mason Rudolph&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    Furthermore, Mason Rudolph of Oklahoma State was one of the few quarterback prospects who met expectations in the postseason. A consistent performer throughout the regular season, Rudolph threw for an impeccable 4904 yards with 37 passing touchdowns to 9 interceptions to give him a respectable 83.8 QBR for the season. His main connection was with star receiver James Washington, who had over 1000 receiving yards this year. Rudolph has impressive size at 6 foot 5 and 230 pounds, and his leadership skills have been highly touted by scouts. This is probably why he was motivated to get his school and teammates a win in the bowl game against Virginia Tech. Rudolph impressed with 351 passing yards, 2 touchdowns, and no interceptions against a stingy Virginia Tech defense that ranked 5th in the nation with 13.5 points allowed per game. This kind of play could translate well to the NFL, where Rudolph will have to face even tougher defenses while con-tinuing to make good decisions. In addition to his skills on the field, his intangibles could earn him a spot in the first few rounds of the draft. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/stidham.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jarrett Stidham&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    The next highest quarterback prospect is Jarrett Stidham, an Auburn standout who transferred from Baylor. Stidham had a decent season on a strong Auburn team, as he led his team to a 10 win sea-son with 3158 passing yards and 18 touchdowns thrown. His 61.0 QBR during the season was good enough to get wins for most of the season, as the Auburn defense carried the team at times, but when better teams like LSU came along, the quarterback’s efforts were not good enough. This was especially evident in their bowl game to UCF, a small conference opponent who many considered inferior to Auburn before their matchup. Auburn ultimately lost 34-27 to UCF, who complet-ed the nation’s only perfect season this year. Stidham’s play in this game definitely didn’t help Auburn’s cause, as he threw two interceptions and rushed for negative 25 yards due to the 6 sacks he endured. The 32.0 QBR he earned in this bowl game was miserable, and Auburn’s loss to a small school like UCF could be chalked up to their quarterback play. Stidham didn’t do any favors for himself in terms of his NFL draft standing, as scouts are probably questioning his poise and decision making skills; he should be a late-round pick.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/ferguson.png&quot; alt=&quot;Riley Ferguson&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Another quarterback standout is Riley Ferguson from Memphis, who led his team with prolific offensive numbers that rivaled those of predecessor Paxton Lynch. Ferguson completed 63.1% of his passes, threw for 4257 yards, had 38 passing touchdowns, and possessed a 76.8 QBR on the season. Games versus UCLA and Connecticut made him stand out early in the season and put him on the map for many scouts. Against UCLA, he threw 6 passing touchdowns and torched the UCLA defense with 41 offensive points. In an even better performance versus Connecticut, Ferguson erupted for 7 passing touchdowns, 431 yards in the air, and had an unbelievable 91.7 QBR for that game. The sustained success that Memphis had under Ferguson’s leadership led the team to the #20 spot in the College Football Playoff Rankings before their bowl matchup against Iowa State. Many believed Memphis would crush Iowa State with a powerful offense, but Ferguson and the Tigers did not show up like they had during the regular season. The star quarterback threw for a modest 286 yards, was sacked 6 times, and had a QBR of 50.1. As a result of this meager quarterback play, the Tigers only put up 20 points in a 1 point loss, their second fewest points scored by the team all season. Ferguson’s ability to read defenses before the snap could be a weakness that scouts note due to the amount of sacks he took. Due to this poor postseason showing, Ferguson could be slotted as a late-round pick.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/benkert.png&quot; alt=&quot;Kurt Benkert&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    To continue, Kurt Benkert was a bright spot on a Virginia team that ended the season with a losing record. The quarterback threw for 3207 yards passing and 25 touchdowns against just 9 interceptions, and he has shown flashes of greatness against Boise State and Miami. In the Boise State game, Benkert led Virginia to victory with 3 passing touchdowns in a 42-23 win. Against Miami, he had a gutsy performance with 4 passing touchdowns and an insane 384 passing yards that put him on the radar. Unfortunately, these efforts did not translate to the all important bowl game against Navy, where Benkert had arguably his worst game of the season. He threw for only 145 yards, did not account for a touchdown, threw an interception, and had an awful 10.7 QBR for the game. As a result, Virginia was pounded by Navy 49-7, and there were no positive takeaways from this game for Benkert. Navy’s defense wasn’t even that great this season, as they allowed just under 28 points per game coming into this matchup. So, scouts must be concerned about Benkert’s potential performances against NFL defenses that feast on mistakes from quarterbacks. Due to his recent efforts, Benkert is poised to be a late-round pick.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/proprospects2018/white.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mike White&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    The last quarterback prospect to be analyzed is Mike White of Western Kentucky, who thrived during the regular season under a pass happy offense. Specifically, White has thrown for 63 touchdowns over the past two years, and he has over 4000 pass yards each of the past two years. At one point this season, White had a tremendous stretch where he threw for 5 touchdowns in consecutive games against in conference foes Charlotte and Old Dominion. However, White and his team lost 5 of their final six games, including their bowl game against Georgia State. The standout quarterback performed poorly in the postseason, where he led his team to just 17 offensive points against an average Georgia State defense that was ranked 55th in the nation with 25.5 points allowed per game. White threw a costly interception late in the fourth quarter that ended the game, and his 31.9 QBR was his second worst rating of all games this season. Scouts must be wondering what version of White will show up in the NFL; his 6 foot 4 inch frame projects well to the next level, but his lack of athleticism and throwing strength are concerns. White should be a late-round pick if he is drafted at all. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Through an analysis of the top ten NFL quarterback prospects who played in bowl games, it is clear that these players did not live up to expectations in postseason play. Overall, these quarterbacks combined for a 2-8 record in bowl season, which shows that they were probably more focused on the NFL than anything else. The only two winners were Josh Allen and Mason Rudolph, the only quarterbacks in the top ten who surpassed their regular season QBRs in postseason play. Also, the average QBR of 48.3 for the top ten quarterbacks in bowl games was significantly lower than their average QBR for the season as a whole, which was 69.0. Although these players are supremely talented, these prospects clearly have other things on their minds that might be hindering their play. Whether they are thinking of avoiding injury or if they simply don’t care about the game’s result, the numbers support the idea that these players didn’t show the same level of commitment as they did in the regular season. 
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Veroulis</name></author><summary type="html">One hot topic for debate among coaches, fans, and analysts who follow college football centers around the role of pro prospects in postseason play (bowl games) and whether or not they should play. This is because several highly touted players have opted to skip their bowl games to protect their health for their future in the NFL. This trend captures a very small portion of players who declare for the NFL Draft, but notable players such as Josh Rosen and Derwin James have skipped their games this year to prevent injuries.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Think Twice Against ESPN Fantasy Projections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/thinktwice" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Think Twice Against ESPN Fantasy Projections" /><published>2017-09-19T15:20:51-07:00</published><updated>2017-09-19T15:20:51-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/thinktwice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/thinktwice">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/avg-error.png&quot; alt=graph&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    With the second week of the NFL concluding last night with a 24–10 victory for the Lions over the Giants, I decided to take a look at ESPN fantasy point projection accuracy thus far. 
    ESPN is one of the leading hosts for fantasy football leagues around the country with millions of people trusting their projections to decide which players they should start. After comparing the starting point projections for each week against the actual number of points the player earned, it looks like ESPN has to step up their game.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    Having an average error percentage of 98.54%, ESPN projections for defense thus far staggers above any other position. Week 1 especially was awful with an error percentage of 108%! It’s almost as if they are spitting out projected numbers at random! According to FiveThirtyEight, week 1 had the fewest amount of “close” games in NFL history with only 3 games decided by 7 points or fewer, so it makes sense as to why defensive points were so scattered all over the place. To hurt ESPN’s credibility to predict defensive performances further, week 2 was nearly just as bad with an error percentage of 89%. Perhaps, the NFL is trending towards becoming a lopsided league like the MLB.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    Another interesting statistic to look at besides error percentage is ESPN’s point differential between actual and projected points.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/1*QnSRFkUDKXHGxpBKS8o_qw.png&quot; alt=graph2&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
        Across every position besides a kicker, the point differential hovers around 5 points. For some high scoring positions like a quarter back, and some good running backs, 5 points does not have much of a difference. But, compared to lower scoring positions like defense and tight end, 5 points is precious.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
        Week 2 projection accuracy in both error percentage and point differential was better as the number of blowout games decreased. Fantasy football fans can only hope the accuracy improves each week.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
        While there are still 15 weeks left in the season, ESPN projections for defense and a tight end seem to be random guesses as to how they will perform. Surprisingly, quarterback and kicker projections seem to be a fantasy player’s best bet when deciding between who to start. So, for the average Joe fantasy player who only puts in players with a projected high amount of points, you may want to start to think twice and do some personal research!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
            Data was scraped from &lt;a href = &quot;http://www.espn.com/fantasy/football/&quot;&gt;ESPN Fantasy Football&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
            Fantasy Points are based off the &lt;a href = &quot;http://games.espn.com/ffl/resources/help/content?name=scoring-settings-standard&quot;&gt;PPR Standard Scoring&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Konner Macias</name></author><summary type="html">With the second week of the NFL concluding last night with a 24–10 victory for the Lions over the Giants, I decided to take a look at ESPN fantasy point projection accuracy thus far. ESPN is one of the leading hosts for fantasy football leagues around the country with millions of people trusting their projections to decide which players they should start. After comparing the starting point projections for each week against the actual number of points the player earned, it looks like ESPN has to step up their game.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Kershaw-less Dodgers: A Not So Dark Time…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/kershawless" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Kershaw-less Dodgers: A Not So Dark Time…" /><published>2017-08-29T15:20:51-07:00</published><updated>2017-08-29T15:20:51-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/kershawless</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/kershawless">&lt;p&gt;As the Los Angeles Dodgers end the month of August, they are still the heavy favorite to win the World Series. Since July 23rd, 2017, Clayton Kershaw has not played one game for the Dodgers. Many fans thought the absence of their star pitcher would be devastating to their pace to break the MLB record for best win percentage. While his back injury should of been disastrous, it appears at though the Dodgers are doing just fine without Clayton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since his last game, the Dodgers have been on a tear. With a win percentage of 76.7% over the last 30 games, they have continued to dominate the NL West with a 19 game lead over second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kershaw1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Win percentage&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the date of his injury, the Dodgers were only sitting at a 68.7% win percentage. Shockingly, the rest of the Dodgers pitchers seem unfazed without their leader. When compared against the entire season, the pitching staff seems to be doing at least on par if not better than when Kershaw was active. Looking at the team’s ERA, earned run average, and WHIP, a statistic which tells a pitcher’s propensity for allowing batters to reach base, we see nearly similar numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kershaw2.png&quot; alt=&quot;ERA and WHIP&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 60vw&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing against all Dodgers who have started at least 3 games, the Dodgers have put up lower ERA and WHIP numbers during Clayton’s absence. So, who is Kershaw’s replacement that’s making this possible? The rest of the regular pitchers are doing great as always, but who has been filling the gap? The answer is Yu Darvish.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kershaw3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Yu Darvish&quot; style=&quot;float: left; padding-right: 10px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;Recently traded from the Texas Rangers on July 31st, Darvish was just what the Dodgers needed. Since his time for The Blue Crew, he has posted an ERA of 3.13 and WHIP of 1.16. Though he has only played four games, he is producing numbers just on par with the rest of the pitching staff. With a pitching staff still remaining strong, then that leaves the Dodger’s batting for these crazy win percentage numbers. With Turner, Bellinger, Seager, and the gang still beating up on other teams, it appears as though they all consciously making up for the absence of the 3-time Cy Young winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s not forget what Kershaw brings the table. We cannot expect these hitters to continue to perform at this high of caliber through the rest of season and playoffs. While it’s tough to remember, Kershaw was off to another amazing year for the Dodgers in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed&quot; src =&quot;/assets/kershaw4.png&quot; alt=&quot;With and without Kershaw&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why they pay him the big bucks, with a 2.04 ERA and 0.88 WHIP for the Boys in Blue. Kershaw’s impact cannot be forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just yesterday, Manager, Dave Roberts, just reported that Kershaw will be returning to the mound Friday against the Padres. If he’s anything like what he was at the start of the season, it will alleviate a lot of pressure off the batters, and make for a historic rest of a season for the Dodgers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;cited&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
          Source: baseball-reference.com
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Konner Macias</name></author><summary type="html">As the Los Angeles Dodgers end the month of August, they are still the heavy favorite to win the World Series. Since July 23rd, 2017, Clayton Kershaw has not played one game for the Dodgers. Many fans thought the absence of their star pitcher would be devastating to their pace to break the MLB record for best win percentage. While his back injury should of been disastrous, it appears at though the Dodgers are doing just fine without Clayton.</summary></entry></feed>