<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-11-29T00:22:37-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bruin Sports Analytics</title><author><name>Bruin Sports Analytics</name></author><entry><title type="html">2018 Ballon d’Or: A Look at the Contenders and their Numbers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ballonDOr" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2018 Ballon d'Or: A Look at the Contenders and their Numbers" /><published>2018-11-28T22:23:26-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-28T22:23:26-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ballonDOr</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ballonDOr">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Lionel Messi winning the 2016 Ballon d'Or (Credit: Getty Images)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;What is it?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 3, 2018, the French publication France Football will announce the winner of this year's Ballon d'Or, which translates to the &quot;Golden Ball&quot;. The award, which recognizes the best male footballer in the world, has been around for a while now.  In fact, this will be the 53rd time that it will be awarded. Every year, the speculation around who the eventual winner will be creates a ton of buzz, and this year is no different. Before we join in on that hype train, let's take a look at how the &quot;Golden Ball&quot; has exchanged hands over the last of couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To any football fan, it would come as no shock to learn that ever since 2008, the award has been shared by just two players - Cristiano Ronaldo and Lionel Messi. Both have secured 5 Ballon d'Ors each (or the FIFA Ballon d'Or, as it was known from 2010 to 2015) in the last decade. Ever since Kaka picked up the award in 2007 after a terrific season with A.C. Milan, Ronaldo and Messi's sheer dominance of the game has made the Ballon d'Or a two-horse race, with the rest of the world just battling to earn a place alongside them in the top three. This year, however, that could very well change.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
		&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Cristiano Ronaldo with his 5 Ballon d'Ors (Credit: AFP/Getty Images)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When France Football announced the 30-man shortlist on October 9, there were not many surprises. The usual suspects including Ronaldo, Messi, Luis Suarez, Neymar were all included. However, the members of the World Cup winning France team are the ones making headway in the race to win the prestigious award. With only a week to go, the press is speculating that Ronaldo and Messi will not even finish in the top three. So if Ronaldo and Messi aren't the favorites, who can snag up the Ballon d'Or?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Who are the contenders?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask the bookmakers, it is the Croatian midfielder Luka Modric who is by far the favorite. Winning his fourth UEFA Champions League with Real Madrid was probably enough to earn him a nomination, but it was his incredible display in Russia that has made him the favorite in the eyes of the press, as well as the bookies. Under his leadership, Croatia became the runners up in what was a fairytale run up to the finals of the 2018 FIFA World Cup . Modric picked up 3 Man of the Match trophies along the way, while also snatching the award for the Best Player of the Tournament, which is also coincidentally titled the Golden Ball. He also led the field in terms of the most miles covered during the tournament, which goes to show how much work he put in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
		&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Luka Modric with his Best Player of the Tournament Award (Credit: Reuters)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the incredible performance in Russia, he received a lot of praise and accolades, as he went on to beat his Real Madrid teammate Ronaldo and Liverpool's Mohamed Salah to win both the UEFA Men's Player of the Year and The Best FIFA Men's Player awards. Winning these two individual awards have bolstered his chances of picking up the Ballon d'Or as well. However, a poor start to the new season with Real Madrid, which resulted in the sacking of the newly appointed manager Julen Lopetegui, and Croatia's relegation to League B in the inaugural season of the UEFA Nations League, have shown that Modric has failed to capitalize on an amazing summer. While this poor post-World Cup performance might deter some people to vote for him, most believe that it won't be enough to deny him his first Ballon d'Or.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the fact that it was Modric's World Cup performance that has put him in front of the race, it isn't shocking that the other front runners also had a tremendous World Cup campaign. The French World Cup winning trio of Antoine Griezmann, Kylian Mbappe, and Raphael Varane are hot on Modric's tail to get the nod for the honor. Griezmann, the Atletico Madrid forward, has been consistently performing at the top level for years now, and 2018 for him wasn't any different. He helped Atletico lift the UEFA Europa League and was named the Europa League's Player of the Season for his efforts. He continued his exceptional form in Russia as well. By scoring 4 goals and chipping in with 2 assists, he helped France secure the World Cup. He also snatched up the Man of the Match award in the World Cup final.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
		&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&gt;Antoine Griezmann, Raphael Varane and Kylian Mbappe representing France in the 2018 FIFA World Cup (Credit: Goal.com)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Griezmann was the focal point of the French forward line, it was the 19 year old Paris Saint-Germain winger who was garnering a lot of attention for all the right reasons. The 2017-18 season ended with Mbappe lifting the Ligue 1 title as well as the Coupe de France in what was a really successful first season for him in Paris. He quickly followed that up with a stunning World Cup performance. He scored two against Argentina and scored with a brilliant 25 yard strike against Croatia in the final, which led to him winning the FIFA World Cup Best Young Player Award. The 2018-19 season has gone off to a blistering start for him. His numbers are a lot higher as compared to the previous season in almost every aspect. While he is a strong contender to win the Ballon d'Or, he is also the outright favorite to lift the Kopa Trophy, which is awarded by France Football to the best performing player under the age of 21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the third member of the French team who has also been in the limelight is the Real Madrid centre-back Varane. Along with Sergio Ramos, he formed the backbone of Real Madrid's defense as they lifted the UEFA Champions League trophy in yet another successful campaign in Europe. He carried that success over in Russia as he helped the French defense keep 4 clean sheets on their way to victory. He was the anchor of the French defense, and he even scored the opening goal in the quarterfinal win against Uruguay. If he does win, he will be the first defender since Fabio Cannavaro to do so, who had led Italy as they were crowned the 2006 FIFA World Cup champions. However, Varane's bid to win the award has suffered the same blow as Modric's, as Real Madrid's dismal performance during the start of this 2018-19 season has left them in 6th place in the La Liga standings. Madrid's shaky defense has played a significant role in their poor form, and Varane hasn't done nearly enough to be immune from the blame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ronaldo and Messi haven't had a bad year either by any standards. Cristiano Ronaldo, along with his Real Madrid teammates, won the UEFA Champions League for the third consecutive year. Moreover, he had a decent performance in Russia as well, scoring 4 goals (including a hattrick) against Spain. Following the World Cup, Ronaldo again made headlines by transferring to Juventus. While many were skeptical about how successful he'd be in Italy, he has proved his critics wrong by quickly adapting to the Series A and he's currently the joint top scorer while also being second in terms of assists. Messi, on the other hand, won the domestic double as he played an integral role in another one of FC Barcelona's dominant seasons in Spain. Although a disappointing summer in Russia hampered his hopes of ever winning the biggest tournament in football, it has been business as usual for Messi and his Barcelona teammates. They are at the top of their Champions League group and second in La Liga, trailing Sevilla by just one point. While they aren't the favorites anymore, it can't be denied that both of them have again had a tremendous year individually, while also picking up some silverware along the way. These two have perennially been at the top of the football world, and even though the dynamics are changing, they aren't leaving anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
		&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Salah celebrating after scoring a goal (Credit: Reuters)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rounding up the list of possible contenders is Liverpool forward Mohamed Salah. He took the Premier League by storm last year as he became the top scorer with 32 goals, which is the highest tally since Alan Shearer's 34 goal haul during the 1994-95 season. Add to that the fact that Liverpool completely surpassed expectations and reached the UEFA Champions League finals, and you've got yourself the perfect candidate for the Ballon d'Or. Unfortunately for Salah, he was subbed in the first half of the Champions League final after suffering a shoulder injury, and had to watch his teammates suffer defeat at the hands of  Real Madrid. The injury also played a role in limiting his participation in the World Cup. Despite that, he managed to score both of Egypt's goals in the tournament. The fact that he was nominated in the top three for both the UEFA Men's Player of the Year and The Best FIFA Men's Player should have paved the way for him to be a serious contender for the Ballon d'Or, but the sheer dominance of the French trio mentioned above has pushed him down the list of favorites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;What do the stats say?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ballon d'Or takes into consideration a player's performance during the calendar year. So we're going to focus on the stats beginning from January 1, 2018. Furthermore, in a year like this, where the center of attention has undoubtedly been the FIFA World Cup, the year can be looked at as a tale of two halves. Separating the players' stats into what happened before, during, and after the World Cup can help us better analyze the numbers. Since the players play in different countries and participate in different competitions, it can often skew the statistics. For instance, the domestic cup in different countries follow different formats. England has two domestic cups in which a single knockout game decides the outcome of each game, whereas in Spain, there's only one domestic cup in which there are knockout rounds played over two legs. Since the domestic league and the UEFA Champions League are at the top of the clubs' and players' priorities, focusing on the stats from just these two competitions, along with the FIFA World Cup, can help us better make sense of each player's performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our pool of probable winners consists of 5 forwards, 1 midfielder, and 1 defender. Now the most important statistic in any football game is the number of goals. Looking at the chart for the total goals scored in the domestic league, Champions League ( Europa League in Griezmann's case), and the World Cup since January 1, it will come as no surprise that Ronaldo and Messi are comfortably leading. Obviously one can't expect a creative midfielder like Modric to match the numbers achieved by such prolific forwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
		&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the Shot Accuracy (Shots On Target/Total Attempts) and the Shots Attempted per game, it makes sense why it is highly unlikely for a player like Modric to ever reach Ronaldo's or Messi's numbers. Unsurprisingly, Ronaldo has more attempts per game than the rest. Modric attempts less than a fifth of the numbers of shots that his former Real Madrid teammate does. The far fewer attempts, which is typical for a creative midfielder, explains why he trails the others by such a huge margin in terms of goals. Messi is the only player with a shot accuracy of over 50%, whereas Modric has the worst percentage. This can be attributed to the fact that more than half of Modric's attempts come from outside the box, whereas the others have a much higher percentage of their attempts coming from inside the box.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
		&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
		&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might expect Modric with his incredible passing, link-up play, and set piece duty to comfortably led the charts for assists and chances created, but that is not the case. Messi, Griezmann, and Salah all have created more chances and have more assists in all competitions. One interesting point that is evident from the graphs is that Mbappe's performance before the World Cup wasn't anywhere close to his competitors. It is his recent burst of form, a continuation of his World Cup exploits, which has helped him gain a lot of ground in the Ballon d'Or race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
	
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these aren't the categories in which Modric is producing the best figures, then one might wonder why he is the favorite to lift the Ballon d'Or. His role as a playmaker compels him to focus more on building the attack. Receiving the ball from the defense and channeling it to the forwards is something that he is really good at, and his role in the center of the pitch allows him to connect both the flanks as well. This is made evident through the passing stats. He has completed the most passes per game, with Messi close behind him. Furthermore, Modric also helps out the team defensively, which is also an important factor. For instance, looking at the interception numbers, we can see that his defensive contributions outweigh that of the rest by quite a margin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
	
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 11&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varane is the only defender in our list of favorites. Unlike his Real Madrid teammate Marcelo, who bursts forward down the left wing quite a bit and chips in with goals and assists, Varane sticks to his centre-back duties. Looking at the data of goals conceded and the number of clean sheets can hence provide a good understanding of actually how successful he has been during this year. Comparing his stats to that of fellow La Liga centre-backs, Atletico Madrid's Diego Godin and FC Barcelona's Samuel Umtiti can help us gauge his performance relative to his peers. Looking at the graphs, it is clear that fellow Ballon d'Or nominee Godin's performances have been much more solid defensively. Even Varane's partner in the French back line, Umtiti, who wasn't even in the 30-man shortlist, has produced better numbers. As it is evident from these stats, Varane's defensive abilities don't measure up to that of his counterparts. This does bring his candidacy for the award into question.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
	
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/messiDor/pic_13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 13&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;What can we expect?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ballon d'Or is notorious for creating controversy. Disagreements over who the winner should be always takes center stage, and this year is no different. The Ballon d'Or uses the following criteria to rank players and select the eventual winner: (1) Individual and collective performances (winners) during the year, (2) Player class (talent and fair play), and (3) Overall judgment of the player's career. While the first is something that we can quantitatively measure, the other two are rather subjective, which might make it seem to the uninitiated that the Ballon d'Or is awarded quite arbitrarily. Most of the criticism regarding the selection process has often been about favoritism of one player over the other. The second and third criterions do allow some intrinsic factors to play a role in the decision. Due to this, it is entirely possible for the numbers to tell a story completely different than what the journalists deciding the winner choose to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All seven of the players that I've talked about have had an outstanding year and while it would be justifiable if any one of them received the honor, it would be a surprise for most if Modric fails to add to his collection of accolades that he has received this year. It can be argued that his stats aren't the most impressive, but a lot of what he adds to the team, whether it be in terms of skill or leadership, can't be quantified through mere numbers. For each of the last 5 years, the Ballon d'Or has gone to a member of the UEFA Champions League winning team, which also bodes well for Modric. This does show how much stress they put on &quot;collective performances&quot; and the fact that this was a World Cup year, it is bound to play even more of a role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With France winning the World Cup, Griezmann, Mbappe, and Varane have all cemented their names in the history books. However, the fact that France had a strong overall squad takes the spotlight away from their individual brilliance. They might not win the Ballon d'Or this year, but they are all young and still have a lot of years ahead of them, and it will be interesting to see how much they can improve in the seasons to come. Similarly, Salah also had a tremendous season and no one expected him to achieve the feats that he did. He could also potentially be a Ballon d'Or winner in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Ronaldo and Messi aren't the favorites, they do have the stats on their side. Both have won prestigious silverware and have displayed excellent form throughout the year. The last 10 years of Ballon d'Or have just been about these 2 extraordinary legends of the sport and both of them are still a force to be reckoned with. They show no signs of fading away as they continue to dominate the top-tiers of football in Europe. Despite their strong display, it is almost certain that on December 3, we will have a new heir to the football throne. This year has surely signaled a change in the footballing landscape and with new talents being discovered every single season, we might not have a duopoly, like the one we've seen for the past decade, for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: Goal.com, Squawka.com, Soccerstats.com, Footystats.org, Francefootball.fr&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Vedant Sahu</name></author><summary type="html">On December 3, 2018, the French publication France Football will announce the winner of this year's Ballon d'Or, which translates to the &quot;Golden Ball&quot;. The award, which recognizes the best male footballer in the world, has been around for a while now. In fact, this will be the 53rd time that it will be awarded. Every year, the speculation around who the eventual winner will be creates a ton of buzz, and this year is no different. Before we join in on that hype train, let's take a look at how the &quot;Golden Ball&quot; has exchanged hands over the last of couple of years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can the Toronto Maple Leafs Pay Up?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/NHLContracts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can the Toronto Maple Leafs Pay Up?" /><published>2018-11-28T14:55:02-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-28T14:55:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/NHLContracts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/NHLContracts">&lt;p&gt;It's no secret that William Nylander has held out on signing a contract with the Toronto Maple Leafs. As a restricted free agent about to enter into his first non-entry level NHL contract, Nylander is very limited in his options: sign with the Leafs, or don't play at all. Players rarely choose not to play at all, with many top six players opting for bridge deals - three-to-four year contracts typically valued far less than they wish in exchange for an opportunity to prove themselves more capable of a future contract more extensive in both term and salary. It is also common for players to begin negotiations asking for high pay, only to settle for what they were actually hoping for. What makes Nylander's situation unique isn't that he reportedly asked for upward of $8 million per year (money typically reserved for roughly top two talent on a team), but that he has not since backed down and signed for less. Against everyone's expectations, it is now late November, the Leafs have played over a quarter of the season, and they are still without the 22 year old Swede.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nylander's holdout begs the question: how much money should he sign for? In order to come to any sort of conclusion, one must first consider what exactly goes into the value of a contract. Player ability, clearly, is the most important variable. To find a comparison, data was used from all 965 NHL players from the 2017-18 season. For issues of sample size, a minimum of 50 games played was set, bringing the total down to 513 players. To better fit Nylander's situation, only forwards 25 years or younger were considered. Finally, only players with contracts of over $1 million per year AAV (Average Annual Value, per Cap Friendly) were included to prevent entry level contracts from significantly altering conclusions - it would be unwise to compare contract sizes otherwise when Art Ross winner Connor McDavid was only paid $925 thousand for the season. In the end, 67 players are left that fit the criteria described above. How does Nylander stack up to these 67?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most obvious comparison to draw is how many points each player earned. In the chart below, total points are plotted against contract sizes. The vertical blue line is where Nylander's 61 points would place him among his peers.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhlCon/cover.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This result may be surprising to someone that has followed the Nylander situation. While his initial request for $8 million has been deemed ridiculously high by most, it has been generally thought that he would end up receiving a contract in the $6 million to $7 million range. The linear model places Nylander very near the $5 million mark based on contracts of those with similar point totals to his. Also noteworthy is how less-than-stellar the chart makes out Nylander to be as a scorer. Though it should be stressed again that the chart is only showing young players that make over $1 million per year - you won't find many fourth line grinders here - it is interesting to point out that, among those in similar circumstances, Nylander's point total isn't exactly elite. One may consider that Nylander wasn't playing top line minutes for the Maple Leafs (about 16 minutes per game), and that total playing time (including loss of time due to injury) greatly affects year end point totals. To compensate, an adjusted plot is shown below this time using points-per-sixty minutes played along the x-axis. The result is a more linear plot, but with near identical findings in regards to Nylander.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhlCon/pic_1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, points do not tell the entire tale of player ability. However, while other statistics such as shooting percentage, Corsi, faceoff percentage (for centers), and point shares are clearly telling of how effective a player is, these statistics by themselves have little correlation when it comes to contract values, especially compared to simply the amount of points they put up. There is, as always, variation. Quality of line-mates certainly affects point totals, and it is likely that other statistics, including those listed above, have a lot to do with the variability about the regression line. But, the only other statistic that isn't directly derived from points that clearly relates to contract amounts is time on ice per game. At first glance, this appears trivial - better players get more playing time, who would've thought? - but the importance becomes more apparent when comparing two players on different teams with similar ability. Though nearly identical in skill, the one that gets more ice time per game will likely be paid more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhlCon/pic_2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This leads to another observation: player ability is without a doubt connected to how much they get paid, but, perhaps more significantly, it is player importance to a team that determines how much the team is willing to pay. Teams are restricted by the salary cap, and do not have unlimited resources to provide their players. A center, regardless of skill, would likely be paid more by the Montreal Canadiens (who notably lack center depth) than the Pittsburgh Penguins (who have Sidney Crosby and Evgeni Malkin already taking up positions). To relate this back to Nylander, it is enlightening to look at comparisons to a group of five other players around the NHL, who each have similar numbers and contracts set in stone and could be used as reference points. These players are Dylan Larkin, Jack Eichel, Jonathan Marchessault, Viktor Arvidsson, and Nikolaj Ehlers. The chart below is the same points-per-minute plot as before, but with these 5 players now marked in red (and Marchessault now added, as he did not meet the initial criteria due to age).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhlCon/pic_3.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few additional comments that should be made to give more insight into these players. Larkin, Eichel, and Ehlers each played last season at the same age as Nylander (21 years old). Arvidsson was 24 years old, but had his break-out year around the same time as the others listed. Marchessault was older at 27 years old last year, but also put up similar numbers to Nylander and signed a new contract for the 2018-19 season. In addition, Jack Eichel played only 67 games due to injury, weakening some of his statistics. Shown below is the points-per-minute for each of the players last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhlCon/pic_4.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nylander's points-per-minute is roughly the same as Arvidsson, Ehlers, and Eichel. Marchessault's higher value, being a more experienced player, can be seen as a reasonable expectation of growth for any of the other players listed. Larkin's value is lower, but that is partially accounted for with his abysmal 6.9% shooting percentage (significantly lower than his career average, which has returned to form currently in the 2018-19 season). The primary takeaway here should be how similar these players' offensive efficiencies are. The number of points put up by five of the six players (excluding Marchessault) was between 60 and 64; however, as seen below, the goal numbers vary considerably more. Compared to a player like Ehlers, the bulk of Nylander's points came through assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhlCon/pic_5.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After accounting for Eichel's missing 15 games, it is clear that Nylander and Larkin are a step behind the others when it comes to putting the puck in the net. Finally, comparing each player's relative Corsi (percentage of shot attempts taken by the player's team when he is on the ice relative to other players on the same team) suggests Ehlers and Marchessault are a level above the others when it comes to driving possession, while Nylander again takes fifth out of the six players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhlCon/pic_6.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, with the knowledge of how these players compare to each other in performance, it is revealing to compare their contracts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhlCon/pic_7.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is the cause for these significant differences? As discussed before, the importance to the team is possibly the most important factor in determining contract values - more-so than actual ability. This is especially the case for young players, who are locked in to their teams as restricted free agents. Jack Eichel is undoubtedly the franchise player for the Buffalo Sabres, whose next largest contract belongs to Kyle Okposo for $6 million per year. For the time being, nobody on the Sabres is as important to the organization as Eichel, and it certainly shows in his contract. The case is similar for Dylan Larkin. Despite only having a contract of $6.1 million, he is the highest paid player on the Detroit Red Wings, and would likely have been paid more had the team not had an expected $0 in cap space for the upcoming season (shown below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/nhlCon/pic_8.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nikolaj Ehlers has an interesting contract of $6 million despite being the fifth highest-paid person on the Winnipeg Jets. However, the Jets are in a situation with enough cap space to sign such contracts. Jonathan Marchessault and Viktor Arvidsson (playing for the Vegas Golden Knights and the Nashville Predators, respectively) have lower contracts than the rest. In Marchessault's case, it is likely due to uncertainty of replication of last year's stats (something that could be said about much of the Golden Knights' season). For Arvidsson, it is a matter of being a very good player on a team of very great players - he is tied for seventh highest paid person on the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is in these comparisons that the Nylander situation has evolved. William Nylander would likely be disappointed in Larkin's $6.1 million dollar contract. But it is simply fact that Nylander is not as important to the Toronto Maple Leafs - a team with incredible talent such as John Tavares, Morgan Reilly, and Patrick Marleau already signed to large contracts and with Auston Matthews and Mitch Marner requiring upcoming extensions - as Larkin is to the Red Wings. There just isn't space for the Maple Leafs and Nylander to come to a satisfactory deal, and if rumors of a near $7 million contract become true, it would likely end up hurting the Maple Leafs more than it helps. Unfortunately for Nylander, his standing with his team seems much more akin to Viktor Arvidsson than Jack Eichel. His raw stats suggest a $5 million contract and his reference players suggest $6 million, but his willingness to hold out and the financial state of his team suggest one of two options: either he gives in and signs for $5.5 million from Toronto, or his refusal to sign lands him roughly $6.5 million on a team that's able to pay. Either way, it is certain that Nylander will have a pivotal role on the team that signs him, and his play will certainly hold the interest of fans, if for no other reason than to see if record setting contract negotiations lead to equally impressive performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joe Dunham</name></author><summary type="html">It's no secret that William Nylander has held out on signing a contract with the Toronto Maple Leafs. As a restricted free agent about to enter into his first non-entry level NHL contract, Nylander is very limited in his options, sign with the Leafs, or don't play at all. Players rarely choose not to play at all, with many top six players opting for bridge deals - three-to-four year contracts typically valued far less than they wish in exchange for an opportunity to prove themselves more capable of a future contract more extensive in both term and salary. It is also common for players to begin negotiations asking for high pay, only to settle for what they were actually hoping for. What makes Nylander's situation unique isn't that he reportedly asked for upward of $8 million per year (money typically reserved for roughly top two talent on a team), but that he has not since backed down and signed for less. Against everyone's expectations, it is now late November, the Leafs have played over a quarter of the season, and they are still without the 22 year old Swede.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The NBA’s ‘Perfect Game’ by One of Basketball’s Rising Superstars</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jokicRisingStar" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The NBA’s ‘Perfect Game’ by One of Basketball’s Rising Superstars" /><published>2018-11-24T14:54:02-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-24T14:54:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jokicRisingStar</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jokicRisingStar">&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In baseball, a &quot;perfect game&quot; is achieved when a pitcher does not allow an opposing player to reach base - 27 up, 27 down. While basketball does not have an easily recognizable equivalent, NBA fans were treated to a perfect game this season on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.espn.com/nba/game?gameId=401070716&quot;&gt;Oct. 20&lt;/a&gt;. In an easily overlooked rout of the Phoenix Suns, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203999/&quot;&gt;Nikola Jokic&lt;/a&gt; recorded a 31-point triple-double with no turnovers while shooting perfect from the field (11-11), joining &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/76375/career/&quot;&gt;Wilt Chamberlain&lt;/a&gt; as one of the only two players to ever achieve such a feat, according to a tweet from @ESPNStatsInfo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jokic and the Denver Nuggets surpassed expectations from the onset, boasting a 9-1 record and the second seed in the Western Conference in early November. Since then, the Nuggets have lost six of their last nine games due to poor three-point shooting and inconsistent defense. Fortunately, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1627823/&quot;&gt;Juancho Hernangomez&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1628420/&quot;&gt;Monte Morris&lt;/a&gt; have emerged as key rotation players around the young core of &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1627750/&quot;&gt;Jamal Murray&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203914/&quot;&gt;Gary Harris&lt;/a&gt;, and Jokic (21, 24, and 23 years old, respectively).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite recent struggles, the Nuggets are still a solid playoff lock in the West and possess one of the best young cores looking forward for the next few years. The Nuggets had the &lt;a href=&quot;https://herosports.com/nba/oldest-youngest-teams-start-2018-19-season-byby&quot;&gt;youngest team in the league at the beginning of the 2018-2019 season&lt;/a&gt; with an average age of 24.72, per Hero Sports. Additionally, the Nuggets have the fourth best point differential in the league, are one of only three teams with a top-ten offensive and defensive efficiency (along with the Raptors and Bucks), and are led by Jokic, a soon to be all-star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jokic is a generational talent, emerging as the undisputed best passing center in the current NBA, and is making a legitimate case to be the best passing center in NBA history. His average assists per game have increased every season: 4.9 in 2016-17, 6.1 in 2017-18, and 7.3 to date this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/jokicRS/pic_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;*Cousins has not yet played in the 2018-2019 season&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/jokicRS/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jokic has also increased his assist percentage (the percentage of his teammates' field goals assisted on) from 29.6% last season to 36.6% this season, within a couple percentage points of point guards universally known for their passing abilities, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/1627732/&quot;&gt;Ben Simmons&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/101108/&quot;&gt;Chris Paul&lt;/a&gt;, per Basketball Reference. Jokic already has the second most games of any center with at least 10 assists, trailing only Wilt Chamberlain (a player being mentioned with Wilt this often is astounding).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a video of one of his mind-boggling passes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Gi9AKeGKWDc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many players will fake shot attempts and sling the ball to their teammates once the defense assumes the ball is going up, but nobody else actually completes their shooting motion, lofting the ball to their teammate. This move takes equal parts basketball intelligence, as well as guts, to attempt in an NBA game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Jokic is the lynchpin in the Nuggets offense, his defensive woes have been well documented. Jokic was dead last among centers (who played at least 65 games) during the 2017-2018 season when he was the closest defender to opponents shooting inside of 6 feet, per NBA.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/jokicRS/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;*Among NBA centers who played at least 65 games&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Jokic has displayed major improvements on defense this season, as opponents are only shooting 61.3% inside of 6 feet with Jokic as the closest defender, opposed to 66.8% last season. Jokic has an above average defensive efficiency rating compared to other centers this season and the Nuggets currently have the fifth best defensive efficiency rating in the league.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/YrBFFxzVNL8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one play, Jokic successfully closes out on &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/201572/&quot;&gt;Brook Lopez&lt;/a&gt;, traps Bledsoe after a pick-and-roll, recovers to &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/101141/&quot;&gt;Ilyasova&lt;/a&gt; after Hernangomez helps on Lopez, then steps in front of &lt;a href=&quot;https://stats.nba.com/player/203114/&quot;&gt;Khris Middleton&lt;/a&gt;, forcing an errant pass, and an eventual shot clock violation. Jokic is showing more active hands and quicker feet than in years past where he would lazily reach and the opposing team would be rewarded with an easy layup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another major knock on Nikola Jokic's game is that he will sometimes pass too much instead of shooting the ball. He is incredibly efficient from the field, having shot 49.9% from the field, 39.6% on threes, and 85% on free throws last season. According to ESPN, Jokic is the 12th most efficient player in the league this season by PER (a measure of a player's efficiency), but only has the 45th highest usage rate and attempted the 69th most shots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/jokicRS/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;*FGA and TPA are per-game statistics&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 13 most efficient players in the league this season, Jokic has the third lowest usage rate (the estimated number of a team's possessions used by a player) and takes the third least shot attempts (the two players below him, Harrell and Sabonis, are not the fulcrums of their offenses and take 100% and 96.4% of their shots from inside the three-point line, respectively). Jokic has taken less than 10 shots in a game on six different occasions this year, including a game in which he took only one shot and the Nuggets lost. Jokic takes pride in getting his teammates easier baskets and he is good enough to make an impact on the game without scoring. But if the Nuggets want to make the playoffs (and win a playoff series), Jokic must shoot more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 1, the Nuggets gave their young superstar a five-year, $147 million contract. Jokic responded by improving his defense and continuing to make the case to become the greatest passing center in NBA history. Jokic does not need to be &quot;perfect&quot; in every game, but shooting more will only benefit Jokic and his teammates on offense. Barring injury, Nikola Jokic will be playing in his first All-Star game this season in Charlotte, N.C., and will lead the Denver Nuggets to the playoffs for the first time since 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Chad Shimozaki</name></author><summary type="html">In baseball, a &quot;perfect game&quot; is achieved when a pitcher does not allow an opposing player to reach base -27 up, 27 down. While basketball does not have an easily recognizable equivalent, NBA fans were treated to a perfect game this season on Oct. 20. In an easily overlooked rout of the Phoenix Suns, Nikola Jokic recorded a 31-point triple-double with no turnovers while shooting a perfect from the field (11-11), joining Wilt Chamberlain as one of the only two players to ever achieve such a feat, according to a tweet from @ESPNStatsInfo.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Raw Powerlifting is Coming at Full Force</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/powerlifting" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Raw Powerlifting is Coming at Full Force" /><published>2018-11-20T16:42:06-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-20T16:42:06-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/powerlifting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/powerlifting">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/plift/cover.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;9for9 Media&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Introduction to the sport&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On first glance, powerlifting appears to be a sport destined for greatness, featuring incredible feats of strength through the squat, bench, and deadlift, some of the most ubiquitous exercises in the gym. In addition to that, the basic rules of the sport are mind-numbingly simple to understand - the best of three attempts at each lift are added together to form a total, which is then compared among competitors in the same weight class. In the right moments, the battle to become the strongest lifter can play out in dramatic conditions, such as John Haack's 315kg (694lb) pull at 83kg (183lb) to secure the IPF World Classic Powerlifting Championships title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/p3vR-OFazyU?start=226&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, powerlifting has largely flown under the radar, only garnering appeal from fellow competitors and precious few others. While the sport has been a mainstay of both the Special Olympics and the Summer Paralympics (bench-only) since 1991 and 1984 respectively, the International Olympic Committee (IOC) has yet to recognize a single governing body for powerlifting. In contrast, powerlifting's more acrobatic sibling Olympic weightlifting has origins in the inaugural 1896 Games, becoming a regular of mainstream sports consciousness and featuring a much more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2X0iGnQgvXo&quot;&gt;raucous&lt;/a&gt; global fanbase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why has this been the case? One plausible reason could stem from the problem of standardization. Powerlifting is heavily divided into scores of different international federations, which all contain different technical nuances and standards in their rules. To complicate matters even further, different federations also exist at the national level, most of them affiliated with an international body. Indeed, on last count no fewer than 14 different international federations and 34 in the United States alone were listed on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openpowerlifting.org/&quot;&gt;openpowerlifting.org&lt;/a&gt;. We can thus understand the IOC's reluctance to recognize one particular governing body for powerlifting when so many of them exist out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lift Proportions in Powerlifting by Equipment Categories&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the complicated state of federations in powerlifting, we will work only with results from USA Powerlifting (USAPL) meets and the USA affiliate of the International Powerlifting Federation (IPF). There are a few compelling reasons for this choice. Firstly, the IPF is the only international federation that continues to drug-test their athletes under World Anti-Doping Agency (WADA) regulations. Becoming WADA-compliant places the IPF in pole position in becoming recognized by the IOC in the future, a concrete path for powerlifting to attain mainstream popularity. Additionally, the USAPL in particular has a strong reputation for strictly enforcing refereeing regulations, which ensures that the meet results were consistent. Finally and certainly most significantly, the USAPL is also the federation that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/uclapowerlifting/&quot;&gt;UCLA Powerlifting&lt;/a&gt; competes in (no bias was formed in the construction of this sentence).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/plift/pic_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;(Author of this article with mediocre lifts pictured back row, third from left) (credit: UCLA Powerlifting)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;USAPL meets fall into two equipment categories, Raw and Equipped. In raw lifting, the only equipment allowed are knee sleeves, wrist wraps and a lifting belt. However, in equipped lifting the use of assistive equipment such as squat, bench or deadlift suits and knee wraps are permitted in competition. To obtain a quantitative measure of the resultant differences between the two categories at the highest level, data only from the past 10 years of the annual National competitions was used. I filtered the winners of the Junior (19-23) and Open (24+) divisions, generally considered to be the most competitive populations, obtaining the mean proportion of the total split by each lift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/plift/pic_2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;Lifts&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The results may not seem significant initially, with only a maximum difference of 4.5% separating the average raw and equipped deadlift. However, we must also remember that these are measures of individual lifts as a proportion of a total. When directly comparing the different categories to each other, we observe that from raw to equipped, our squat proportion increases by 6.96% and bench proportion by 8.77%, both non-negligible amounts. Interestingly, we see a dramatic drop in the prominence of the deadlift in equipped lifting, with the proportion of its total falling by 10.9% when compared to the raw deadlift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discrepancy can be explained by the mechanics of the supportive gear used in the Equipped category. These assist a lift by storing elastic energy during the descent, allowing lifters to utilize this force on the ascent to overcome weights far beyond their 'natural' capabilities. The perfect example of this can perhaps be found in Chen Wei-Ling's unbelievable 210kg (463lb) squat, more than 4 times her bodyweight. After struggling to walk out with the weight on her back, Chen's descent is noticeably slow and controlled as she fights against the elastic resistance of both her squat suit and knee wraps. Once she begins to stand up with the weight, the stored energy gives her the 'pop' out of the bottom position to complete the lift successfully. While a similar concept also applies to the bench, the deadlift exercise is unique. Unlike the squat and the bench where the weight is lowered then raised, the weight begins stationary on the floor before the deadlift begins. As a result, the elastic energy stored on the descent by a deadlift suit only really occurs as the lifter reaches down to the barbell, a meagre amount when juxtaposed against the enormous boost that squat and bench suits provide.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HVk7bpHYBdY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great way to illustrate this even further is to scrutinize lifters who compete in both categories. Elite powerlifter Blaine Sumner competed at Raw Nationals in 2014, hitting (more than) respectable numbers of 400/240/335 kg (882/529/738 lbs) for the squat, bench and deadlift respectively. Just two years later, he competed at Equipped Nationals instead, posting up an astronomical total of 445/375/355 kg (981/826/782 lbs). While Sumner's squat and bench went up by 11.25% and 56.25%, his deadlift only saw a slight improvement of 5.97%. This may seem like an extreme case, but top equipped lifters like Sumner see even more drastic improvements on their squat and bench than on their deadlift when switching over from raw lifting precisely because they recognize the technical proficiency required in mastering how best to use their equipment to extract the maximum poundage possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NfLxhHIyHw8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/M67nuMWUNqA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lift Proportions in Powerlifting by Level of Expertise&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I have a confession to make. My initial plan was to examine how the proportions of the three lifts change when contrasting the general population of powerlifting competitors with those at the elite level. To my surprise, the lift proportions of the Open and Junior division winners at national competitions differed only slightly from the pool of all USAPL lifters. This is especially the case for raw powerlifting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/plift/pic_3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;Lifts&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before analyzing the data, I hypothesized that raw lifters with proportionally bigger deadlifts would end up prevailing in powerlifting competitions more often. Since the deadlift is the final event in a powerlifting meet, serious competitors are aware of the exact amount of weight they need to prevail over the tight competition. It would seem to follow that those with strong deadlifts would have the opportunity to hit these numbers much more often. In contrast, a lifter with a strong squat or bench might not have as good a sense of how much more weight they need to lift over their competition to maintain their advantage going into the final deadlifts. Obviously, this theory was quickly debunked. Rather, it seems like world class lifters come in all shapes and forms, regardless of individual greatness or lack thereof in any single lift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hmyflzmPFGs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having a relatively subpar bench that placed him 30th out of 32 competitors, Matt Sohmer's massive squat and deadlift were enough to secure him the victory in the 120kg weight class during the 2018 Raw Nationals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/y_rDcuWpKrI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Thompson, who won 9 consecutive Raw National titles in her weight class from 2009 - 2017, is well-known in the powerlifting community for benching about 6.4 standard deviations over the mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our equipped data tells a similar story, but differences in the squat, bench and deadlift proportions are slightly more pronounced, where accomplished equipped lifters have a higher squat and bench proportion of their total. These findings are not surprising. As alluded to earlier, the addition of assistive equipment as a new variable creates a new technical challenge for lifters, creating an environment where top lifters do have to not only have the raw strength to complete a lift, but also make full use of their equipment to reap the most reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it is still apparent that no matter the equipment category, differences in proportion-of-total between the general population and the best lifters in the USAPL are not significant enough to establish a case for any single lift's importance over the others. This has promising implications for the average lifter. Rather than wasting needless time and effort worrying whether any particular weak lift is holding your powerlifting total back, our findings suggest that training hard and letting your lifts develop and grow over time naturally as you gain strength will serve you well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HjSdkJcZK5Q&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite only placing 3rd for squat and bench and 4th for deadlift, Bryce Lewis' consistency was enough to secure him the victory in the IPF Raw Worlds 105kg weight class. Being a well-balanced lifter isn't all that bad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Powerlifting's Growth&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that said and done, why bother to devote so much time in analyzing a fringe sport like powerlifting? Let's take a look at powerlifting's popularity from 1997 till today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/plift/pic_4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The exponential rise of the number of participants in USAPL meets appears to have its origins from 2013 and accelerated from 2014 to 2018 (updated to 21st October, 2018), color-coded in blue in the graph. While certainly not currently at the forefront of sporting prominence, the USAPL has displayed an impressive track record in growing interest in powerlifting. However, this overall picture can be deceiving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/plift/pic_5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/plift/pic_6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two graphs above showcase a stunning disparity in the fortunes of raw and equipped powerlifting respectively. Indeed, it is raw powerlifting that was enjoyed an explosion of growth, making up the bulk of the complete population and thus really the driving factor towards the upward of USAPL competitors. On the other hand, while equipped lifting was much more prevalent in the beginning years of the federation, its numbers were eventually superseded by raw powerlifting. Additionally, the number of powerlifters each year in this category have actually dropped every year since 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than immediately form a conjecture to explain the current state of equipped lifting, we first look to explain the rise of raw powerlifting. Simply put, raw powerlifting has one of the lowest barriers for entry in sports both cost and convenience-wise - besides a lifting singlet, everything else is optional. Because of this, most view raw lifting as a 'true' test of real strength by the human body alone, thus gravitating towards it. This has been facilitated by the growing prominence of the fitness industry in general, where popular mainstream YouTube stars often collaborate with raw powerlifters to provide advice that people looking to train for general strength to learn from. Some of these figures themselves choose to dabble in raw powerlifting because of its ease of access.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_rqe3IItJ04&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popular fitness YouTuber Omar Isuf collaborates with the owner of Barbell Brigade, a popular strength gym in Los Angeles. In this video, Omar extolled the virtues of powerlifting for a better body, a topic that attracts mass appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to raw lifting, the appeals of equipped lifting lie in pushing one's body beyond their limits and moving weights that others can only dream of (watch that Chen Wei-Ling squat video again). The importance of technical mastery over equipment could perhaps thus have alienated people interested in getting into powerlifting for the sole purpose of getting stronger, who view the category as an unnecessary complication. From an anecdotal perspective, many people that I know have expressed similar doubts over the effectiveness of equipped powerlifting in demonstrating true strength. At the end of the day, it is still worrying to see the stagnant state of equipped powerlifting. While it may certainly be true that this aspect of the sport doesn't emphasize pure strength as much, I have personally drawn inspiration watching the mental fortitude of these lifters. Take Dmytro Semenenko for example. After enduring catastrophic equipment failure at the bottom of his second squat, he added an additional 5kg onto the bar and promptly smashes the lift for a world record. Moments like these add to the excitement of powerlifting and the potential downfall of equipped lifting would thus be a huge loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/I5zUmdXXD8Y?start=38&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So much attention has been devoted to the growth of participants in powerlifting because of how critical this is for the sport. As a case study, let us examine the best squats of the 83kg Men's weight class from past Raw Nationals. This data was further filtered to include only the top 20 lifters of the Open and Junior categories to ensure that the highest levels of competition are selected to be represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/plift/pic_7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Over the last 7 years, we can clearly see that both the median and highest squat weight have increased consistently, with the exception of the median squat weight 2017-2018 (while not discernible from the graph, even the highest squat weight has improved from 300kg in 2016 to 300.5kg in 2017, and to 301kg in 2018). It is highly plausible that the accelerated baseline interest in raw powerlifting played a role in driving top-end competitiveness forwards steadily over time, something worth taking note of as powerlifting becomes even more popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even within powerlifting itself, we can see nuances between the raw and equipped categories. The former focuses on raw strength (as the name implies), and the latter requires an additional degree of technical skill to truly perform as well as possible. Consequently, raw lifters tend to have their deadlift represented strongly as a proportion as their total, while equipped lifters see greater gains in their squat and bench, lifts that see the largest enhancements from assistive gear. However, it also seems as if the proportions of each individual lift towards the total isn't as relevant to the average powerlifting enthusiast, who could benefit more towards simply training to the best of their ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The differences between raw and equipped has also resulted in far different rates of growth, which we can attribute to increased perceptions of powerlifting as a pure strength sport, a mindset that raw powerlifting serves far better than equipped powerlifting. Together with raw's far greater accessibility for general strength trainees, it is no wonder that the popularity of raw powerlifting has surged at a staggering rate while equipped powerlifting has stagnated. Overall, the growth of powerlifting is critical because this helps to push the ceiling of the sport even further, allowing us to see even crazier weights lifted that not only generate massive entertainment, but also fulfilment in pushing the strength limits of the human body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Powerlifting is a relatively new sport. Therefore, I believe that there is abundant potential for further data analysis in the future, whether that be generating an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strongerbyscience.com/whos-the-most-impressive-powerlifter/&quot;&gt;accurate method to compare relative strength levels between weight classes&lt;/a&gt; or means to use data to compare the training methods themselves even. These possibilities become even more relevant when considering the fact that in 2017, the IPF was able to receive official &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.powerlifting.sport/federation/presidents-corner/presidents-corner-detail.html?tx_news_pi1%5Bnews%5D=207&amp;tx_news_pi1%5Bcontroller%5D=News&amp;tx_news_pi1%5Baction%5D=detail&amp;cHash=de329d8a86a39c27610df738e303f536&quot;&gt;FISU recognition&lt;/a&gt; (International University Sports Federation), an organization recognized by the IOC. Steps like these brings about renewed hopes of future IOC recognition and possible future acceptance of powerlifting as a mainstream strength sport in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article uses data from the OpenPowerlifting project, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openpowerlifting.org&quot;&gt;https://www.openpowerlifting.org&lt;/a&gt;. A copy of the data can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/openpowerlifting/opl-data&quot;&gt;https://gitlab.com/openpowerlifting/opl-data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Qi Jing Yap</name></author><summary type="html">On first glance, powerlifting appears to be a sport destined for greatness, featuring incredible feats of strength through the squat, bench, and deadlift, some of the most ubiquitous exercises in the gym. In addition to that, the basic rules of the sport are mind-numbingly simple to understand - the best of three attempts at each lift are added together to form a total, which is then compared among competitors in the same weight class. In the right moments, the battle to become the strongest lifter can play out in dramatic conditions, such as John Haack's 315kg (694lb) pull at 83kg (183lb) to secure the IPF World Classic Powerlifting Championships title.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How ‘Mexican Style’ Came Back to Haunt GGG</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mexicanStyle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How 'Mexican Style' Came Back to Haunt GGG" /><published>2018-10-26T20:25:27-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-26T20:25:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mexicanStyle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mexicanStyle">&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image11.png&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of a boxer comes down to not only how he can fight, but also how he can spread his brand. The man from Kazakhstan known around the world today as 'GGG' did not have traction in the popularity department for a massive portion of his fighting career. After an incredible amatuer career of 350 fights, Gennady Golovkin's professional career stalled for years due to promotional issues. In 2012, already 30 years of age, Golovkin finally decided to take his career to the United States under a new promoter. At the time, his record was 23-0 with 20 knockouts and he was already the WBA Middleweight Champion. Because of his dangerous record and lack of popularity, the top fighters in the division heavily avoided him for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many lower-tier middleweights were put in front of Golovkin and he dismantled one after the other, gaining favor with American fight fans as the &quot;people's champion&quot;. Of great importance is the fact that he began to have a massive following among Mexican fans as well, as his &quot;seek and destroy&quot; style and increasing knockout streak was reminiscent of the Mexican legend Julio Caesar Chavez. In other words, Golovkin finally had a promotional cornerstone. His promoter Tom Loeffler and trainer Abel Sanchez promoted the 'GGG' brand as 'Mexican Style' and promised action in every fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image1.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 1&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2015, Golovkin went from being a foreign delight to becoming the IBF, IBO, WBA, WBC, and Ring Magazine Unified Middleweight Champion of the World with one of the largest fan bases in North America. Phrases like 'Triple G', 'Mexican Style', and 'Big Drama Show' have become forever tied to his legacy. He lived as boxing's longest reigning champion of his time until September of this year, when he lost via decision to Mexican superstar Saul 'Canelo' Alvarez. It was the rematch of a fight that took place a year prior and ended in a draw. Both results are deemed controversial because 77% of ringside media scored the first fight for Golovkin and 98% of ringside media scored the second fight as either a draw or win for Golovkin. So how did he end up walking away with a draw and a loss on his record (now 38-1-1, 34 KO) instead? Perhaps it was simply corruption since Alvarez is the biggest money maker in prize fighting and has a history of judges being biased towards him in big fights. But more plausible is the idea that the very 'Mexican Style' brand that brought Golovkin to stardom was not accurate. His style is simply not that of a belligerent Mexican fighter and the numbers are here to prove it. This truth was made clear when he came out and fought a very cautious, non-'Mexican Style' fight against the highly talented Alvarez. Although Golovkin may have won both fights in the eyes of the fans, this uncharacteristic change of gameplan was likely and unfortunately seen as discomfort and failure in the eyes of the judges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Mexicans are not from Kazakhstan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to first have an idea of what Mexican style boxing really is. Technically, Mexican style fighting involves close proximity between fighters and emphasizes power punches, especially body work, over jabbing and distance. As much as Golovkin has been branded as a Mexican style fighter, his fighting simply does not line up with this definition. In fact, he controls distance and utilizes his jab more than any fighter in the entire sport:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 3&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golovkin lands more jabs than any man in boxing with 10.3 per round and does so at a higher percentage than any man boxing with a 31.6% connect rate. He has mastered the art of distance, using his ramrod jab to set up his offense. This is not something that is encompassed by the Mexican style as distance is relatively ignored and fighters prefer to exchange in the pocket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's also the less technical but more electric quality about Mexican style fighting: fighters are willing to take punishment to give it back. It involves a certain lack of respect for opponents' power that makes every event a fight rather than a boxing match. But the hardest puncher that Golovkin has faced, Canada's David Lemieux, ended up being the man against whom he took the least risks and fought the most carefully behind his jab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image9.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 9&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golovkin obliterated rational jabbing statistics across the board in his fight against Lemieux. He landed an unreal 21.3 jabs per round, four times the middleweight average at the time, with 47% connection. A staggering 65% of the punches he threw were jabs. So what does all of this jabbing mean? It means that while Golovkin is known for having a tremendous chin, he had absolutely no interest in a &quot;take two give one&quot; war against a big puncher when his ring generalship and length could dominate the fight. Nothing is being taken away from Golovkin's win; he brilliantly out-boxed Lemieux and his performance was a masterpiece. But brilliantly out-boxing someone is not nearly the Mexican solution to that problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image5.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 5&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that Golovkin still landed 58.8% of his power punches in the Lemieux fight when the middleweight average was 37.7%. Throughout this time he was also thought of as perhaps the biggest puncher in the division. His high power output and connection in virtually all of his fights is what continued to string him along as a Mexican Style destroyer, a false image that would create unnecessary expectations for him in his two historic fights against Canelo Alvarez.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image13.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 13&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Wars in the Desert&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canelo-Golovkin fights both took place in Las Vegas and generated tremendous interest as boxing's Super Bowl. Both delivered on their promises, but Golovkin was coming into each with an additional onus. Alvarez is a natural counter puncher so it was widely expected that Golovkin, the &quot;true Mexican style fighter&quot; of the two, would be the one to take the fight to Alvarez and press forward. But when push came to shove in the ring, he realized how dangerous Alvarez was and did what his instincts told him. Much to the surprise of experts and fans, 'Mexican Style' officially went out the window. Golovkin has a 2 inch reach and height advantage over Alvarez and, as it has been throughout this article, Golovkin's jab was a key ingredient to both fights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image6.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 6&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alvarez is known for being a counter puncher with tremendous power. A Mexican Style fighter may normally walk such a man down and be willing to eat leather along the way as long as he can get inside and dish punishment back. But the most prolific jabber in boxing once again stuck to his true roots to win rounds in both fights. He did not need to get hit unnecessarily when he could wear Alvarez down with his jabbing and footwork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image2.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 2&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Golovkin jabbed, jabbed, and jabbed to set up his power punches, seemingly racking up points as the mere volume of his attack was tremendous. He didn't just out-jab Alvarez, he more than doubled Alvarez's landed jabs across both fights. And such a mismatch in the jab department was not Golovkin's only notable success. In both fights, he out-landed Canelo in total punches for the majority of rounds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image4.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 4&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a casual boxing fan were told that in two fights, one man would double the other's landed jabs and out-land the other outright in 18 of the 24 combined rounds, the casual fan would probably guess that this man handily won both fights. Yet only one of the six combined official judges had Gennady Golovkin winning. This is where the 'Mexican Style' image that Golovkin has built around himself over the years comes into play. Everyone, including the judges, was expecting Golovkin to make each fight a close distance firefight because that's the way he has been marketed. As great as Golovkin's jab and overall output were, he failed in the 'Mexican Style' department. As mentioned earlier, Mexican style fighting comes down to two technical aspects: power punches and body work. Golovkin was not able to beat Alvarez at either of those two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image7.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 7&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Golovkin totally neglected attacking the body in both fights; only 6.2% of his landed power punches were downstairs. Alvarez, meanwhile, threw to the body much more vigorously, with 35% of his landed power shots going there. More notably, Golovkin, the man who was supposed to bring the power-punching fire, was actually out-landed by Alvarez in terms of power punches and was less efficient with his power punches as well, landing 33.5% of his shots while Alvarez landed 40.2%. Essentially, Alvarez, the Mexican man in the fight, also ended up having the more Mexican statistics across both fights and undermining Golovkin's signature 'Mexican Style'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image8.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 8&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to have had a direct effect on the official score cards, as there is a glaring trend about the way that each of the 24 combined rounds was scored (by the majority of the 3 judges in each round):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image12.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 12&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, judges were scoring rounds for the man who had the higher power punch percentage regardless of the volume of punches, jab, or ring generalship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appeared to most ringside observers and fans that Golovkin had done enough to win both fights because despite getting outlanded in power shots and never hitting the body, he often controlled the tempo and did so with incredible punch output. But the thing that seems to have mattered to the official judges more than anything else is: &quot;Who is fighting more like a Mexican?&quot;, a question that only entered their heads in the first place because of how much 'Mexican Style' had become entangled with the story of the fight over the years. In their eyes, here is what happened: A man who has built his career around being a Mexican style fighter that comes forward and attacks relentlessly was unable to do so because Canelo Alvarez was dictating the fights and making him afraid and uncomfortable in the ring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/mexicanS/image10.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture 10&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 95%;&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's sound logic if Golovkin was ever actually a Mexican style fighter, but he's not and the numbers have made it quite clear. The fact is that Golovkin is a high quality attacker who had an extensive amateur career for years with an Eastern European style based on distance and calculation. He came to the United States hoping to make the most of his incredible boxing ability and after a string of knockouts against lower-tier opponents, fans across the continent fell in love with the idea of 'GGG': the true Mexican style monster who traps opponents on the ropes and finishes them. But he was just a fighter who had never yet had truly elite-level opposition. When the elite opponent was finally put in front of him, the undefeated champ dug deep into his bag of tricks and amateur pedigree to outbox the man, but it unfortunately didn't come across that way to the judges; they had expectations for him that stemmed from false advertising and were never realistic. He is the greatest middleweight of this era, but like many people who go to Vegas, Gennady Golovkin walked in with high expectations and ended up leaving empty handed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sources: CompuBox numbers via HBO Boxing and Sports Illustrated, mmafighting.com, sportsviewlondon.com&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kathir Ilango</name></author><summary type="html">The success of a boxer comes down to not only how he can fight, but also how he can spread his brand. The man from Kazakhstan known around the world today as 'GGG' did not have traction in the popularity department for a massive portion of his fighting career. After an incredible amatuer career of 350 fights, Gennady Golovkin's professional career stalled for years due to promotional issues. In 2012, already 30 years of age, Golovkin finally decided to take his career to the United States under a new promoter. At the time, his record was 23-0 with 20 knockouts and he was already the WBA Middleweight Champion. Because of his dangerous record and lack of popularity, the top fighters in the division heavily avoided him for years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vegas Golden Knights: The Most Successful Expansion Team in NHL History</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vegasGK" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vegas Golden Knights: The Most Successful Expansion Team in NHL History" /><published>2018-06-08T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-08T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vegasGK</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vegasGK">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Associated Press&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t supposed to happen. The first major professional sports team to ever grace the city of Las Vegas wasn’t supposed to be this good. Hockey wasn’t meant to be played in the desert. A team full of disposable parts and cast-offs wasn’t supposed to mesh this well together. It must be a fluke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vegas Golden Knights have been bombarded with these narratives all season, brushing them aside with every milestone attained, every record broken. They are for real. If finishing with 109 points atop the Pacific division and fifth in the league didn’t convince you, their playoff run sure did. Stanley Cup Finalists. Western Conference Champions. Not a bad inaugural season for the NHL’s newest franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one saw this coming in the offseason of last year. Preseason odds given to Vegas to win the Stanley Cup ranged from 300-1 to 500-1. Almost every expert, media personality, and journalist had the team as a cellar dweller who would be vying for a favorable position in the draft lottery come April; not cruising to home-ice advantage in the playoffs. Ironically, the city of Las Vegas was facing one of its biggest potential losses in betting history as the Knights were on the brink of a Cup win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To all the fans who stuck with them from the beginning, through all the adversity… yeah, no. The unprecedented success of the Golden Knights has brought to the forefront a recurring theme: Sports aren’t always fair. Kevin Durant joining the Golden State Warriors. The college football playoff selection process when it comes to non-power-5 teams (read: UCF). The list goes on. Do you think fans of the St. Louis Blues, who have never won a Cup and haven’t made it to the Finals in 48 years, have a soft spot for Vegas? Or fans of the Florida Panthers, who have gone 21 years without winning a single playoff series?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how one of the greatest sports stories of this millennium unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to look at is roster composition. Although teams were not able to protect as many players as in previous expansion drafts, general manager George McPhee didn’t exactly have a cupboard full of exciting star talent to choose from. Each team was allowed to protect seven forwards, three defensemen, and one goaltender, or eight skaters regardless of position and one goaltender. There were some minor rules such as the requirement to expose at least two forwards and one defenseman who played 40 or more games in the previous season, but nothing that would make an organization have to give up a perennial superstar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mock drafts had the team chalk full of fringe top-6 forwards, borderline top-4 defensemen and a slew of young but unproven wildcards. And that is how the actual draft appeared to go down last summer. Pundits lamented the mediocre, uninspiring collection of players. Sure, the future looked bright with some exciting prospects and draft picks to develop in coming years. But there was no indication that this team would be competing for a Stanley Cup in their first season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enter an offense that would see the emergence of new, elite talent, a goaltender with a history of success playing the best hockey of his career, and a coach whose system is very much compatible with the ‘speed and skill’ style of the modern NHL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Karlsson turned into an elite goal scorer seemingly overnight. He failed to top 10 goals in each of his first three seasons in the NHL with Anaheim and Columbus. Moves to Vegas and pots 43, third in the league behind only Alex Ovechkin, one of the best scorers of all time, and young phenom Patrik Laine. Even worse for Columbus, they traded Vegas two high draft picks to select Karlsson (and take on a bad contract to provide salary cap relief).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many on the Vegas roster who had breakout seasons took advantage of increased responsibility, leading to more ice time, powerplay time, etc. Karlsson played nearly 19 minutes per game, on the first powerplay unit, compared to 13-14 minutes and almost no PP time with Columbus. This is a recipe for increased production, regardless of the player. A 23.4 shooting percentage is unsustainable, so some type of regression is expected next year. But scoring 40+ goals in a season doesn’t happen by accident. Karlsson is one of the top young players in the game today and a building block for Vegas going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Marchessault was similarly involved in a trade that would help Florida clear out a bad contract. In hindsight, that did not turn out so well for the Panthers. Every dollar counts in the salary cap era, and it’s clear that teams have made it a top priority to manage their money. Vegas took advantage of this because they have plenty of cap space; no superstars means no reason to sign anyone to albatross contracts. Karlsson is a restricted free agent and is due to get paid this offseason, but they locked up Marchessault to a six year, $5 million per deal that is looking like it could be an absolute steal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Vegas was competitive right off the bat. By midseason mark, they created a sizable gap from first to second in the Pacific and never relinquished it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Golden Knights boasted a record of 29-10-2 at T-Mobile Arena on the Las Vegas strip. Only Winnipeg and Pittsburgh had more wins at home. The theory of ‘Vegas Flu’ has been tossed around, where visiting teams would succumb to the atmosphere/distractions of the city on nights before playing the Knights. But nearly every game has been sold out and their 103.9% average capacity is fourth in the league. Ticket prices are not cheap either. Extravagant pregame shows, boisterous locals, and the support of a city riding a wave of anomalous success has created significant home ice advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advanced hockey analytics paint a favorable picture of the Knights as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scope of quality hockey statistics is not nearly at the level of basketball, and nowhere close to baseball. The sport is more fluid than either of those two, and parallels soccer in its low scoring nature. How do you judge a team’s overall strength? Goals scored and against is the obvious answer, but there are only a few hundred of those per team, per season. Largely influenced by random fluctuations and ‘puck luck’, the sample size over a single year is not enough to draw definitive conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of looking at goals, shots (on goal, blocked, missed net) have been used as a proxy for puck possession. Generally, if a team has more shot attempts for than against, they probably have the puck more. The graph above uses scoring chances, which are shot attempts from dangerous scoring locations. 5v5 indicates these are even strength scoring chances. Further adjustments such as taking into account the score of the game (a team with the lead tends to sit back and defend it, hence the trailing team will get a skewed percentage of chances) can also be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlighted regions of the graphic above are top-5 and bottom-5 indicators. While Vegas does not lie in any of the blue, they are in the fourth quadrant (‘Good’), generating more scoring chances per 60 minutes and allowing less than league average. It’s important to not put too much stock into any one statistic. Calgary and Carolina look like superb teams here, but neither made the postseason (due to a combination of mediocre goaltending and scoring ineptitude).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A record of 20-6-3 against Pacific division rivals foreshadowed good things to come in the playoffs. The overwhelming factor in Vegas’ run to the Stanley Cup Final was the play of their goaltender, Marc-Andre Fleury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/vegas/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;golden knights&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleury has been the face of the franchise from the beginning. After losing his starting job to the younger Matt Murray in Pittsburgh, he was clearly the best available netminder up for selection. The first overall pick in the 2003 Entry Draft, ‘The Flower’ has enjoyed a decorated career. Three Stanley Cups, 404 wins (11th all time). He posted career highs in save percentage and goals against average in Vegas’ inaugural season. A concussion caused him to miss two months early in the year or he might’ve topped his previous high of 42 wins. Remarkably, the Golden Knights hardly missed a beat despite being down to their fourth string goalie at one point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first playoff series in franchise history would come against Los Angeles: A veteran team that has won two Cups in recent years, and usually turns it up a notch in the postseason. It was a goaltending duel from start to finish. Kings goalie Jonathan Quick, 2012 Conn Smythe winner, did everything he could to give his team a chance to win. Unfortunately for him, the Kings offense scored 3 goals in 4 games and were shutout twice by Fleury in a sweep for Vegas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up was San Jose. Okay, this was a real playoff team. Coming of a sweep of their own against Anaheim, the Sharks will put Vegas in their place. Nope. The Knights jumped out to a 4-0 lead just 12 minutes into the series, completely outclassing the Sharks 7-0 in Game 1. It would go six games, but on the back of Marc-Andre Fleury, Vegas proved too much for San Jose to overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Western Conference Final would pit them against the Jets. The Pacific Division was weak this year; this was the true Cup contender that would end the Knights Cinderella run. Negative. Vegas won four straight after dropping Game 1 in Winnipeg. Fleury did not allow more than two goals in games 2 through 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miraculously, an expansion team was heading to the Stanley Cup Finals. Only the Washington Capitals, a franchise with a long history of playoff disappointment, stood in their way. They were not favorites to come out of the East, and Vegas had defeated them in both matchups during the regular season. Surely the Knights were destined to achieve the unthinkable and make quick work of them…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny how sports work sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fleury fell back down to Earth. Heading into the SCF, he was on track to have the best playoff run by a goaltender in terms of save percentage since the 2005 lockout (at least 10GP). His numbers fell off a cliff against Washington, although he was hardly to blame for the series loss. Vegas’ defense was carved up by the Capitals attack, leaving Fleury out to dry. Caps goalie Braden Holtby stole the spotlight. Evgeny Kuznetsov had the most productive spring since Evgeni Malkin and Sidney Crosby of the ’08-09 Penguins. Alex Ovechkin, starved of postseason success throughout his career, played inspired hockey to lead Washington to its first Stanley Cup in franchise history. There are very few people in the entirety of the sports world who deserved a championship more than him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this incredible run by Vegas did not get its storybook ending, their inaugural season was an overwhelming success. They’ve accomplished more in one year than many teams have in decades. With a core of young studs, a franchise goaltender, and plenty of cap space, it will be an exciting summer and future for the Golden Knights.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Joey Maurer</name></author><summary type="html">The Associated PressThis wasn’t supposed to happen. The first major professional sports team to ever grace the city of Las Vegas wasn’t supposed to be this good. Hockey wasn’t meant to be played in the desert. A team full of disposable parts and cast-offs wasn’t supposed to mesh this well together. It must be a fluke.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">BSA Exclusive: Our Journey Through Research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/pred_NBA_salaries_journey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BSA Exclusive: Our Journey Through Research" /><published>2018-06-03T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-03T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/pred_NBA_salaries_journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/pred_NBA_salaries_journey">&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Goal of this Article&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this article, we hope to detail our process as members of Bruin Sports Analytics to work towards getting a well-done research paper completed, with guidance given by our club advisor, Professor Almohalwas of the UCLA Statistics department. We wish to detail our journey, and all the lessons we have taken from each one to move us closer to completing our desired task. In hopes of creating a paper worthy of being published in an official sports analytics journal, we have decided to take more time in working towards our final result. However, we have decided to write this extended article to provide a checkpoint of where currently stand in hopes for others to get inspired to do research as an undergrad, and learn more about the interesting attempts we have tried to solve our problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;Predicting NBA Free Agent Salaries&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Introduction&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Relevance&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Front offices and player agents alike would benefit from a model that can assess a free agent’s true value given the player’s performance in an array of statistical categories. In 2016, teams were clearly unsure how much free agents were actually worth due to the increased salary cap (it increased by over $24 million). As the salary cap continues to increase with the influx of more league revenue from television contracts, this problem will continue. Our research attempts to lay the groundwork for a tool to accurately gauge the true worth of a player’s on-court contributions in relation to the salary cap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Background&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More so than any of the other big four American sports, the NBA is a superstar-driven league. Every championship team this millennium aside from the 2004 Detroit Pistons and the 2011 Dallas Mavericks have featured at least two bona-fide superstars. This trend has been accentuated by the 2010-2014 Miami Heat featuring three superstars and the current Golden State Warriors featuring four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far the easiest way to acquire superstars is through signing a superstar through free agency, which requires no sacrifice of time or assets except money of course. The player and his new team need only agree to a maximum contract, without the team compensating his previous team. Thus, signing free agent superstars is, on paper, the easiest way to get a superstar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NBA CBA designates a salary cap and a maximum contract, which complicate the signing of multiple high-salary superstars while keeping a strong roster of complementary players. This leaves little to no room for overpaying players - every dollar counts. Thus, there is a need for a model that can analyze statistics to accurately predict any player’s appropriate salary for the next season, a tool which can help teams avoid overspending and help free agents know their clients’ worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Understanding Contracts and Free Agency&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First round draft picks enter the league on two-year guaranteed contracts dictated by the CBA and its “rookie scale”. The rookie scale outlines how first rounders’ pay is based on a range tied to the salary cap in their draft year. This means players on rookie contracts are paid based on draft position, NOT on-court performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rookie scale&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rookie scale makes players on rookie contracts irrelevant to our research, and thus we removed these players from our data. Players like Donovan Mitchell (13th pick) and Kyle Kuzma (27th pick) have greatly outperformed their draft positions’ salaries while other players (busts) would underperform. Either way, both types of players would damage our model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Methodology&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Organizing the Data&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We obtained player metrics (both basic box-score and advanced numbers) from basketball-reference.com for players from the 2013-2014 through 2016-17 season. These metrics included the player’s Per Game and Advanced statistics, as these statistics do an adequate job of detailing the skill of a particular player. Each player was matched with average salary data for the corresponding player for the next season via spotrac.com. Our reason for using the next season’s salary was so that the model would be trained to predict player salary in the following season based on their performance in the previous season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we had a dataframe of four seasons, we decided to optimize our data to focus our attention on players who were relevant over the course of an NBA season. Thus, we cleaned the data by removing duplicates and players who played less than 25 games in a season. These are generally players who are either injured or do not have much impact in games. In the case that a player was injured during the season, it would not make sense to predict their salary based on the performance from a season in which they were injured. Also, players that are generally unproductive when they are on the floor often bounce around teams on shorter contracts and thus have a greater variability in salaries over seasons. Cases like these could affect the model unfavorably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another step taken to clean the data for the model was to take out players on rookie contracts. As stated earlier, when a player is on a rookie contract, their salaries are set in stone for a certain amount of years. This means that predicting a player’s salary while on a rookie contract would be futile, since their salaries are set in stone for a fixed amount of years after they are drafted, and are not based on performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we had to re-examine the goal of this project, which was to create a statistically valid model that could predict NBA player salaries for next season, the 2018-19 season. To do this, we decided to train the model on predicting player salaries for the 2017-18 season based on player performance in the 2016-17 season. We found that using the larger dataset of data from the previous seasons (2013-16) posed some issues in our methodology, namely in that the “local model” with just one season’s worth of data was more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Interesting Notes&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the data had been prepared, one of the first statistics we looked at was whether there was a significant difference in terms of average salary by player position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;By Position&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To our surprise, after running a One-way ANOVA test comparing whether the average salary between groups was different, we concluded no significant difference between position thus did not add this factor into our multiple linear regression model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor we explored was if playing for a specific team impacted the type of salary a player is expected to get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;By Team&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After performing another another ANOVA test, there was a significant difference in terms of average salary by Team. However, after performing Post-hoc Tukey’s test to discover which pair was significant and adding that to our model, it also proved insignificant compared to our other variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;An Attempt to Create our Own Statistic&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the other aspects that we worked on was creating a new statistic that we could eventually use in our regression model. The goal was to create a metric that would quantify how much a player was overachieving or underachieving with respect to their contract. Our belief was that a player who was underpaid would eventually see a pay raise in their next contract and a player that was underperforming would more than likely have to take a pay cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in creating this new metric was to place the players into salary brackets according to how much they were being paid. We worked with the 2016-2017 player data and used their next year’s salary  (2017-2018 season) to place them into salary brackets. We chose to have eight different salary brackets, where bracket eight represented players who received a max level contract, which was over 21% of the salary cap. The lowest bracket belonged to players on a minimum contract and from there the brackets went up in increments of roughly 3-4% of the overall cap. The following chart displays the distribution of players in each of the eight salary brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Salary Bracket&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After assigning each of the players in the 2016-2017 season into a salary bracket, the next step was to group the players into clusters based on their performance. We used the K-Means clustering algorithm to create the groups. We chose to use a k-value of 8, because we wanted to be consistent with the number of salary brackets that we had previously created. After running the K-Means algorithm, each player was assigned into a performance cluster from one to eight. The eighth performance cluster represented the top performing players in the league and not surprisingly contained players like Lebron James, Stephen Curry, and Russell Westbrook. The chart below highlights the number of players in each of the respective performance clusters based on the 2016-2017 player data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Performance Cluster&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After assigning each player a performance cluster and a salary bracket, we had the information needed in order to create our new metric, which we called over/under. The formula for over/under was the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;over/under = performance cluster - salary bracket&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A positive over/under score meant that the player was outperforming their contract and was in line for a pay raise. Conversely, a negative over/under score represented a player that was underachieving and was most likely due for a decrease in pay in their next contract. The chart below shows a few players from our 2016-2017 dataset and their over/under score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/table1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Prediction Table&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown, Lebron James, who belongs to both the highest performance cluster and highest salary bracket, has an over/under score of 0 which means that he should see similar pay in his future contract. In the cases of the Isaiah Thomas, who was an MVP candidate, and Will Barton, a sixth man of the year candidate, both had some of the highest over/under scores, which makes sense because they both significantly outperformed with respect to their contract. Joakim Noah achieved a negative score because of his limited production even though he belonged to such a high salary bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, after adding the over/under statistic into our regression model, we received an R^2 value of 82%, which was one of the best models that we had produced. However, the issue was that the over/under statistic relied on know the next year’s player salary, which was not possible if you were working with the most current NBA season. One way that we will use to solve this issue is by scaling the years back when calculating a player’s salary bracket. This would mean that for example with the 2016-2017 player data we would use the 2016-2017 player salary and not the 2017-2018 player salary. We also tried to use just the performance cluster metric for each player in a model and see if that had any statistical significance, but unfortunately it did not. Going forward there are numerous aspects that we can tune such as changing the number of performance clusters/salary brackets and scaling the salary years back in order to create a new metric that may improve our eventual regression model. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Final Variable Selection &amp; Model Creation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we decided a multiple linear regression model would do the job in predicting average salary given a combination of various statistics, we had to require our model follow a large number of assumptions in order draw adequate conclusions. To begin with, we had to ensure that the player salaries were as close to normally distributed as possible. Average salary’s Gaussian Kernel Density estimation shape was greatly skewed but after applying the square root transformation, the assumption of normality was satisfied. Had this transformation not been applied, the standard errors would have been biased leading to faulty conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we took a look at how the variables correlated with each other to better understand relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Correlation Table&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When analyzing data as large as this, it is vital to view how the other statistics interact with average salary (the far right column). Next, for the variables which correlate greatly, you need to check how they correlate with each other. By checking for possible multicollinearity, we can avoid adding variables into our model which give the same information and just choose the one who provides us with the most information. For instance, the number of free throws made per game and free throw percentage tell nearly the same story in how a player performs at the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we decided to use a powerful function within R, regsubsets, for regression subset selection which basically finds the best combination of variables at various subset sizes in terms of a given criterion. We decided Adjusted R^2 was an adequate criteria to base our ability to explain average salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic7.png&quot; alt=&quot;regsubsets&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our task then became selecting the subset which provides the highest adjust R^2 and cutting the model down while taking VIF into account. The variance inflation factor of a variable gives us a sign of multicollinearity which we obviously want to avoid from our model. Finally, we worked our model down while keeping VIF of each variable under 5 to obtain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic8.png&quot; alt=&quot;regsubsets&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We noticed that Minutes played per game, Win Shares, Steals per game, True Shooting %, Games played in the season, and offensive rebound % proved the most significant variables in predicting average salary according to this model. When checking for validity of a model, diagnostics must be examined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/pic9.png&quot; alt=&quot;regsubsets&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four plots prove to us that our assumptions of normality and constant variance are all satisfied meaning that the conclusions we draw from the model can be taken seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model is nowhere near perfect yet, it has a low adjusted R^2, and some of the coefficients are negative when intuitively should be positive. We are still in progress to rework the regression model to raise our adjusted R^2 and explore different interactions between variables. However, we were able to satisfy all model assumption which at least gives a checkpoint to build off of as we begin to tune or rework this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Results&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based off this model for predicting 17-18 salaries, we decided to approximate what free agents for the 18-19 season should earn. Since the salary cap for the 18-19 season is so close to the 17-18 season, we decided to reuse this model to create approximate predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some top performers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/table2.png&quot; alt=&quot;top performers&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editor's Picks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/salJourney/table3.png&quot; alt=&quot;editor picks&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not too shabby, but there’s so much more to go with the project if we want to improve our accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Next Steps&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently working with the professor on obtaining a model using Principal Component Analysis, and also exploring unsupervised methods to help create predictions on data with no attached labels. We also will try to incorporate more statistics such as offensive and defensive rating to hopefully give us more insight into detailing what a player is worth. Additionally, we will working to create extra statistics, such as our performance cluster and another which takes into account previous years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope to one day predict full contracts with contract length attached, and possibly a web application for people to easily check a player’s worth in terms of what they deserve in salary against what they are currently earning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This piece was just an update of where we are at so far, and to hopefully lay out a foundation on which we or others can build upon. All of our data from 2011-2017 of player’s perGame, advStats, salaries, free agent lists, etc is all our our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/konnermacias/Free-Agents&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; for you to use. Working towards getting this project completed has been an extremely rewarding experience, allowing us to get closer with our club members and working with our club advisory. It is highly recommended if you ever want to work towards solving a difficult problem and doing something you’re passionate about.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Konner Macias</name></author><summary type="html">With this article, we hope to detail our process as members of Bruin Sports Analytics to work towards getting a well-done research paper completed, with guidance given by our club advisor, Professor Almohalwas of the UCLA Statistics department. We wish to detail our journey, and all the lessons we have taken from each one to move us closer to completing our desired task. In hopes of creating a paper worthy of being published in an official sports analytics journal, we have decided to take more time in working towards our final result. However, we have decided to write this extended article to provide a checkpoint of where currently stand in hopes for others to get inspired to do research as an undergrad, and learn more about the interesting attempts we have tried to solve our problem.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Early Overachievers: The 2018 Oakland Athletics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/oakAs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Early Overachievers: The 2018 Oakland Athletics" /><published>2018-05-30T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-30T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/oakAs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/oakAs">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/cover.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;A's Teammates&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Mercury News&lt;/i&gt;; from L to R, Matt Chapman, Matt Olson, and Marcus Semien&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the 2018 MLB season, many experts thought the Oakland Athletics would once again sport one of the worst records in baseball. According to Baseball Prospectus, the Athletics were projected to have a 76-86 record this year, which would be a miniscule improvement from their 75-87 record last year. The oddsmakers at Bovada had even lower expectations for the squad, as the over/under for their win total was set at 74.5. Given that the team has been in the American League West cellar for three years straight, even the most optimistic A’s fans had to acknowledge that a playoff appearance might not be in order for at least a couple of years. So, you can’t really blame all the people who slept on the A’s going into the season, especially since Oakland didn’t do much over the offseason to improve themselves. But, the A’s have given their fans some hope with their impressive start to the season; after the first 54 games of the campaign, Oakland stands at 28-26, good for a .519 win percentage. People around the game might be surprised at this kind of run, but when looking at the roster makeup and the major statistics on both sides of the ball, one can better understand why the A’s are experiencing this kind of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/pic1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stephen Piscotty&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;MLB.com; Stephen Piscotty&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/pic2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jonathon Lucroy&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;MLB: Jonathon Lucroy&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a team not in contention going into the 2018 year, the Oakland Athletics didn’t make any splashes with trades or free agency. As a result, much of the team from last year has been kept intact, as only a few moves were made here and there. First of all, the A’s traded away first baseman Ryon Healy to the Seattle Mariners in order to give emerging youngster Matt Olson more playing time. As a result, Olson has performed admirably as a starter, as the 6’5” power hitter has carried the momentum of his 24-home run effort last year into 2018. Then, the A’s traded for St. Louis Cardinals’ outfielder Stephen Piscotty to bolster their outfield depth, which was important given they were bringing up guys from Triple-A to fill those spots last year. Later on, they traded away struggling pitcher Jesse Hahn to the Kansas City Royals and received a dependable reliever in Ryan Buchter as a result. And in March, Oakland signed a quality catcher in Jonathan Lucroy, who was a hot item on the trade market not too long ago due to his 2014 and 2016 All-Star credentials. And just before the season, the A’s brought on Trevor Cahill and Brett Anderson, both former A’s, to solidify the starting rotation. Nothing flashy, but Oakland filled a couple of key needs heading into 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick look at the depth chart gives us an idea of the main contributors this year. First, the newly-acquired Lucroy has been the predominant starter at catcher for Oakland, and his presence behind the plate has arguably calmed the nerves of the young pitching staff. For the infield, Olson has been the guy at 1st base, Jed Lowrie has been excellent as the starting 2nd baseman, Marcus Semien has been stationed at shortstop, and Matt Chapman has played stellar defense at third base. In the outfield, it’s mainly been some combination of Matt Joyce, Dustin Fowler, Stephen Piscotty, and Chad Pinder. Joyce has played in left field for the most part, Fowler has been in center field, and Piscotty has been in right field. Pinder is a utility guy, so he has filled in for any of the three aforementioned players when they had an off day. In the designated hitter slot, Khris Davis has gotten his fair share of hacks as the team’s best power hitter, but a recent leg injury has sidelined him for the past few games. Thankfully, he should be back this week. Finally, the pitching rotation has been arguably the weakest link for Oakland recently, as an array of injuries has forced quite a bit of shuffling to occur. As it stands now, the five main starters are ace Sean Manaea, Daniel Mengden, Trevor Cahill, Daniel Gossett, and Frankie Montas. This is a relatively young rotation, as Cahill is the elder statesman at 30 years of age, while the others are all either 25 or 26 years old. They have held it together up to this point, but we’ll have to see if the A’s staff can maintain this level of consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Athletics struggled to win last year, they have bounced back in 2018 with a winning record so far. This success is largely due to the offensive efforts of the squad, as young guns and veterans alike have enjoyed their fair share of triumphs at the plate. As a team, the Athletics rank 6th in the American League (AL) with 66 home runs and have a slugging percentage of .412, good for 7th in the AL. Clearly, these metrics demonstrate the offensive power of the A’s. After all, five A’s players rank in the top 50 in the AL with at least 7 home runs on the year: outfielder Khris Davis (ranked 8th with 13), 2nd baseman Jed Lowrie (ranked 24th with 9), 3rd baseman Matt Chapman / 1st baseman Matt Olson (both tied for 32nd with 8), and utility player Mark Canha (ranked 43rd with 7). In particular, Lowrie has had quite the year so far; he possesses a .303 batting average, good for 14th in the AL, and he has 38 runs batted in (RBIs), tied with Davis for 5th in the AL. And in terms of hits, shortstop Marcus Semien and Lowrie are tied for 9th with 63 apiece. Clearly, Oakland has the firepower to hit with the best offensive teams in the league, and their ability to do so has been why they have a winning record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;RBI Leaders&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above is a chart detailing some of the RBI leaders in the American League thus far in the 2018 season. Manny Machado and J.D. Martinez are tied for the league lead with 44 apiece, but A’s teammates Khris Davis and Jed Lowrie aren’t too far behind them. With 38 RBIs each, Lowrie and Davis are tied for 5th in this category, which makes for a formidable pairing in the heart of the Oakland lineup. In fact, they have the 3rd-highest combined RBI total for two teammates in the league, trailing a couple of Red Sox pairs for that honor. Now, Lowrie and Davis aren’t exactly your household names when you think of Major League Baseball. No, you’d probably think of reigning AL MVP Jose Altuve, defending NL MVP Giancarlo Stanton, and Future Hall-of-Famer Albert Pujols. Well, Davis and Lowrie have clearly outproduced these big names in the RBI department so far, as the closest player to them, Altuve, comes up a full 9 RBIs short of the Athletics’ duo. Comparing small market players like Lowrie and Davis to the big guns emphasizes the fact that Oakland’s offense has been underrated this year, but if the A’s can continue to produce at this level, maybe they’ll get some attention from national networks like ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/oakland/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Assist Leaders&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving on, the Athletics’ defense has improved markedly from past seasons. The A’s have been one of the worst defensive teams in the AL for the past couple of years, as they have been notorious for committing tons of errors and not converting simple putouts. Part of that was the youth of the team, but many of these guys now have some major league experience, which has presumably given them confidence to field better. The numbers from this year suggest that they are an above-average defensive team. First of all, it’s quite impressive that Oakland ranks 1st in the AL in total assists with 580, a full 38 more than the Texas Rangers, the next-highest total. Even the league average, 493, is almost 100 assists less than what the A’s have tallied so far. Moreover, they rank 5th in the AL in putouts with 1499 and are 3rd in the league in defensive efficiency ratio at .705. This statistic is basically a measure of how likely a team’s defense is to convert a ball in play into an out. So, the A’s have been able to do this roughly 70% of the time. Plus, some individual performers have stood out on defense. For one, 3rd baseman Matt Chapman has been a consistent playmaker, as his 144 assists are good for 3rd place in the league among all fielders. Also, 1st baseman Matt Olson has a tremendous 530 putouts to lead the league in that category; not only is he making plays, but he has started every game for the A’s thus far. Additionally, he sports a relatively high fielding percentage of .995, as he has made only 3 errors on the year. Overall, these defensive strides have allowed the pitching staff to relax and get to the dugout even faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the Oakland pitchers, the A’s slingers have held their own in the home-run era of Major League Baseball. After all, they rank 5th in the AL with an impressive 3.94 Earned Run Average (ERA), a vast improvement from their 4.67 ERA from 2017. Their pitchers also do a good job of not giving away too many walks; Oakland has only issued 153 free passes, the 4th-lowest total in the AL. As for individual performances, the two headliners in the starting rotation have been youngsters Sean Manaea and Daniel Mengden. Manaea, the decided ace of the staff, has a no-hitter to his name against the dangerous Boston Red Sox from this past April. And amongst qualified AL starters, he ranks 15th with a 3.34 ERA and 12th in innings pitched with 70.0. Perhaps his most impressive stat is the low amount of walks and hits he gives up per inning (WHIP), as his 0.96 WHIP is 6th among AL starters. Similarly, Daniel Mengden’s early success has also yielded some stellar statistics. In fact, he bettered Manaea in ERA, as his 2.85 figure is 9th in the AL, while he matched Manaea with a 0.96 WHIP. It’s nice that Oakland can depend on these two workhorses for quality starts, especially since the rotation as a whole has been prone to injury. As for the bullpen, Blake Treinen has assumed the role of closer ever since he was traded from the Washington Nationals last year. Although he struggled quite a bit in D.C., he has thrived as a hard-throwing reliever in Oakland thus far. Through 27 innings pitched in 2018, Treinen has accumulated an ERA of 1.00, and opponents are batting a mere .196 against him. Plus, he is tied for 4th in AL in saves, as he has converted on 12 out of 14 save opportunities. If Oakland can minimize any kind of regression from their current efforts, then they will give their offense a better chance to win games for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Oakland Athletics have overachieved in the first third of the 2018 season, we still have to remember there is a ton of baseball left to play. Major questions still loom over the Oakland pitching staff with respect to both health and consistency, and they need to get themselves together for Oakland to have a realistic shot at a wild card berth. We know the offense is pretty solid, but as they say, defense wins championships, so the A’s offensive firepower will be a moot point if the pitching unravels. But at this point, a fanbase that last experienced the playoffs in 2014 is glad that their team is giving them hope to believe that 2018 will be a successful season. Only time will tell if Oakland will clinch a playoff berth or wallow in the cellar of the competitive AL West.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;*Stats updated as of 5/29&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: athletics.mlb.com, Baseballprospectus.com, Baseball-reference.com, mlb.com/stats&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Veroulis</name></author><summary type="html">The Mercury News; from L to R, Matt Chapman, Matt Olson, and Marcus SemienAt the beginning of the 2018 MLB season, many experts thought the Oakland Athletics would once again sport one of the worst records in baseball. According to Baseball Prospectus, the Athletics were projected to have a 76-86 record this year, which would be a miniscule improvement from their 75-87 record last year. The oddsmakers at Bovada had even lower expectations for the squad, as the over/under for their win total was set at 74.5. Given that the team has been in the American League West cellar for three years straight, even the most optimistic A’s fans had to acknowledge that a playoff appearance might not be in order for at least a couple of years. So, you can’t really blame all the people who slept on the A’s going into the season, especially since Oakland didn’t do much over the offseason to improve themselves. But, the A’s have given their fans some hope with their impressive start to the season; after the first 54 games of the campaign, Oakland stands at 28-26, good for a .519 win percentage. People around the game might be surprised at this kind of run, but when looking at the roster makeup and the major statistics on both sides of the ball, one can better understand why the A’s are experiencing this kind of success.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does Defense Really Win Championships? An In-Depth Analysis of the NBA Playoffs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/defChamp" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does Defense Really Win Championships? An In-Depth Analysis of the NBA Playoffs" /><published>2018-05-22T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-22T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/defChamp</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/defChamp">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;2004 Pistons&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Jed Jacobsohn/Getty Images&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Introduction&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 2 minutes left on the clock, Richard Hamilton stepped up to the free throw line.  He dribbled the ball a few times and calmly knocked down both shots to seal one of the most stunning upsets in playoff history.  The Detroit Pistons had defeated the heavily favored Los Angeles Lakers to become the 2004 NBA Champions.  Hardly anyone could have predicted that this team would overcome the combined talents of Kobe Bryant and Shaquille O’Neal along with the brilliance of Phil Jackson.  Most analysts give credit to the outstanding defense the Pistons displayed.  Though their offense just placed 7th, this Pistons team had the best ranked defense throughout the playoffs and actually had the highest average defensive rating in postseason history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic1.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Top off/def teams&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;*Adjusted for Pace (Defensive rating is reversed scored)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was largely due in part because of their defensive stalwart Ben Wallace, who averaged 19.8 rebounds, 2.7 steals, and 3.4 blocks per 100 possessions.  Clearly, defense was a significant aspect of the playoffs that year, but since then, the game has started to trend in another direction.  Nowadays, there has been a resurgence in robust offenses as shown by both the 2017 Warriors and Cavaliers who contributed substantially to the recent spike in average offensive rating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;avg off/def per year&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even with this new style of fast-paced basketball taking over, can one say with certainty that a relentless offense is more valuable than a resilient defense?  Or even, is there a way to quantify the impact of defensive prowess versus offensive tenacity on a team’s postseason success?  Using comprehensive data from previous playoffs, we can explore all the possible answers to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Dataset&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this analysis, I scraped 32 seasons of playoff statistics (1986-2017) from basketball-reference.com giving me 512 instances of teams to work with.  The data used were the playoff averages of each statistic.  The reason I excluded the regular season is because playoff basketball creates a highly competitive atmosphere.  Each possession is much more valuable and players exert an exceptional level of effort when the season is on the line.  Also, the goal is to measure the components of a win within the scope of the playoffs so it would be erroneous to use regular season data which includes tanking teams and high variances in player performances due to injuries and suspensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After extracting the information, I created a database with all the necessary offensive and defensive variables that would be viable predictors of a team’s success.  I determined these based on the correlation coefficients between each variable and a team’s number of wins during their playoff run.  All statistically insignificant predictors were removed using t-tests for individual factors and likelihood-ratio tests for joint significance tests. This step is done to avoid removing relevant variables because of multicollinearity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The database is located in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Donaldvu18/Playoffproject&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;. The predictors are described in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/table1.png&quot; alt=&quot;variable descriptions&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;i&gt;Note that defensive rating, defensive FG %, and defensive FT/FGA are correlated inversely with predicted number of wins since they measure the opponent’s performance.  This means the lower the value, the better a team’s defensive ability.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Method&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective is to create a model that can predict the total amount of playoff wins a team will achieve based on their averages for the parameters mentioned above.  Note that the purpose of this model is not to predict whether a certain team will win the championship, but rather to see the trends associated with teams given their amount of wins and other variables.  From these estimates, we are able to see how deep a playoff team will go, but the intention is to see how much each offensive or defensive measure contributes to an overall win count.  This is better than just simply making an algorithm purely focused on win outcome because that would depend on matchups and countless other elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before creating the models, I standardized and centered each predictor due to the varying magnitudes from percentages and ratings.  Using forward and backwards stepwise regression, I generated the best model for each subset size based on the criteria of highest R-squared.  The R-squared value for each model represents how accurately the predictors can estimate the outcome, which in this case is total playoff wins.  Since we have eleven predictors, this produced eleven unique models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/table2.png&quot; alt=&quot;models&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step was to choose the optimal model out of all these options which means  finding the one with the lowest mean squared error.  The MSE will provide us with an idea of a model’s precision since it measures how much its predictions deviate from the true observations. To acquire these MSE values, I chose to employ cross-validation methods instead of traditional criterions such as AIC, BIC, or adjusted R-squared.  Cross validation is a more suitable approach since our sample size is relatively small (n=512) compared to the amount of predictors (k=11) which makes the error variance much harder to estimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I utilized a 10-folds cross validation which consists of dividing the dataset into ten groups, or folds, of equal sizes.  The first fold is chosen as the validation set while the rest of the data is used to fit the proposed model.  The fitted model is then tested on the first fold and we are able to find our first MSE value by comparing our estimates of each team’s total wins with the actual numbers.  We continue to do 10 iterations of this step with a different fold being designated as the validation set each time while all the other groups are used to train the model.  Then we average the ten MSE values acquired which gives us the overall MSE of that specific model.  This entire process is repeated for each subset size listed above which consequently allows us to narrow down our pool to a single quintessential model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Final Model&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/model1.png&quot; alt=&quot;model 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Results&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we have standardized and centered our predictor values, there are certain ways to interpret these numbers.  The intercept value represents the base number of wins that all teams start off with and then it will increase or decrease depending on the values of the parameters.  For example, keeping all else constant (fancy way of saying keep all other variables at their average value), for every increase in one standard deviation of a team’s offensive rating, the amount of predicted wins increases by 2.4010377.  Conversely, for every increase in one standard deviation of a team’s defensive rating, the amount of predicted wins decreases by -2.1930858 (remember that defensive rating is inversely correlated).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am just looking to compare the magnitude of offensive measures versus defensive ones, I will interpret the results in terms of standard deviation.  However, if you want to work with concrete numbers, you can find the mean and standard deviation of each predictor by referencing back to the excel database in my github.  The number of total wins remains unscaled so it can be construed normally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, our model gives the edge to the defensive side of the ball by incorporating five defensive components in its algorithm versus two offensive ones.  However, the strongest indicators are offensive and defensive rating with the former having the edge.  The correlation is illustrated in the graphic below where one can visualize the apparent trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Playoff Wins&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the results of the model dictate that all the various mechanics of a team’s defensive scheme play a pivotal role in achieving wins, while on the offensive side, the main factor is if your shots are falling through the net or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were four variables left out of the model as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Offensive rebound percentage&lt;/b&gt; - excluded from the model probably because there are not enough instances of it in a game to impact a team’s total wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Offensive FG/FTA&lt;/b&gt; - usually most teams do not have to rely on getting to the line often to achieve a win which could explain why offensive FG/FTA was left out of the equation.  However, if a team’s opponents are getting an abundance of calls from the referees, it can shift the game outcome which explains why defensive FG/FTA is used in the model still.  An example of this would be teams facing against James Harden who notoriously goes to the free throw line with high-frequency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Offensive Turnover Percentage&lt;/b&gt; - a possible explanation for this predictor being omitted from the model is that most playoff teams are usually skilled at taking care of the ball so the offensive turnover percentages may be similar across the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;3-Point Attempt Rate&lt;/b&gt; - when considering all the playoff teams, the amount of 3-pointers attempted do not differ greatly among them.  You might have a few exceptions like the recent Golden State Warriors and Houston Rockets but those are not enough to warrant the inclusion of the predictor in the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's take a glance at the predictive aspect of our model.  At first, it may seem like a prediction error of 2.887163 wins is fairly high.  But one has to consider that the model consist of handpicked predictors that would best showcase the influence of offensive and defensive traits.  Since the primary objective was to analyze these effects, other predictors that could have refined the algorithm’s prediction ability like a team’s seed or number of all-stars were excluded to reduce noise.  Having said that, our estimates are still in close vicinity to the actual number of wins. With the standard error being 2.887163 wins, it gives our estimates some breathing room while not forfeiting too much precision.  It also helps that the playoffs are set up in a best-of-seven format because this way, the better team will usually move on and have the opportunity to add to their win total thus lowering the variance.  This is in contrast to the NFL where each playoff round consists of a single game and can lead to highly unexpected results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the model heavily relies on the accuracy of its predictors, it may also use a bit of luck.  For example, it predicted that the 2015 Clippers would reach a total win count of seven in the playoffs.  Though the model was correct with that estimate, it is far-fetched to believe the algorithm could have anticipated that the Clippers would infamously collapse and blow a 3-1 lead against the Rockets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Residual Error&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The histogram above displays the distribution of our model’s residual error rounded to the nearest .5.  If the estimate was a negative number, I converted it to a zero which explains the spike around the 0 to 1 interval.  As depicted by the graph, a majority of the residual errors fall within the range of -3 to 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our model does have its weaknesses.  For example, consider the 2016 San Antonio Spurs who finished their season with a 67–15 record, their best winning percentage in franchise history.  With a roster comprised of decorated all-stars such as Tim Duncan, Tony Parker, Kawhi Leonard, and LaMarcus Aldridge, this Spurs team was expected to compete head-to-head with the defending champion Warriors.  When we plug their average statistics into the model, the Spurs are predicted to have 11.78863 wins which is equivalent to reaching the championship finals.  However, they were defeated in the conference semifinals by the OKC Thunder led by spectacular performances from future MVP Russell Westbrook and scoring champion Kevin Durant.  The Spurs ended up with a total of 6 wins which deviates substantially from our estimate when you consider the model’s error range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, our algorithm runs into problems when players perform well above their expectations or below them, but it is difficult to foresee these anomalies since each game is treated as an independent event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though these results do provide some insight into our research question, we can make things a bit more interesting.  Instead of generalizing our models to the entire postseason, lets customize our model on a round-to-round basis.  Since each playoff round is based on seedings, this will produce higher skilled matchups in the later stages which may lead to unique insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Further Methods&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the same methods from before, but instead of sampling the entire pool of playoff teams, I only used the teams that advanced into the next round to compute the respective model.  I decided to skip the initial round just because of the high variation of statistics due to one-sided matchups (1st vs 8th seed, 2nd vs 7th, etc…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Further Findings&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conference Semifinals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Celtics Sixers&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;YONG KIM / File Photograph&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/model2.png&quot; alt=&quot;model 2&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this model, I sampled all the playoff teams that made it into their conference semifinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yikes.  Only three predictors remain out of the eleven that were available.  Offensive and defensive ratings continue to have a profound impact on wins as expected, but offensive FG was the only other variable to be included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;FG conf semis&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As illustrated above, there is a strong correlation between field goal percentage and a team’s playoff run. Overall, this model confirms the importance of a team’s shot selection but does not give us too much to interpret other than that which may be due to the numerous one-sided matchups that are still skewing the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conference Finals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Harden&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Image via Air Alamo&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/model3.png&quot; alt=&quot;model 3&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This model will help identify what factors assist teams in the conference finals advance to the championship finals.  The sample size only includes teams that made it into their conference finals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all the defensive measures had a significant role in a team’s wins while only one offensive factor was deemed notable. Conference final matchups involve the top two teams within each conference battling it out and usually these lineups consist of superstars who can score at will. As a result, the different offensive factors are not as remarkable since teams will usually find a way to attain points.  However, defensive effort can vary for each team depending on the roster assembled and coach’s personal style. Defensive plays such as forcing a turnover or a clutch block can swing the outcome of a tightly contested game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, remember that in our overall model, offensive rating was the strongest predictors of wins.  However, defensive rating has now surpassed it by about .20 which is a sizable difference.  This further supports the notion that defensive grit is critical in these middle playoff rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;NBA Finals&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lebron vs. Steph&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Associated Press&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/model4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Model 4&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will help us choose what factors help teams move on from the finals to become the NBA champions.  Only teams that have gone to the finals were sampled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this model, we have the usual suspects but also a few surprises.  It makes sense that when the best two teams go head to head, whoever can defensively lock down their opponents will most likely get the win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is interesting to see that the 3-point attempt rate made the cut as a predictor in this model while other variables did not.  I believe this is because when a team is hustling and outplaying their opponents, they are producing more open looks which correlates with the amount of 3 pointers being taken.  In this case, the 3-point attempt rate would be a compelling indicator of which team is controlling the flow of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/defense/pic9.png&quot; alt=&quot;FG Finals&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there are other plausible explanations such as a team adopting an offensive strategy based on 3 pointers or individual sharpshooters having hot hands.  Also, note that offensive rating has reclaimed the top coefficient over defensive rating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on which playoff round it is, there are certain team attributes that are emphasized more than others.  However, for the most part, defensive abilities have the potential to make more of an overall impact on an outcome even though the amount of points scored is still usually the highest weighted determinant.  In the conference semifinals and conference finals, defensive potency is valued more than offensive power which demonstrates the strong leverage of defensive plays in the middle rounds.  For the finals , it does shift back to an offensive based model that takes the amount of 3 pointers attempted into consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though all these statistics and equations can tell you about the various aspects that go into winning a playoff game, it is not an absolute indicator of what a team should focus on.  The data used in this research goes back 32 seasons when a distinct style of basketball was being played and since then, the game has evolved immensely.  Also, there are factors that one cannot quantify or account for such as the greatness of Lebron James or Draymond Green’s ability to earn himself technicals.  Nevertheless, these models can still provide us insight on the offensive and defensive patterns associated with successful playoff teams.  In the end, these are just analytics and nothing will beat the good old-fashioned way of playing your heart out and leaving it all on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;i&gt;All analytics computed in R&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/br&gt;
    &lt;i&gt;Graphics produced in Tableau&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Don Vu</name></author><summary type="html">Jed Jacobsohn/Getty ImagesWith 2 minutes left on the clock, Richard Hamilton stepped up to the free throw line. He dribbled the ball a few times and calmly knocked down both shots to seal one of the most stunning upsets in playoff history. The Detroit Pistons had defeated the heavily favored Los Angeles Lakers to become the 2004 NBA Champions. Hardly anyone could have predicted that this team would overcome the combined talents of Kobe Bryant and Shaquille O’Neal along with the brilliance of Phil Jackson. Most analysts give credit to the outstanding defense the Pistons displayed. Though their offense just placed 7th, this Pistons team had the best ranked defense throughout the playoffs and actually had the highest average defensive rating in postseason history.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Has Alexander Zverev Failed to Deliver at Grand Slams?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/zverevGS" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Has Alexander Zverev Failed to Deliver at Grand Slams?" /><published>2018-05-09T00:00:20-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-09T00:00:20-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/zverevGS</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/zverevGS">&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;zverev backhand&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2004, the ATP “World Number 1” ranking in tennis has been controlled by four men. In fact, no one else has been able to even enter the top 2 over the last decade and a half. But all good things must come to an end. The Big Four are not getting any younger, and they cannot sustain this era of unparalleled dominance forever. So what’s next for men’s tennis? Who will take up the mantle of world number 1 after Federer, Nadal, Djokovic, and Murray can no longer play as they have? Look no further than Alexander “Sascha” Zverev Jr, the 21 year old German youngster who took the tennis world by storm this past year. Of all of the “Next Gen” players on tour, Zverev has made the most progress as he is currently ranked number 3 in the world. In 2017, at just 20 years old, he legitimized his potential for greatness when he finished the year at world number 4. Along the way, he captured 5 singles titles overall, including 2 Masters 1000 titles over Djokovic and Federer in each final, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a six-foot-six frame, excellent footwork and speed, fantastic mechanics, and an engaging personality, Zverev has everything it takes to be the face of the sport for many years to come. However, there is one glaring issue. Despite all of his success last year, he has been unable to make any kind of mark on the most prestigious part of the ATP world tour: Grand Slams. Having never made it past the 4th round of a major, he has given many people reason to doubt his capability of someday becoming the best player in the world. This article takes a closer look at his game and what to take away from this young man’s career thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Best of 3 Dominance&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic1.png&quot; alt=&quot;confetti&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In best of 3 matches (all matches not including Slams and Davis Cup) since the beginning of 2017, Zverev has been on cruise control. He has played in more tournaments than any other player on tour and had incredible success. The chart below shows the performance of 32 of the top ranked players in best of 3 matches, where the size of the bubbles represents how much above 1800 their average opponent’s elo rating is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic2.png&quot; alt=&quot;bubbles&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite playing more matches than anyone else, Zverev boasts a fantastic win percentage of 73.2%. He has also accomplished this against more difficult opposition, with his average opponent’s elo rating sitting at 2010.4 (his own elo being 2129.4 and the highest being 2380.1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zverev’s speed in best of 3 matches is also noteworthy. Since the beginning of 2017, no player in the current ATP top 10 has won more games per minute than he:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic3.png&quot; alt=&quot;games per minute&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only is he winning a lot against difficult opposition, but he is also winning games at the highest rate. The combination of his stellar consistency throughout the tour and the speed with which he wins games underscores how dominant he has been in all matches outside of Grand Slams on the tour. It is the reason why he has reached more rounds of 32, rounds of 16, quarter-finals, and semifinals than any other man since the beginning of 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Grand Slam Disappointment&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;break that racket&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not as if Zverev’s game falls off of a cliff the second he enters a Grand Slam; it’s just that he has never reached the quarterfinal of a Grand Slam, let alone won one. He has posted very similar in-game numbers in his Grand Slam matches as he has during the rest of the tour. There must be a reason, then, for his disproportionate lack of success in Slams. There are a few important differences in the spider chart below that can explain this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;spider chart&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Grand Slams, Zverev sees roughly 4 more break point opportunities than in his best of 3 set matches. Moreover, he saves 7% more break points faced in Slams at a clutch 69.7% clip. If he holds his serve this well and has more break point chances, then why is he consistently coming up short in these Grand Slam matches? One possible factor is a nearly 9% decrease in break points won, or in other words, a 9% increase in break point opportunities squandered. Fewer break point conversions entails much tighter sets and possibly longer matches. Coupled with a 5% decrease in tiebreaks won, Zverev’s wasted break point opportunities have proven to be costly. Consequently, he finds himself in more high-pressure situations with even smaller margins of error because losing a tiebreaker, which can literally come down to just one bad service point, can easily change the momentum of an entire match and be extremely demoralizing for the player who loses it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting indicator of his dip in form in Grand Slams is seen through 2 key ratios:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Points Dominance (% of return points won divided by % of service points lost)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Break Points Ratio (% of break points converted divided by % of faced break points lost)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic6.png&quot; alt=&quot;key ratios&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 2 ratios progressively decline and dip below tour average (1.00) as he advances to deeper stages of slams. However, in best-of-3 contests, his ratios stabilize and still remain well above the tour average as he goes further into the tournaments. Though one may argue that the quality of opposition likely increases in the later phases of a tournament, Zverev’s freefall in Grand Slams detracts from his consistency in all rounds of best-of-3 tournaments and accentuates his shortcomings on tennis’ brightest stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;Time is the Enemy...&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s clear that Zverev’s numbers drop in Grand Slams enough to derail his prospects of groundbreaking success so far in any of the four majors. But why? Our guess is fatigue and a lack of mental and physical endurance. The most obvious difference between a 3 set match and a 5 set match is the most important one for Zverev: match time. In 3 set matches, he spends 96 minutes on the court in wins and 99 in losses. Win or lose, he is on the court for a little more than an hour and a half. In Grand Slams, however, he spends 160 minutes on the court in wins and 202 minutes in losses. He tends to lose matches when they drag on past 3 hours. A lack of ability to perform well in very long matches strongly suggests a lack of the physical conditioning that is required to succeed at this level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More intriguingly, when a Grand Slam match is tied 1-1 in the set score, it essentially becomes a best of 3 match. Considering the fact that Zverev is a phenomenal 3 set player, he should be able to win most of his Slam matches when they go 1-1. But he doesn’t. Of his six Slam matches that have gone 1-1 through the first two sets, he has won a grand total of one. The only difference between this type of 3 set match and a normal 3 set match is the extra hour or so that Zverev has spent on the court. A match in a grand slam is a marathon and players need to manage their bodies to go the distance if necessary. Zverev does not yet have the ability to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic7.png&quot; alt=&quot;mad zverev&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking all of this into consideration, it’s not just a physical issue with Zverev. Here are the scores of the final set in Grand Slam matches that Zverev has lost:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic8.png&quot; alt=&quot;table&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except for his 4 set loss to Coric last year, he’s gotten annihilated in the final set of matches that he loses. This is demonstrative not only of exhaustion physically but also of a lack of mental toughness. It appears as though Zverev loses interest towards the later sets of matches that are not quite going his way and therefore ends up getting demolished in the final sets of losing efforts. It’s a combination of relatively poor endurance and a lack of mental discipline and concentration that cause his Grand Slam numbers to drop, denying him the opportunity to reach the second week of a Major.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;
	&lt;b&gt;But Time is Also a Friend&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;center&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;materialboxed responsive-img&quot; src =&quot;/assets/zverev/pic9.png&quot; alt=&quot;fist pump&quot;&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note through all of this that Alexander Zverev is still 21 years old. Although Grand Slam success continues to elude him, he is still the future of men’s tennis and is spearheading the Next Gen youth movement. The tour has not seen a player as young as Zverev dominate the way he has since the Big Four made their mark. At the moment, he may lack the necessary stamina for five set matches, but with more experience and gameplay, he can only become better. To put things into perspective, at 21 years of age, Rafael Nadal and Novak Djokovic certainly weren’t the unbreakable five-set marathoners that they are now. Roger Federer didn’t even crack the top 3 until a month before his 22nd birthday. Andy Murray didn’t win his first Grand Slam until he was 25. Time is on Zverev’s side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, there are virtually no weaknesses in Zverev’s game technique-wise. The dual-threat of the speed with which he wins games and covers the court for someone of his size is just one of many weapons in his burgeoning arsenal. His blistering groundstrokes are enough to blast his opponent off the court. His agile, towering 6’6” frame allows for impeccable precision of serve placement. One can only expect so much early on from a generational talent like Zverev, who has certainly not disappointed through his age-21 season so far, relative to other highly touted youngsters like Nick Kyrgios and Hyeon Chung. Zverev himself has admitted to suffering from mental issues during decisive moments at Slams, which gives us additional context for his fifth set meltdowns. He has all the right tools but simply doesn’t know how to put them altogether just yet. With a great ATP ranking comes great expectations, and it is up to Zverev to make the necessary adjustments to prove his doubters wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kevin Hahn</name></author><summary type="html">Since 2004, the ATP “World Number 1” ranking in tennis has been controlled by four men. In fact, no one else has been able to even enter the top 2 over the last decade and a half. But all good things must come to an end. The Big Four are not getting any younger, and they cannot sustain this era of unparalleled dominance forever. So what’s next for men’s tennis? Who will take up the mantle of world number 1 after Federer, Nadal, Djokovic, and Murray can no longer play as they have? Look no further than Alexander “Sascha” Zverev Jr, the 21 year old German youngster who took the tennis world by storm this past year. Of all of the “Next Gen” players on tour, Zverev has made the most progress as he is currently ranked number 3 in the world. In 2017, at just 20 years old, he legitimized his potential for greatness when he finished the year at world number 4. Along the way, he captured 5 singles titles overall, including 2 Masters 1000 titles over Djokovic and Federer in each final, respectively.</summary></entry></feed>